1 Corinthians

1
2
3
4
5
6
7
8
9
10

11
12
13
14
15
16

THE FIRST EPISTLE OF PAUL THE APOSTLE TO THE CORINTHIANS

1

1 Paul, called to be an apostle of Jesus Christ through the will of God, and Sosthenes our brother, 2 To the church of God which is at Corinth, to them that are sanctified in Christ Jesus, called to be saints, with all that in every place call upon the name of Jesus Christ our Lord, both theirs and ours. 3 Grace be to you, and peace from God our Father, and from the Lord Jesus Christ. 4 I thank my God always on your behalf, for the grace of God which is given you by Jesus Christ; 5 That in every thing ye are enriched by him, in all utterance, and in all knowledge; 6 Even as the testimony of Christ was confirmed in you: 7 So that ye come behind in no gift; waiting for the coming of our Lord Jesus Christ: 8 Who will also confirm you to the end, that ye may be blameless in the day of our Lord Jesus Christ. 9 God is faithful, by whom ye were called to the fellowship of his Son Jesus Christ our Lord. 10 Now I beseech you, brethren, by the name of our Lord Jesus Christ, that ye all speak the same thing, and that there be no divisions among you; but that ye be perfectly joined together in the same mind, and in the same judgment. 11 For it hath been declared to me concerning you, my brethren, by them who are of the house of Chloe, that there are contentions among you. 12 Now this I say, that every one of you saith, I am of Paul; and I of Apollos; and I of Cephas; and I of Christ. 13 Is Christ divided? was Paul crucified for you? or were ye baptized in the name of Paul? 14 I thank God that I baptized none of you, but Crispus and Gaius; 15 Lest any should say that I had baptized in my own name. 16 And I baptized also the household of Stephanas; besides, I know not whether I baptized any other. 17 For Christ hath not sent me to baptize, but to preach the gospel: not with wisdom of words, lest the cross of Christ should be made of no effect. 18 For the preaching of the cross is to them that perish, foolishness; but to us who are saved, it is the power of God. 19 For it is written, I will destroy the wisdom of the wise, and will bring to nothing the understanding of the prudent. 20 Where is the wise? where is the scribe? where is the disputer of this world? hath not God made foolish the wisdom of this world? 21 For when in the wisdom of God the world by wisdom knew not God, it pleased God by the foolishness of preaching to save them that believe. 22 For the Jews require a sign, and the Greeks seek wisdom: 23 But we preach Christ crucified, to the Jews a stumbling-block, and to the Greeks foolishness; 24 But to them who are called, both Jews and Greeks, Christ the power of God, and the wisdom of God. 25 Because the foolishness of God is wiser than men; and the weakness of God is stronger than men. 26 For ye see your calling, brethren, that not many wise men after the flesh, not many mighty, not many noble are called : 27 But God hath chosen the foolish things of the world to confound the wise; and God hath chosen the weak things of the world to confound the things which are mighty; 28 And base things of the world, and things which are despised, hath God chosen, and things which are not, to bring to naught things that are: 29 That no flesh should glory in his presence. 30 But of him are ye in Christ Jesus, who from God is made to us wisdom, and righteousness, and sanctification, and redemption: 31 That, according as it is written, He that glorieth, let him glory in the Lord.

2

1 And I, brethren, when I came to you, came not with excellence of speech, or of wisdom, declaring to you the testimony of God. 2 For I determined not to know any thing among you, save Jesus Christ, and him crucified. 3 And I was with you in weakness, and in fear, and in much trembling. 4 And my speech and my preaching was not with enticing words of man's wisdom, but in demonstration of the Spirit, and of power: 5 That your faith should not stand in the wisdom of men, but in the power of God. 6 However, we speak wisdom among them that are perfect: yet not the wisdom of this world, nor of the princes of this world, that come to naught: 7 But we speak the wisdom of God in a mystery, even the hidden wisdom which God ordained before the world to our glory: 8 Which none of the princes of this world knew: for had they known it , they would not have crucified the Lord of glory. 9 But as it is written, Eye hath not seen, nor ear heard, neither have entered into the heart of man, the things which God hath prepared for them that love him. 10 But God hath revealed them to us by his Spirit; for the Spirit searcheth all things, even the deep things of God. 11 For what man knoweth the things of a man, save the spirit of man which is in him? even so the things of God knoweth no man, but the Spirit of God. 12 Now we have received, not the spirit of the world, but the spirit which is from God; that we may know the things that are freely given to us by God. 13 Which things also we speak, not in the words which man's wisdom teacheth, but which the Holy Spirit teacheth; comparing spiritual things with spiritual. 14 But the natural man receiveth not the things of the Spirit of God: for they are foolishness to him: neither can he know them , because they are spiritually discerned. 15 But he that is spiritual judgeth all things, yet he himself is judged by no man. 16 For who hath known the mind of the Lord, that he may instruct him? But we have the mind of Christ.

3

1 And I, brethren, could not speak to you as to spiritual, but as to carnal, even as to babes in Christ. 2 I have fed you with milk, and not with meat: for hitherto ye were not able to bear it , neither yet now are ye able. 3 For ye are yet carnal: for whereas there is among you envying, and strife, and divisions, are ye not carnal, and walk as men? 4 For while one saith, I am of Paul; and another, I am of Apollos; are ye not carnal? 5 Who then is Paul, and who is Apollos, but ministers by whom ye believed, even as the Lord gave to every man? 6 I have planted, Apollos watered: but God hath given the increase. 7 So then, neither is he that planteth any thing, neither he that watereth: but God that giveth the increase. 8 Now he that planteth and he that watereth are one: and every man shall receive his own reward, according to his own labor. 9 For we are laborers together with God: ye are God's husbandry, ye are God's building. 10 According to the grace of God which is given to me, as a wise master-builder, I have laid the foundation, and another buildeth upon it. But let every man take heed how he buildeth upon it. 11 For other foundation can no man lay than that which is laid, which is Jesus Christ. 12 Now if any man buildeth upon this foundation, gold, silver, precious stones, wood, hay, stubble; 13 Every man's work will be made manifest: for the day will declare it, because it will be revealed by fire; and the fire will try every man's work, of what sort it is. 14 If any man's work abideth which he hath built upon it, he shall receive a reward. 15 If any man's work shall be burned, he will suffer loss: but he himself shall be saved; yet so as by fire. 16 Know ye not that ye are the temple of God, and that the Spirit of God dwelleth in you? 17 If any man defileth the temple of God, him will God destroy: for the temple of God is holy, which temple ye are. 18 Let no man deceive himself. If any man among you seemeth to be wise in this world, let him become a fool, that he may be wise. 19 For the wisdom of this world is foolishness with God. For it is written, He taketh the wise in their own craftiness. 20 And again, The Lord knoweth the thoughts of the wise, that they are vain. 21 Therefore let no man glory in men: for all things are yours: 22 Whether Paul, or Apollos, or Cephas, or the world, or life, or death, or things present, or things to come; all are yours; 23 And ye are Christ's; and Christ is God's.

4

1 Let a man so account of us, as of the ministers of Christ, and stewards of the mysteries of God. 2 Moreover, it is required in stewards that a man be found faithful. 3 But with me it is a very small thing that I should be judged by you, or by man's judgment: yes, I judge not my own self. 4 For I know nothing against myself; yet am I not hereby justified: but he that judgeth me is the Lord. 5 Therefore judge nothing before the time, until the Lord shall come, who will both bring to light the hidden things of darkness, and will make manifest the counsels of the hearts: and then shall every man have praise from God. 6 And these things, brethren, I have in a figure transferred to myself, and to Apollos, for your sakes; that ye may learn in us not to think of men above that which is written, that no one of you on account of one, may be puffed up against another. 7 For who maketh thee to differ from another ? and what hast thou that thou didst not receive? now if thou didst receive it , why dost thou glory, as if thou hadst not received it ? 8 Now ye are full, now ye are rich, ye have reigned as kings without us: and I wish ye did reign, that we also might reign with you. 9 For I think that God hath set forth us the apostles last, as it were appointed to death: for we are made a spectacle to the world, and to angels, and to men. 10 We are fools for Christ's sake, but ye are wise in Christ; we are weak, but ye are strong; ye are honorable, but we are despised. 11 Even to this present hour we both hunger, and thirst, and are naked, and are buffeted, and have no certain dwelling-place; 12 And labor, working with our own hands. Being reviled, we bless; being persecuted, we suffer it; 13 Being defamed, we entreat: we are made as the filth of the world, the offscouring of all things to this day. 14 I write not these things to shame you, but as my beloved sons I warn you . 15 For though ye have ten thousand instructors in Christ, yet have ye not many fathers: for in Christ Jesus I have begotten you through the gospel. 16 Wherefore I beseech you, be ye followers of me. 17 For this cause have I sent to you Timothy, who is my beloved son, and faithful in the Lord, who will bring you into remembrance of my ways which are in Christ, as I teach every where in every church. 18 Now some are puffed up, as though I would not come to you. 19 But I will come to you shortly, if the Lord will, and will know, not the speech of them who are puffed up, but the power. 20 For the kingdom of God is not in word, but in power. 21 What will ye? shall I come to you with a rod, or in love, and in the spirit of meekness?

5

1 It is reported commonly that there is lewdness among you, and such lewdness as is not so much as named among the Gentiles, that one should have his father's wife. 2 And ye are puffed up, and have not rather mourned, that he who hath done this deed might be taken away from among you. 3 For I verily, as absent in body, but present in spirit, have judged already as though I were present, concerning him that hath so done this deed, 4 In the name of our Lord Jesus Christ, when ye are assembled, and my spirit, with the power of our Lord Jesus Christ, 5 To deliver such one to Satan for the destruction of the flesh, that the spirit may be saved in the day of the Lord Jesus. 6 Your boasting is not good. Know ye not, that a little leaven leaveneth the whole lump? 7 Cleanse out therefore the old leaven, that ye may be a new lump, as ye are unleavened. For even Christ our passover is sacrificed for us: 8 Therefore let us keep the feast, not with old leaven, neither with the leaven of malice and wickedness; but with the unleavened bread of sincerity and truth. 9 I have written to you in this epistle, not to associate with persons guilty of lewdness: 10 Yet not altogether with lewd persons of this world, or with the covetous, or extortioners, or with idolaters: for then ye must needs go out of the world. 11 But now I have written to you not to keep company, if any man that is called a brother is a lewd person, or covetous, or an idolater, or a railer, or a drunkard, or an extortioner: with such person no not to eat. 12 For what have I to do to judge them also that are without? do ye not judge them that are within? 13 But them that are without God judgeth. Therefore put away from among yourselves that wicked person.

6

1 Dare any of you, having a matter against another, go to law before the unjust, and not before the saints? 2 Do ye not know that the saints will judge the world? and if the world shall be judged by you, are ye unworthy to judge the smallest matters? 3 Know ye not that we shall judge angels? how much more, things that pertain to this life? 4 If then ye have judgments of things pertaining to this life, set them to judge who are least esteemed in the church. 5 I speak to your shame. Is it so, that there is not a wise man among you? no, not one that will be able to judge between his brethren? 6 But brother goeth to law with brother, and that before unbelievers. 7 Now therefore there is utterly a fault among you, because ye go to law one with another. Why do ye not rather take wrong? why do ye not rather suffer yourselves to be defrauded? 8 But ye do wrong, and defraud, and that your brethren. 9 Know ye not that the unrighteous shall not inherit the kingdom of God? Be not deceived; neither fornicators, nor idolaters, nor adulterers, nor effeminate, nor abusers of themselves with mankind, 10 Nor thieves, nor covetous, nor drunkards, nor revilers, nor extortioners, shall inherit the kingdom of God. 11 And such were some of you: but ye are washed, but ye are sanctified, but ye are justified in the name of the Lord Jesus, and by the Spirit of our God. 12 All things are lawful to me, but all things are not helpful: all things are lawful for me, but I will not be brought under the power of any. 13 Meats for the belly, and the belly for meats: but God will destroy both it and them. Now the body is not for lewdness, but for the Lord; and the Lord for the body. 14 And God hath both raised up the Lord, and will also raise up us by his own power. 15 Know ye not, that your bodies are the members of Christ? shall I then take the members of Christ, and make them the members of a harlot? By no means. 16 What? know ye not that he who is joined to a harlot is one body? for two, saith he, shall be one flesh. 17 But he that is joined to the Lord is one spirit. 18 Flee lewdness. Every sin that a man doeth, is without the body; but he that committeth lewdness, sinneth against his own body. 19 What, know ye not that your body is the temple of the Holy Spirit which is in you, which ye have from God, and ye are not your own? 20 For ye are bought with a price: therefore glorify God in your body, and in your spirit, which are God's.

7

1 Now concerning the things of which ye wrote to me: It is good for a man not to touch a woman. 2 Nevertheless, to avoid lewdness, let every man have his own wife, and let every woman have her own husband. 3 Let the husband render to the wife due benevolence: and likewise also the wife to the husband. 4 The wife hath not power of her own body, but the husband: and likewise also the husband hath not power of his own body, but the wife. 5 Defraud ye not one the other, except with consent for a time, that ye may give yourselves to fasting and prayer; and come together again, that Satan may not tempt you for your incontinence. 6 But I speak this by permission, and not as a commandment. 7 For I would that all men were as I myself. But every man hath his proper gift from God, one after this manner, and another after that. 8 I say therefore to the unmarried and widows, It is good for them if they remain even as I. 9 But if they cannot contain, let them marry: for it is better to marry than to burn. 10 And to the married I command, yet not I, but the Lord, Let not the wife depart from her husband: 11 But if she shall depart, let her remain unmarried, or be reconciled to her husband: and let not the husband put away his wife. 12 But to the rest I speak, not the Lord, if any brother hath a wife that believeth not, and she is pleased to dwell with him, let him not put her away. 13 And the woman who hath a husband that believeth not, and if he is pleased to dwell with her, let her not leave him. 14 For the unbelieving husband is sanctified by the wife, and the unbelieving wife is sanctified by the husband: else were your children unclean; but now are they holy. 15 But if the unbelieving departeth, let him depart. A brother or a sister is not under bondage in such cases ; but God hath called us to peace. 16 For how knowest thou, O wife, whether thou shalt save thy husband? or how knowest thou, O man, whether thou shalt save thy wife? 17 But as God hath distributed to every man, as the Lord hath called every one, so let him walk. And so I ordain in all churches. 18 Is any man called being circumcised? let him not become uncircumcised. Is any called in uncircumcision? let him not become circumcised. 19 Circumcision is nothing, and uncircumcision is nothing, but the keeping of the commandments of God. 20 Let every man continue in the same calling in which he was called. 21 Art thou called being a servant? care not for it; but if thou mayest be made free, use it rather. 22 For he that is called in the Lord, being a servant, is the Lord's free-man: likewise also he that is called, being free, is Christ's servant. 23 Ye are bought with a price; be not ye the servants of men. 24 Brethren, let every man in the state in which he is called, continue in it with God. 25 Now concerning virgins, I have no commandment of the Lord: yet I give my judgment as one that hath obtained mercy from the Lord to be faithful. 26 I suppose therefore that this is good for the present distress, I say , that it is good for a man so to be. 27 Art thou bound to a wife? seek not to be loosed. Art thou loosed from a wife? seek not a wife. 28 But if thou marry, thou hast not sinned: and if a virgin marry, she hath not sinned. Nevertheless, such will have trouble in the flesh; but I spare you. 29 But this I say, brethren, The time is short. It remaineth, that both they that have wives, be as though they had none; 30 And they that weep, as though they wept not; and they that rejoice, as though they rejoiced not; and they that buy, as though they possessed not; 31 And they that use this world, as not abusing it . For the fashion of this world passeth away. 32 But I would have you without anxious care. He that is unmarried, is anxious for the things that belong to the Lord, how he may please the Lord: 33 But he that is married, is anxious for the things that are of the world, how he may please his wife. 34 There is a difference also between a wife and a virgin. The unmarried woman is anxious for the things of the Lord, that she may be holy, both in body and in spirit: but she that is married, is anxious for the things of the world, how she may please her husband. 35 And this I speak for your own profit; not that I may cast a snare upon you, but for that which is comely, and that ye may attend upon the Lord without distraction. 36 But if any man thinketh that he behaveth himself uncomely towards his virgin, if she hath passed the flower of her age, and need so requireth, let him do what he will, he sinneth not: let them marry. 37 Nevertheless, he that standeth steadfast in his heart, having no necessity, but hath power over his own will, and hath so decreed in his heart that he will keep his virgin, doeth well. 38 So then he that giveth her in marriage doeth well; but he that giveth her not in marriage doeth better. 39 The wife is bound by the law as long as her husband liveth; but if her husband is dead, she is at liberty to be married to whom she will; only in the Lord. 40 But she is happier if she so remain, after my judgment; and I think also that I have the Spirit of God.

8

1 Now as concerning things offered to idols, we know that we all have knowledge. Knowledge puffeth up, but love edifieth. 2 And if any man thinketh that he knoweth any thing, he knoweth nothing yet as he ought to know. 3 But if any man loveth God, the same is known by him. 4 Therefore as concerning the eating of those things that are offered in sacrifice to idols, we know that an idol is nothing in the world, and that there is no other God but one. 5 For though there are that are called gods, whether in heaven or upon earth, (as there are gods many, and lords many) 6 Yet to us there is but one God, the Father, from whom are all things, and we in him; and one Lord Jesus Christ, by whom are all things, and we by him. 7 But there is not in every man that knowledge: for some with conscience of the idol to this hour eat it as a thing offered to an idol; and their conscience, being weak, is defiled. 8 But food commendeth us not to God: for neither if we eat, are we the better; neither if we eat not, are we the worse. 9 But take heed lest by any means this liberty of yours should become a stumbling-block to them that are weak. 10 For if any man shall see thee, who hast knowledge, sit eating in the idol's temple, will not the conscience of him who is weak be emboldened to eat those things which are offered to idols; 11 And through thy knowledge shall the weak brother perish, for whom Christ died? 12 But when ye thus sin against the brethren, and wound their weak conscience, ye sin against Christ. 13 Wherefore, if food maketh my brother to fall into sin, I will eat no flesh while the world standeth, lest I make my brother to fall into sin.

9

1 Am I not an apostle? am I not free? have I not seen Jesus Christ our Lord? are ye not my work in the Lord? 2 If I am not an apostle to others, yet doubtless I am to you: for ye are the seal of my apostleship in the Lord. 3 My answer to them that examine me is this, 4 Have we not power to eat and to drink? 5 Have we not power to lead about a sister, a wife, as well as other apostles, and as the brethren of the Lord, and Cephas? 6 Or I only and Barnabas, have we not power to forbear working? 7 Who goeth a warfare at any time at his own charges? who planteth a vineyard, and eateth not of its fruit? or who feedeth a flock, and eateth not of the milk of the flock? 8 Do I say these things as a man? or saith not the law the same also? 9 For it is written in the law of Moses, Thou shalt not muzzle the mouth of the ox that treadeth out the grain. Doth God take care for oxen? 10 Or saith he this altogether for our sakes? for our sakes, no doubt, this is written: that he that ploweth should plow in hope; and that he that thresheth in hope should be partaker of his hope. 11 If we have sown to you spiritual things, is it a great thing if we shall reap your carnal things? 12 If others are partakers of this power over you, are not we rather? Nevertheless we have not used this power; but suffer all things, lest we should hinder the gospel of Christ. 13 Do ye not know that they who minister about holy things live from the things of the temple, and they who wait at the altar are partakers with the altar? 14 Even so hath the Lord ordained that they who preach the gospel should live by the gospel. 15 But I have used none of these things: neither have I written these things, that it should be so done to me: for it were better for me to die, than that any man should make my glorying void. 16 For though I preach the gospel, I have nothing to boast of: for necessity is laid upon me; and woe is to me, if I preach not the gospel! 17 For if I do this thing willingly, I have a reward: but if against my will, a dispensation of the gospel is committed to me. 18 What is my reward then? Verily that, when I preach the gospel, I may make the gospel of Christ without charge, that I may not abuse my power in the gospel. 19 For though I am free from all men , yet I have made myself servant to all, that I might gain the more. 20 And to the Jews I became as a Jew, that I might gain the Jews; to them that are under the law, as under the law, that I might gain them that are under the law; 21 To them that are without law, as without law, (being not without law to God, but under the law to Christ,) that I might gain them that are without law. 22 To the weak I became as weak, that I might gain the weak: I have become all things to all men , that I might by all means save some. 23 And this I do for the gospel's sake, that I may be partaker of it with you . 24 Know ye not, that they who run in a race, all run, but one receiveth the prize? So run, that ye may obtain. 25 And every man that striveth for the mastery is temperate in all things. Now they do it to obtain a corruptible crown; but we an incorruptible. 26 I therefore so run, not as uncertainly; so I fight, not as one that beateth the air: 27 But I keep under my body, and bring it into subjection: lest by any means when I have preached to others, I myself should be a cast-away.

10

1 Moreover, brethren, I would not that ye should be ignorant, that all our fathers were under the cloud, and all passed through the sea; 2 And were all baptized to Moses in the cloud and in the sea; 3 And all ate the same spiritual food; 4 And all drank the same spiritual drink: (for they drank of that spiritual Rock that followed them: and that Rock was Christ.) 5 But with many of them God was not well pleased: for they were overthrown in the wilderness. 6 Now these things were our examples, to the intent we should not lust after evil things, as they also lusted. 7 Neither be ye idolaters, as were some of them: as it is written, The people sat down to eat and drink, and rose up to play. 8 Neither let us commit lewdness, as some of them committed, and fell in one day three and twenty thousand. 9 Neither let us tempt Christ, as some of them also tempted, and were destroyed by serpents. 10 Neither murmur ye, as some of them also murmured, and were destroyed by the destroyer. 11 Now all these things happened to them for examples: and they are written for our admonition, upon whom the ends of the world are come. 12 Wherefore let him that thinketh he standeth, take heed lest he fall. 13 There hath no temptation taken you but such as is common to man: but God is faithful, who will not suffer you to be tempted above what ye are able; but will with the temptation also make a way to escape, that ye may be able to bear it . 14 Wherefore, my dearly beloved, flee from idolatry. 15 I speak as to wise men; judge ye what I say. 16 The cup of blessing which we bless, is it not the communion of the blood of Christ? The bread which we break, is it not the communion of the body of Christ? 17 For we being many are one bread, and one body: for we are all partakers of that one bread. 18 Behold Israel after the flesh: are not they who eat of the sacrifices, partakers of the altar? 19 What then do I say? that the idol is any thing, or that which is offered in sacrifice to idols is any thing? 20 But I say , that the things which the Gentiles sacrifice, they sacrifice to demons, and not to God: and I would not that ye should have fellowship with demons. 21 Ye cannot drink the cup of the Lord, and the cup of demons: ye cannot be partakers of the Lord's table, and of the table of demons. 22 Do we provoke the Lord to jealousy? are we stronger than he? 23 All things are lawful for me, but all things are not helpful: all things are lawful for me, but all things edify not. 24 Let no man seek his own, but every man another's wealth . 25 Whatever is sold in the provision market, that eat, asking no question for conscience' sake: 26 For the earth is the Lord's, and its fullness. 27 If any of them that believe not invites you to a feast , and ye are disposed to go; whatever is set before you, eat, asking no question on account of conscience. 28 But if any man shall say to you, This is offered in sacrifice to idols, eat not for his sake that showed it, and for conscience' sake: for the earth is the Lord's, and its fullness: 29 Conscience, I say, not thy own, but of the other: for why is my liberty judged by another man's conscience? 30 For if I by grace am a partaker, why am I evil spoken of for that for which I give thanks? 31 Whether therefore ye eat or drink, or whatever ye do, do all to the glory of God. 32 Give no offense, neither to the Jews, nor to the Gentiles, nor to the church of God: 33 Even as I please all men in all things , not seeking my own profit, but the profit of many, that they may be saved.

11

1 Be ye followers of me, even as I also am of Christ. 2 Now I praise you, brethren, that ye remember me in all things, and keep the ordinances, as I delivered them to you. 3 But I would have you know, that the head of every man is Christ; and the head of the woman is the man; and the head of Christ is God. 4 Every man praying or prophesying, having his head covered, dishonoreth his head. 5 But every woman that prayeth or prophesieth with her head uncovered, dishonoreth her head: for that is even all one as if she were shaved. 6 For if the woman is not covered, let her also be shorn: but if it is a shame for a woman to be shorn or shaved, let her be covered. 7 For a man indeed ought not to cover his head, forasmuch as he is the image and glory of God: but the woman is the glory of the man. 8 For the man is not from the woman, but the woman from the man. 9 Neither was the man created for the woman, but the woman for the man. 10 For this cause ought the woman to have power on her head, because of the angels. 11 Nevertheless, neither is the man without the woman, neither the woman without the man in the Lord. 12 For as the woman is from the man, even so is the man also by the woman; but all things from God. 13 Judge in yourselves: Is it comely that a woman should pray to God uncovered? 14 Doth not even nature itself teach you, that if a man hath long hair, it is a shame to him? 15 But if a woman hath long hair, it is a glory to her: for her hair is given her for a covering. 16 But if any man seemeth to be contentious, we have no such custom, neither the churches of God. 17 Now in this that I declare to you , I praise you not, that ye come together not for the better, but for the worse. 18 For first of all, when ye come together in the church, I hear that there are divisions among you; and I partly believe it. 19 For there must be also heresies among you, that they who are approved may be made manifest among you. 20 When therefore ye come together in one place, this is not to eat the Lord's supper. 21 For in eating every one taketh before another his own supper: and one is hungry, and another is drunken. 22 What? have ye not houses to eat and to drink in? or despise ye the church of God, and shame them that have not? What shall I say to you? shall I praise you in this? I praise you not. 23 For I have received from the Lord, that which also I delivered to you, That the Lord Jesus, the same night in which he was betrayed, took bread: 24 And when he had given thanks, he broke it , and said, Take, eat: this is my body, which is broken for you: this do in remembrance of me. 25 After the same manner also he took the cup, when he had supped, saying, This cup is the new testament in my blood: this do ye, as often as ye drink it , in remembrance of me. 26 For as often as ye eat this bread, and drink this cup, ye do show the Lord's death till he shall come. 27 Wherefore, whoever shall eat this bread, and drink this cup of the Lord unworthily, shall be guilty of the body and blood of the Lord. 28 But let a man examine himself, and so let him eat of that bread, and drink of that cup. 29 For he that eateth and drinketh unworthily, eateth and drinketh condemnation to himself, not discerning the Lord's body. 30 For this cause many are weak and sickly among you, and many sleep. 31 For if we would judge ourselves, we should not be judged. 32 But when we are judged, we are chastened by the Lord, that we should not be condemned with the world. 33 Wherefore, my brethren, when ye come together to eat, tarry one for another. 34 And if any man hungereth, let him eat at home; that ye come not together to condemnation. And the rest will I set in order when I come.

12

1 Now concerning spiritual gifts , brethren, I would not have you ignorant. 2 Ye know that ye were Gentiles, carried away to these mute idols, even as ye were led. 3 Wherefore I give you to understand, that no man speaking by the Spirit of God, calleth Jesus accursed: and that no man can say that Jesus is the Lord, but by the Holy Spirit. 4 Now there are diversities of gifts, but the same Spirit. 5 And there are differences of administrations, but the same Lord. 6 And there are diversities of operations, but it is the same God who worketh all in all. 7 But the manifestation of the Spirit is given to every man for profit. 8 For to one is given by the Spirit the word of wisdom; to another, the word of knowledge by the same Spirit; 9 To another, faith by the same Spirit; to another, the gifts of healing by the same Spirit; 10 To another, the working of miracles; to another, prophecy; to another, discerning of spirits; to another, divers kinds of languages; to another, the interpretation of languages: 11 But all these worketh that one and the same Spirit, dividing to every man severally as he will. 12 For as the body is one, and hath many members, and all the members of that one body, being many, are one body: so also is Christ. 13 For by one Spirit are we all baptized into one body, whether Jews or Gentiles, whether bond or free; and have been all made to drink into one Spirit. 14 For the body is not one member, but many. 15 If the foot shall say, Because I am not the hand, I am not of the body; is it therefore not of the body? 16 And if the ear shall say, Because I am not the eye, I am not of the body; is it therefore not of the body? 17 If the whole body were an eye, where were the hearing? If the whole were hearing, where were the smelling? 18 But now hath God set the members every one of them in the body, as it hath pleased him. 19 And if they were all one member, where were the body? 20 But now are they many members, yet but one body. 21 And the eye cannot say to the hand, I have no need of thee: nor again the head to the feet, I have no need of you. 22 Nay, much more those members of the body, which seem to be more feeble, are necessary: 23 And those members of the body, which we think to be less honorable, upon these we bestow more abundant honor; and our uncomely parts have more abundant comeliness. 24 For our comely parts have no need: but God hath tempered the body together, having given more abundant honor to that part which lacked: 25 That there should be no schism in the body; but that the members should have the same care one for another. 26 And thus if one member suffers all the members suffer with it; or, if one member is honored, all the members rejoice with it. 27 Now ye are the body of Christ, and members in particular. 28 And God hath set some in the church, first apostles, secondly prophets, thirdly teachers, next miracles, then gifts of healings, helps, governments, diversities of languages. 29 Are all apostles? are all prophets? are all teachers? are all workers of miracles? 30 Have all the gifts of healing? do all speak in languages? do all interpret? 31 But covet earnestly the best gifts. And yet I show to you a more excellent way.

13

1 Though I speak with the tongues of men and of angels, and have not love, I am become as sounding brass, or a tinkling cymbal. 2 And though I have the gift of prophecy, and understand all mysteries, and all knowledge; and though I have all faith, so that I could remove mountains, and have not love, I am nothing. 3 And though I bestow all my goods to feed the poor , and though I give my body to be burned, and have not love, it profiteth me nothing. 4 love suffereth long, and is kind; love envieth not; love vaunteth not itself, is not puffed up, 5 Doth not behave itself unseemly, seeketh not its own, is not easily provoked, thinketh no evil; 6 Rejoiceth not in iniquity, but rejoiceth in the truth; 7 Beareth all things, believeth all things, hopeth all things, endureth all things. 8 Love never faileth: but whether there are prophecies, they shall fail; whether there are languages, they shall cease; whether there is knowledge, it shall vanish away. 9 For we know in part, and we prophesy in part. 10 But when that which is perfect is come, then that which is in part shall be done away. 11 When I was a child, I spoke as a child, I understood as a child, I thought as a child: but when I became a man, I put away childish things. 12 For now we see through a glass darkly; but then face to face: now I know in part; but then shall I know even as also I am known. 13 And now abideth faith, hope, love, these three; but the greatest of these is love.

14

1 Follow after love, and desire spiritual gifts , but rather that ye may prophesy. 2 For he that speaketh in an unknown language, speaketh not to men, but to God: for no man understandeth him ; yet in the spirit he speaketh mysteries. 3 But he that prophesieth, speaketh to men to edification, and exhortation, and comfort. 4 He that speaketh in an unknown language edifieth himself; but he that prophesieth edifieth the church. 5 I would that ye all spoke in languages, but rather that ye prophesied: for greater is he that prophesieth than he that speaketh in languages, except he interpret, that the church may receive edifying. 6 Now, brethren, if I come to you speaking in languages, what shall I profit you, except I shall speak to you either by revelation, or by knowledge, or by prophesying, or by doctrine? 7 And even things without life giving sound, whether pipe or harp, except they give a distinction in the sounds, how shall it be known what is piped or harped? 8 For if the trumpet shall give an uncertain sound, who will prepare himself for battle? 9 So likewise ye, except ye utter by the tongue words easy to be understood, how shall it be known what is spoken? for ye will speak into the air. 10 There are, it may be, so many kinds of voices in the world, and none of them is without signification. 11 Therefore, if I know not the meaning of the voice, I shall be to him that speaketh a barbarian, and he that speaketh will be a barbarian to me. 12 Even so ye, forasmuch as ye are zealous of spiritual gifts , seek that ye may excel to the edifying of the church. 13 Wherefore, let him that speaketh in an unknown language, pray that he may interpret. 14 For if I pray in an unknown language, my spirit prayeth, but my understanding is unfruitful. 15 What is it then? I will pray with the spirit, and I will pray with the understanding also: I will sing with the spirit, and I will sing with the understanding also. 16 Else, when thou shalt bless with the spirit, how shall he that occupieth the room of the unlearned say Amen at thy giving of thanks, seeing he understandeth not what thou sayest? 17 For thou verily givest thanks well, but the other is not edified. 18 I thank my God, I speak in languages more than ye all: 19 Yet in the church I had rather speak five words with my understanding, that by my voice I may teach others also, than ten thousand words in an unknown language. 20 Brethren, be not children in understanding: yet in malice be ye children, but in understanding be men. 21 In the law it is written, With men of other tongues and other lips will I speak to this people; and yet for all that will they not hear me, saith the Lord. 22 Wherefore languages are for a sign, not to them that believe, but to them that believe not: but prophesying serveth not for them that believe not, but for them who believe. 23 If therefore the whole church is assembled in one place, and all speak in languages, and there come in those that are unlearned, or unbelievers, will they not say that ye are insane? 24 But if all prophesy, and there come in one that believeth not, or one unlearned, he is convinced by all, he is judged by all: 25 And thus are the secrets of his heart made manifest; and so falling down on his face, he will worship God, and report that God is in you in truth. 26 How is it then, brethren? when ye are assembled, every one of you hath a psalm, hath a doctrine, hath a language, hath a revelation, hath an interpretation. Let all things be done to edification. 27 If any man speaketh in an unknown language, let it be by two, or at the most by three, and that by course; and let one interpret. 28 But if there is no interpreter, let him keep silence in the church; and let him speak to himself, and to God. 29 Let the prophets speak two or three, and let the others judge. 30 If any thing is revealed to another that sitteth by, let the first hold his peace. 31 For ye may all prophesy one by one, that all may learn, and all may be comforted. 32 And the spirits of the prophets are subject to the prophets. 33 For God is not the author of confusion, but of peace, as in all churches of the saints. 34 Let your women keep silence in the churches; for it is not permitted to them to speak: but they are commanded to be under obedience, as also saith the law. 35 And if they will learn any thing, let them ask their husbands at home; for it is a shame for women to speak in the church. 36 What? came the word of God out from you? or came it to you only? 37 If any man thinketh himself to be a prophet, or spiritual, let him acknowledge that the things that I write to you are the commandments of the Lord. 38 But if any man is ignorant, let him be ignorant. 39 Wherefore, brethren, covet to prophesy, and forbid not to speak in languages. 40 Let all things be done decently, and in order.

15

1 Moreover, brethren, I declare to you the gospel which I preached to you, which also ye have received, and in which ye stand; 2 By which also ye are saved, if ye keep in memory what I preached to you, unless ye have believed in vain. 3 For I delivered to you first of all, that which I also received, that Christ died for our sins, according to the scriptures; 4 And that he was buried, and that he rose again the third day according to the scriptures: 5 And that he was seen by Cephas, then by the twelve: 6 After that he was seen by above five hundred brethren at once; of whom the greater part remain to this present, but some have fallen asleep. 7 After that he was seen by James; then by all the apostles. 8 And last of all he was seen by me also, as by one born out of due time. 9 For I am the least of the apostles, who am not worthy to be called an apostle, because I persecuted the church of God. 10 But by the grace of God I am what I am: and his grace which was bestowed upon me, was not in vain; but I labored more abundantly than they all: yet not I, but the grace of God which was with me. 11 Therefore whether it was I or they, so we preach, and so ye believed. 12 Now if Christ is preached that he rose from the dead, how say some among you that there is no resurrection of the dead? 13 But if there is no resurrection of the dead, then is Christ not raised. 14 And if Christ is not raised, then is our preaching vain, and your faith is also vain. 15 And indeed we are found false witnesses of God; because we have testified concerning God that he raised up Christ: whom he raised not, if in truth the dead rise not. 16 For if the dead rise not, then is not Christ raised: 17 And if Christ is not raised, your faith is vain; ye are yet in your sins. 18 Then they also who have fallen asleep in Christ have perished. 19 If in this life only we have hope in Christ, we are of all men most miserable. 20 But now is Christ raised from the dead, and become the first-fruits of them that slept. 21 For since by man came death, by man came also the resurrection of the dead. 22 For as in Adam all die, even so in Christ shall all be made alive. 23 But every man in his own order: Christ the first-fruits; afterward they that are Christ's at his coming. 24 Then cometh the end, when he shall have delivered up the kingdom to God, even the Father; when he shall have put down all rule, and all authority, and power. 25 For he must reign, till he hath put all enemies under his feet. 26 The last enemy that shall be destroyed is death. 27 For he hath put all things under his feet. But when he saith, all things are put under him , it is manifest that he is excepted who did put all things under him. 28 And when all things shall be subdued to him, then shall the Son also himself be subject to him that put all things under him, that God may be all in all. 29 Else what will they do, who are baptized for the dead, if the dead rise not at all? why are they then baptized for the dead? 30 And why stand we in jeopardy every hour? 31 I protest by your rejoicing which I have in Christ Jesus our Lord, I die daily. 32 If after the manner of men I have fought with beasts at Ephesus, what advantage is it to me, if the dead rise not? let us eat and drink; for to-morrow we die. 33 Be not deceived: Evil communications corrupt good manners. 34 Awake to righteousness, and sin not; for some have not the knowledge of God. I speak this to your shame. 35 But some man will say, How are the dead raised? and with what body do they come? 36 Thou fool, that which thou sowest is not vivified except it die: 37 And that which thou sowest, thou sowest not that body that shall be, but bare grain; it may be of wheat, or of some other grain : 38 But God giveth it a body as it hath pleased him, and to every seed its own body. 39 All flesh is not the same flesh; but there is one kind of flesh of men, another flesh of beasts, another of fish, and another of fowls. 40 There are also celestial bodies, and bodies terrestrial: but the glory of the celestial is one, and the glory of the terrestrial is another. 41 There is one glory of the sun, and another glory of the moon, and another glory of the stars; for one star differeth from another star in glory. 42 So also is the resurrection of the dead. It is sown in corruption, it is raised in incorruption: 43 It is sown in dishonor, it is raised in glory: it is sown in weakness, it is raised in power: 44 It is sown a natural body, it is raised a spiritual body. There is a natural body, and there is a spiritual body. 45 And so it is written, The first man Adam was made a living soul, the last Adam was made a vivifying spirit. 46 However, that was not first which is spiritual, but that which is natural; and afterward that which is spiritual. 47 The first man is from the earth, earthy: the second man is the Lord from heaven. 48 As is the earthy, such are they also that are earthy: and as is the heavenly, such are they also that are heavenly. 49 And as we have borne the image of the earthy, we shall also bear the image of the heavenly. 50 Now this I say, brethren, that flesh and blood cannot inherit the kingdom of God; neither doth corruption inherit incorruption. 51 Behold, I show you a mystery; We shall not all sleep, but we shall all be changed, 52 In a moment, in the twinkling of an eye, at the last trumpet; for the trumpet shall sound, and the dead shall be raised incorruptible, and we shall be changed. 53 For this corruptible must put on incorruption, and this mortal must put on immortality. 54 So when this corruptible shall have put on incorruption, and this mortal shall have put on immortality, then shall be brought to pass the saying that is written, Death is swallowed up in victory. 55 O death, where is thy sting? O grave, where is thy victory? 56 The sting of death is sin; and the strength of sin is the law. 57 But thanks be to God, who giveth us the victory, through our Lord Jesus Christ. 58 Therefore, my beloved brethren, be ye steadfast, immovable, always abounding in the work of the Lord, forasmuch as ye know that your labor is not in vain in the Lord.

16

1 Now concerning the collection for the saints, as I have given order to the churches of Galatia, even so do ye. 2 Upon the first day of the week, let every one of you lay by him in store, as God hath prospered him, that there be no collections when I come. 3 And when I come, whomsoever ye shall approve by your letters, them will I send to bring your liberality to Jerusalem. 4 And if it be proper that I should go also, they shall go with me. 5 Now I will come to you, when I shall pass through Macedonia: for I am to pass through Macedonia. 6 And it may be that I shall abide, and even winter with you, that ye may bring me on my journey whithersoever I go. 7 For I will not see you now by the way; but I trust to tarry a while with you, if the Lord permit. 8 But I shall tarry at Ephesus until Pentecost. 9 For a great door and effectual is opened to me, and there are many adversaries. 10 Now if Timothy come, see that he may be with you without fear: for he worketh the work of the Lord, as I also do . 11 Let no man therefore despise him: but conduct him forth in peace, that he may come to me: for I look for him with the brethren. 12 As concerning our brother Apollos, I greatly desired him to come to you with the brethren: but his will was not at all to come at this time; but he will come when he shall have convenient time. 13 Watch ye, stand fast in the faith, acquit yourselves like men, be strong. 14 Let all your things be done with love. 15 I beseech you, brethren, (ye know the house of Stephanas, that it is the first fruits of Achaia, and that they have addicted themselves to the ministry of the saints,) 16 That ye submit yourselves to such, and to every one that helpeth with us , and laboreth. 17 I am glad of the coming of Stephanas, and Fortunatus, and Achaicus: for that which was lacking on your part, they have supplied. 18 For they have refreshed my spirit and yours: therefore acknowledge ye them that are such. 19 The churches of Asia salute you. Aquila and Priscilla salute you much in the Lord, with the church that is in their house. 20 All the brethren greet you. Greet ye one another with a holy kiss. 21 The salutation of me Paul with my own hand. 22 If any man loveth not the Lord Jesus Christ, let him be Anathema, Maran-atha. 23 The grace of our Lord Jesus Christ be with you. 24 My love be with you all in Christ Jesus. Amen.

1 Timothy

1
2
3
4
5
6

THE FIRST EPISTLE OF PAUL THE APOSTLE TO TIMOTHY

1

1 Paul, an apostle of Jesus Christ by the commandment of God our Savior, and Lord Jesus Christ, who is our hope; 2 To Timothy, my own son in the faith: Grace, mercy, and peace, from God our Father and Jesus Christ our Lord. 3 As I besought thee to abide still at Ephesus, when I went into Macedonia, that thou mightest charge some that they teach no other doctrine, 4 Neither give heed to fables and endless genealogies, which minister questions, rather than godly edifying which is in faith; so do . 5 Now the end of the commandment is love out of a pure heart, and of a good conscience, and of faith unfeigned: 6 From which some having swerved, have turned aside to vain jangling; 7 Desiring to be teachers of the law; understanding neither what they say, nor concerning what they affirm. 8 But we know that the law is good, if a man useth it lawfully; 9 Knowing this, that the law is not made for a righteous man, but for the lawless and disobedient, for the ungodly and for sinners, for unholy and profane, for murderers of fathers, and murderers of mothers, for man-slayers, 10 For lewd persons, for them that defile themselves with mankind, for men-stealers, for liars, for perjured persons, and if there is any other thing that is contrary to sound doctrine, 11 According to the glorious gospel of the blessed God, which was committed to my trust. 12 And I thank Christ Jesus our Lord, who hath enabled me, for that he counted me faithful, putting me into the ministry; 13 Who was before a blasphemer, and a persecutor, and injurious: but I obtained mercy, because I did it ignorantly in unbelief: 14 And the grace of our Lord was exceeding abundant with faith and love which is in Christ Jesus. 15 This is a faithful saying, and worthy of all acceptation, that Christ Jesus came into the world to save sinners; of whom I am chief. 16 However, for this cause I obtained mercy, that in me first Jesus Christ might show forth all long-suffering, for a pattern to them who should hereafter believe on him to life everlasting. 17 Now to the King eternal, immortal, invisible, God the only wise, be honor and glory for ever and ever. Amen. 18 This charge I commit to thee, son Timothy, according to the prophecies which went before on thee, that thou by them mayest war a good warfare; 19 Holding faith and a good conscience; which some having put away, concerning faith have made shipwreck: 20 Of whom is Hymeneus and Alexander; whom I have delivered to Satan, that they may learn not to blaspheme.

2

1 I exhort therefore, that first of all supplications, prayers, intercessions, and giving of thanks be made for all men; 2 For kings, and for all that are in authority; that we may lead a quiet and peaceable life in all godliness and honesty. 3 For this is good and acceptable in the sight of God our Savior; 4 Who will have all men to be saved, and to come to the knowledge of the truth. 5 For there is one God, and one mediator between God and men, the man Christ Jesus; 6 Who gave himself a ransom for all, to be testified in due time. 7 For which I am ordained a preacher and an apostle, (I speak the truth in Christ, and lie not) a teacher of the Gentiles in faith and verity. 8 I will therefore that men pray every where, lifting up holy hands, without wrath and doubting. 9 In like manner also, that women adorn themselves in decent apparel, with modesty and sobriety; not with broidered hair, or gold, or pearls, or costly array, 10 But (which becometh women professing godliness) with good works. 11 Let the woman learn in silence with all subjection. 12 But I suffer not a woman to teach, nor to usurp authority over the man, but to be in silence. 13 For Adam was first formed, then Eve. 14 And Adam was not deceived, but the woman being deceived was in the transgression. 15 Notwithstanding, she will be saved in child-bearing, if they continue in faith, and love, and holiness, with sobriety.

3

1 This is a true saying, If a man desireth the office of a bishop, he desireth a good work. 2 A bishop then must be blameless, the husband of one wife, vigilant, sober, of good behavior, given to hospitality, apt to teach; 3 Not given to wine, no striker, not greedy of filthy lucre, but patient; not a brawler, not covetous; 4 One that ruleth well his own house, having his children in subjection with all gravity; 5 (For if a man knoweth not how to rule his own house, how shall he take care of the church of God?) 6 Not a novice, lest being lifted up with pride he fall into the condemnation of the devil. 7 Moreover, he must have a good report of them who are without; lest he fall into reproach and the snare of the devil. 8 Likewise must the deacons be grave, not double-tongued, not given to much wine, not greedy of filthy lucre, 9 Holding the mystery of the faith in a pure conscience. 10 And let these also first be proved; then let them use the office of a deacon, being found blameless. 11 Even so must their wives be grave, not slanderers, sober, faithful in all things. 12 Let the deacons be the husbands of one wife, ruling their children, and their own houses well. 13 For they that have used the office of a deacon well, purchase to themselves a good degree, and great boldness in the faith, which is in Christ Jesus. 14 These things I write to thee, hoping to come to thee shortly: 15 But if I tarry long, that thou mayest know how thou oughtest to behave thyself in the house of God, which is the church of the living God, the pillar and ground of the truth. 16 And without controversy, great is the mystery of godliness: God was manifest in the flesh, justified in the Spirit, seen by angels, preached to the Gentiles, believed on in the world, received up into glory.

4

1 Now the Spirit speaketh expressly, that in the latter times some will depart from the faith, giving heed to seducing spirits and doctrines of demons; 2 Speaking lies in hypocrisy, having their conscience seared with a hot iron; 3 Forbidding to marry, and commanding to abstain from meats, which God hath created to be received with thanksgiving by them who believe and know the truth. 4 For every creature of God is good, and nothing to be refused, if received with thanksgiving: 5 For it is sanctified by the word of God, and prayer. 6 If thou shalt put the brethren in remembrance of these things, thou wilt be a good minister of Jesus Christ, nourished by the words of faith and of good doctrine, to which thou hast attained. 7 But refuse profane and old wives' fables, and exercise thyself rather to godliness. 8 For bodily exercise profiteth little: but godliness is profitable to all things, having promise of the life that now is, and of that which is to come. 9 This is a faithful saying, and worthy of all acceptation. 10 For therefore we both labor and suffer reproach, because we trust in the living God who is the Savior of all men, especially of those that believe. 11 These things command and teach. 12 Let no man despise thy youth; but be thou an example of the believers, in word, in deportment, in love, in spirit, in faith, in purity. 13 Till I come, give attendance to reading, to exhortation, to doctrine. 14 Neglect not the gift that is in thee, which was given thee by prophecy, with the laying on of the hands of the presbytery. 15 Meditate upon these things; give thyself wholly to them; that thy profiting may appear to all. 16 Take heed to thyself and to thy doctrine; continue in them: for in doing this thou wilt both save thyself, and them that hear thee.

5

1 Rebuke not an elder, but entreat him as a father; and the younger men as brethren; 2 The elder women as mothers; the younger as sisters, with all purity. 3 Honor widows that are widows indeed. 4 But if any widow hath children or nephews, let them learn first to show piety at home, and to requite their parents: for that is good and acceptable before God. 5 Now she that is a widow indeed, and desolate, trusteth in God, and continueth in supplications and prayers night and day. 6 But she that liveth in pleasure, is dead while she liveth. 7 And these things give in charge, that they may be blameless. 8 But if any provideth not for his own, and especially for those of his own house, he hath denied the faith, and is worse than an infidel. 9 Let not a widow be taken into the number under sixty years old, having been the wife of one man. 10 Well reported of for good works; if she hath brought up children, if she hath lodged strangers, if she hath washed the saints' feet, if she hath relieved the afflicted, if she hath diligently followed every good work. 11 But the younger widows refuse: for when they have begun to grow wanton against Christ, they will marry; 12 Having damnation, because they have cast off their first faith. 13 And at the same time they learn to be idle, wandering about from house to house, and not only idle, but tattlers also, and busy-bodies, speaking things which they ought not. 14 I will therefore that the younger women marry, bear children, guide the house, give no occasion to the adversary to speak reproachfully. 15 For some are already turned aside after Satan. 16 If any man or woman that believeth hath widows, let them relieve them, and let not the church be charged; that it may relieve them that are widows indeed. 17 Let the elders that rule well, be counted worthy of double honor, especially they who labor in the word and doctrine. 18 For the scripture saith, Thou shalt not muzzle the ox that treadeth out the grain. And, The laborer is worthy of his reward. 19 Against an elder receive not an accusation, but before two or three witnesses. 20 Them that sin rebuke before all, that others also may fear. 21 I charge thee before God and the Lord Jesus Christ, and the elect angels, that thou observe these things without preferring one before another, doing nothing by partiality. 22 Impose hands hastily on no man, neither be partaker of other men's sins: keep thyself pure. 23 Drink no longer water, but use a little wine for thy stomach's sake, and thy frequent infirmities. 24 Some men's sins are open beforehand, going before to judgment: and some men they follow after. 25 Likewise also the good works of some are manifest beforehand; and they that are otherwise cannot be hid.

6

1 Let as many servants as are under the yoke count their own masters worthy of all honor, that the name of God and his doctrine may not be blasphemed. 2 And they that have believing masters, let them not despise them , because they are brethren; but rather do them service, because they are faithful and beloved, partakers of the benefit. These things teach and exhort. 3 If any man teacheth otherwise, and consenteth not to wholesome words, even the words of our Lord Jesus Christ, and the doctrine which is according to godliness, 4 He is proud, knowing nothing, but doting about questions and strifes of words, from which cometh envy, strife, railings, evil surmisings, 5 Perverse disputings of men of corrupt minds, and destitute of the truth, supposing gain to be godliness: from such withdraw thyself. 6 But godliness with contentment is great gain. 7 For we brought nothing into this world, and it is certain we can carry nothing out. 8 And having food and raiment, with these let us be content. 9 But they that will be rich, fall into temptation, and a snare, and into many foolish and hurtful lusts, which drown men in destruction and perdition. 10 For the love of money is the root of all evil: which while some have coveted, they have erred from the faith, and pierced themselves through with many sorrows. 11 But thou, O man of God, flee from these things; and follow after righteousness, godliness, faith, love, patience, meekness. 12 Fight the good fight of faith, lay hold on eternal life, to which thou art also called, and hast professed a good profession before many witnesses. 13 I give thee charge in the sight of God, who maketh alive all things, and before Christ Jesus, who before Pontius Pilate testified a good confession; 14 That thou keep this commandment without spot, unrebukable, until the appearing of our Lord Jesus Christ: 15 Which in his times he will show who is the blessed and only Potentate, the King of kings, and Lord of lords; 16 Who only hath immortality, dwelling in the light which no man can approach; whom no man hath seen, nor can see: to whom be honor and power everlasting. Amen. 17 Charge them that are rich in this world, that they be not high-minded, nor trust in uncertain riches, but in the living God, who giveth us richly all things to enjoy; 18 That they do good, that they be rich in good works, ready to distribute, willing to communicate; 19 Laying up in store for themselves a good foundation against the time to come, that they may lay hold on eternal life. 20 O Timothy, keep that which is committed to thy trust, avoiding profane and vain babblings, and oppositions of science falsely so called; 21 Which some professing, have erred concerning the faith. Grace be with thee. Amen.

2 Peter

1
2
3

THE SECOND EPISTLE GENERAL OF PETER

1

1 Simon Peter, a servant and an apostle of Jesus Christ, to them that have obtained like precious faith with us through the righteousness of God and our Savior Jesus Christ: 2 Grace and peace be multiplied to you through the knowledge of God, and of Jesus our Lord, 3 According as his divine power hath given to us all things that pertain to life and godliness, through the knowledge of him that hath called us to glory and virtue: 4 Whereby are given to us exceeding great and precious promises; that by these ye might be partakers of the divine nature, having escaped the corruption that is in the world through lust. 5 And besides this, giving all diligence, add to your faith virtue; and to virtue knowledge; 6 And to knowledge temperance; and to temperance patience; and to patience godliness; 7 And to godliness brotherly kindness; and to brotherly kindness love. 8 For if these things be in you, and abound, they make you that ye shall neither be barren nor unfruitful in the knowledge of our Lord Jesus Christ. 9 But he that lacketh these things is blind, and cannot see afar off, and hath forgotten that he was purified from his old sins. 10 Wherefore the rather, brethren, give diligence to make your calling and election sure: for if ye do these things, ye shall never fall: 11 For so an entrance shall be ministered to you abundantly into the everlasting kingdom of our Lord and Savior Jesus Christ. 12 Wherefore I will not be negligent to put you always in remembrance of these things, though ye know them , and are established in the present truth. 13 Indeed, I think it meet, as long as I am in this tabernacle, to stir you up by putting you in remembrance; 14 Knowing that shortly I must put off this my tabernacle, even as our Lord Jesus Christ hath shown me. 15 Moreover, I will endeavor that ye may be able, after my decease, to have these things always in remembrance. 16 For we have not followed cunningly devised fables, when we made known to you the power and coming of our Lord Jesus Christ, but were eye-witnesses of his majesty. 17 For he received from God the Father honor and glory, when there came such a voice to him from the excellent glory, This is my beloved Son, in whom I am well pleased. 18 And this voice which came from heaven we heard, when we were with him on the holy mount. 19 We have also a more sure word of prophecy; to which ye do well that ye take heed, as to a light that shineth in a dark place, until the day dawn, and the day-star arise in your hearts: 20 Knowing this first, that no prophecy of the scripture is of any private interpretation. 21 For prophecy came not in old time by the will of man: but holy men of God spoke as they were moved by the Holy Spirit.

2

1 But there were false prophets also among the people, even as there will be false teachers among you, who will privately bring in damnable heresies, even denying the Lord that bought them, and bring upon themselves swift destruction. 2 And many will follow their pernicious ways; by reason of whom the way of truth will be evil spoken of. 3 And through covetousness they will with feigned words make merchandise of you: whose judgment now of a long time lingereth not, and their damnation slumbereth not. 4 For if God spared not the angels that sinned, but cast them down to hell, and delivered them into chains of darkness, to be reserved to judgment; 5 And spared not the old world, but saved Noah the eighth person , a preacher of righteousness, bringing the flood upon the world of the ungodly; 6 And turning the cities of Sodom and Gomorrah into ashes, condemned them with an overthrow, making them an example to those that afterwards should live ungodly lives. 7 And delivered just Lot, grieved with the habitual lewdness of the wicked: 8 (For that righteous man dwelling among them, in seeing and hearing, grieved his righteous soul from day to day with their unlawful deeds;) 9 The Lord knoweth how to deliver the godly out of temptations, and to reserve the unjust to the day of judgment to be punished: 10 But chiefly them that walk after the flesh in the lust of uncleanness, and despise government. Presumptuous are they , self-willed; they are not afraid to speak evil of dignities. 11 Whereas angels, who are greater in power and might, bring not railing accusation against them before the Lord. 12 But these, as natural brute beasts, made to be taken and destroyed, speak evil of the things that they understand not; and shall utterly perish in their own corruption: 13 And shall receive the reward of unrighteousness, as they that count it pleasure to riot in the day-time. Spots they are and blemishes, sporting themselves with their own deceivings while they feast with you; 14 Having eyes full of adultery, and that cannot cease from sin; beguiling unstable souls: they have a heart exercised with covetous practices; cursed children: 15 Who have forsaken the right way, and gone astray, following the way of Balaam the son of Bosor, who loved the wages of unrighteousness; 16 But was rebuked for his iniquity: the mute ass speaking with man's voice, forbad the madness of the prophet. 17 These are wells without water, clouds that are carried with a tempest; to whom the mist of darkness is reserved for ever. 18 For when they speak great swelling words of vanity, they allure through the lusts of the flesh, through much wantonness, those that had quite escaped from them who live in error. 19 While they promise them liberty, they themselves are the servants of corruption: for by whom a man is overcome, by the same is he brought into bondage. 20 For if after they have escaped the pollutions of the world through the knowledge of the Lord and Savior Jesus Christ, they are again entangled in them, and overcome, the latter end is worse with them than the beginning. 21 For it had been better for them not to have known the way of righteousness, than, after they have known it , to turn from the holy commandment delivered to them. 22 But it hath happened to them according to the true proverb, The dog is turned to his own vomit again; and, The sow that was washed, to her wallowing in the mire.

3

1 This second epistle, beloved, I now write to you; in both which I stir up your pure minds by way of remembrance: 2 That ye may be mindful of the words which were spoken before by the holy prophets, and of the commandment of us the apostles of the Lord and Savior: 3 Knowing this first, that there will come in the last days scoffers, walking after their own lusts, 4 And saying, Where is the promise of his coming? for since the fathers fell asleep, all things continue as they were from the beginning of the creation. 5 For this they willingly are ignorant of, that by the word of God the heavens were of old, and the earth standing out of the water and in the water: 6 By which the world that then was, being overflowed with water, perished: 7 But the heavens and the earth, which are now, by the same word are kept in store, reserved to fire against the day of judgment and perdition of ungodly men. 8 But, beloved, be not ignorant of this one thing, that one day is with the Lord as a thousand years, and a thousand years as one day. 9 The Lord is not slack concerning his promise, as some men count slackness; but is long-suffering toward us, not willing that any should perish, but that all should come to repentance. 10 But the day of the Lord will come as a thief in the night; in which the heavens will pass away with a great noise, and the elements will melt with fervent heat, the earth also and the works that are therein will be burned up. 11 Seeing then that all these things will be dissolved, what manner of persons ought ye to be in all holy deportment and godliness, 12 Looking for and hasting to the coming of the day of God, in which the heavens being on fire will be dissolved, and the elements will melt with fervent heat? 13 Nevertheless we, according to his promise, look for new heavens and a new earth, in which dwelleth righteousness. 14 Wherefore, beloved, seeing that ye look for such things, be diligent that ye may be found by him in peace, without spot, and blameless. 15 And account that the long-suffering of our Lord is salvation; even as our beloved brother Paul also, according to the wisdom given to him, hath written to you; 16 As also in all his epistles, speaking in them of these things; in which are some things hard to be understood, which they that are unlearned and unstable wrest, as they do also the other scriptures, to their own destruction. 17 Ye therefore, beloved, seeing ye know these things before, beware lest ye also, being led away with the error of the wicked, fall from your own steadfastness. 18 But grow in grace, and in the knowledge of our Lord and Savior Jesus Christ. To him be glory both now and for ever. Amen.

Galatians

1
2
3
4
5
6

THE EPISTLE OF PAUL THE APOSTLE TO THE GALATIANS

1

1 Paul, an apostle, (not from men, neither by man, but by Jesus Christ, and God the Father, who raised him from the dead;) 2 And all the brethren who are with me, to the churches of Galatia: 3 Grace be to you and peace from God the Father, and from our Lord Jesus Christ, 4 Who gave himself for our sins, that he might deliver us from this present evil world, according to the will of God and our Father: 5 To whom be glory for ever and ever. Amen. 6 I marvel that ye are so soon removed from him that called you into the grace of Christ, to another gospel: 7 Which is not another; but there are some that trouble you, and would pervert the gospel of Christ. 8 But though we, or an angel from heaven, should preach any other gospel to you than that which we have preached to you, let him be accursed. 9 As we said before, so I say now again, If any man preacheth any other gospel to you than that ye have received, let him be accursed. 10 For do I now persuade men, or God? or do I seek to please men? for if I yet pleased men, I should not be the servant of Christ. 11 But I certify you, brethren, that the gospel which was preached by me is not according to man. 12 For I neither received it from man, neither was I taught it , but by the revelation of Jesus Christ. 13 For ye have heard of my manner of life in time past in the Jews' religion, that beyond measure I persecuted the church of God, and wasted it; 14 And profited in the Jews' religion above many my equals in my own nation, being more exceedingly zealous of the traditions of my fathers. 15 But when it pleased God, who separated me from my mother's womb, and called me by his grace, 16 To reveal his Son in me, that I might preach him among the heathen; immediately I conferred not with flesh and blood: 17 Neither did I go to Jerusalem to them who were apostles before me: but I went into Arabia, and returned again to Damascus. 18 Then after three years I went to Jerusalem to see Peter, and abode with him fifteen days. 19 But I saw no other of the apostles, save James the Lord's brother. 20 Now the things which I write to you, behold, before God, I lie not. 21 Afterwards I came into the regions of Syria and Cilicia; 22 And was unknown by face to the churches of Judea which were in Christ: 23 But they had heard only, That he who persecuted us in times past, now preacheth the faith which once he destroyed. 24 And they glorified God in me.

2

1 Then fourteen years after I went again to Jerusalem with Barnabas, and took Titus with me also. 2 And I went by revelation, and communicated to them that gospel which I preach among the Gentiles, but privately to them who were of reputation, lest by any means I should run, or had run in vain. 3 But neither Titus, who was with me, being a Greek, was compelled to be circumcised: 4 And that because of false brethren unawares brought in, who came in privately to spy out our liberty which we have in Christ Jesus, that they might bring us into bondage: 5 To whom we gave place by subjection, no, not for an hour; that the truth of the gospel might continue with you. 6 But of these, who seemed to be somewhat, (whatever they were, it maketh no matter to me: God accepteth no man's person:) for they who seemed to be somewhat , in conference added nothing to me: 7 But on the contrary, when they saw that the gospel of the uncircumcision was committed to me, as the gospel of the circumcision was to Peter; 8 (For he that wrought effectually in Peter to the apostleship of the circumcision, the same was mighty in me towards the Gentiles:) 9 And when James, Cephas, and John, who seemed to be pillars, perceived the grace that was given to me, they gave to me and Barnabas the right hands of fellowship; that we should go to the heathen, and they to the circumcision. 10 Only they would that we should remember the poor; the same which I also was forward to do. 11 But when Peter had come to Antioch, I withstood him to the face, because he was to be blamed. 12 For before that certain came from James, he used to eat with the Gentiles: but when they had come, he withdrew, and separated himself, fearing them who were of the circumcision. 13 And the other Jews played the hypocrite with him; so that Barnabas also was carried away with their hypocrisy. 14 But when I saw that they walked not uprightly according to the truth of the gospel, I said to Peter before them all, If thou, being a Jew, livest after the manner of Gentiles, and not as do the Jews, why compellest thou the Gentiles to live as do the Jews? 15 We who are Jews by nature, and not sinners of the Gentiles, 16 Knowing that a man is not justified by the works of the law, but by the faith of Jesus Christ, even we have believed in Jesus Christ, that we may be justified by the faith of Christ, and not by the works of the law: for by the works of the law shall no flesh be justified. 17 But if, while we seek to be justified by Christ, we ourselves also are found sinners, is therefore Christ the minister of sin? By no means. 18 For if I build again the things which I destroyed, I make myself a transgressor. 19 For I through the law am dead to the law, that I may live to God. 20 I am crucified with Christ: nevertheless, I live; yet not I, but Christ liveth in me: and the life which I now live in the flesh, I live by the faith of the Son of God, who loved me, and gave himself for me. 21 I do not frustrate the grace of God: for if righteousness is attainable by the law, then Christ hath died in vain.

3

1 O foolish Galatians, who hath bewitched you, that ye should not obey the truth, before whose eyes Jesus Christ hath been evidently set forth, crucified among you? 2 This only would I learn from you, Received ye the Spirit by the works of the law, or by the hearing of faith? 3 Are ye so foolish? having begun in the Spirit, are ye now made perfect by the flesh? 4 Have ye suffered so many things in vain? if it is yet in vain. 5 He therefore that ministereth to you the Spirit, and worketh miracles among you, doeth he this by the works of the law, or by the hearing of faith? 6 Even as Abraham believed God, and it was accounted to him for righteousness. 7 Know ye therefore, that they who are of faith, the same are the children of Abraham. 8 And the scripture foreseeing that God would justify the heathen through faith, preached before the gospel to Abraham, saying , In thee shall all nations be blessed. 9 So then they who are of faith are blessed with faithful Abraham. 10 For as many as are of the works of the law, are under the curse: for it is written, Accursed is every one that continueth not in all things which are written in the book of the law to do them. 11 But that no man is justified by the law in the sight of God, is evident: for, The just shall live by faith. 12 And the law is not of faith: but, The man that doeth them shall live by them. 13 Christ hath redeemed us from the curse of the law, being made a curse for us: for it is written, Accursed is every one that hangeth on a tree: 14 That the blessing of Abraham might come on the Gentiles through Jesus Christ; that we might receive the promise of the Spirit through faith. 15 Brethren, I speak after the manner of men; Though it is but a man's covenant, yet if it is confirmed, no man disannulleth or addeth to it. 16 Now to Abraham and his seed were the promises made. He saith not, And to seeds, as of many; but as of one, And to thy seed, which is Christ. 17 And this I say, that the covenant that was confirmed before by God in Christ, the law, which was four hundred and thirty years after, cannot disannul, that it should make the promise of no effect. 18 For if the inheritance is by the law, it is no more by promise: but God gave it to Abraham by promise. 19 What purpose then serveth the law? It was added because of transgressions, till the seed should come to whom the promise was made; and it was ordained by angels in the hand of a mediator. 20 Now a mediator is not a mediator of one; but God is one. 21 Is the law then against the promises of God? By no means: for if there had been a law given which could give life, verily righteousness would have been by the law. 22 But the scripture hath concluded all under sin, that the promise by faith of Jesus Christ might be given to them that believe. 23 But before faith came, we were kept under the law, shut up to the faith which should afterwards be revealed. 24 Wherefore the law was our school-master to bring us to Christ, that we might be justified by faith. 25 But after faith is come, we are no longer under a school-master. 26 For ye are all children of God by faith in Christ Jesus. 27 For as many of you as have been baptized into Christ, have put on Christ. 28 There is neither Jew nor Greek, there is neither bond nor free, there is neither male nor female: for ye are all one in Christ Jesus. 29 And if ye are Christ's, then are ye Abraham's seed, and heirs according to the promise.

4

1 Now I say, That the heir, as long as he is a child, differeth nothing from a servant, though he is lord of all; 2 But is under tutors and governors until the time appointed by the father. 3 Even so we, when we were children, were in bondage under the elements of the world: 4 But when the fullness of the time was come, God sent forth his Son, born of a woman, born under the law, 5 To redeem them that were under the law, that we might receive the adoption of sons. 6 And because ye are sons, God hath sent forth the Spirit of his Son into your hearts, crying, Abba, Father. 7 Wherefore thou art no more a servant, but a son; and if a son, then an heir of God through Christ. 8 However then, when ye knew not God, ye did service to them which by nature are no gods. 9 But now, after ye have known God, or rather are known by God, how turn ye again to the weak and beggarly elements, to which ye desire again to be in bondage? 10 Ye observe days, and months, and times, and years. 11 I am afraid of you, lest I have bestowed upon you labor in vain. 12 Brethren, I beseech you, be as I am; for I am as ye are : ye have not injured me at all. 13 Ye know that in infirmity of the flesh I preached the gospel to you at the first. 14 And my temptation which was in my flesh ye despised not, nor rejected; but received me as an angel of God, even as Christ Jesus. 15 What then was the blessedness ye spoke of; for I bear you testimony, that, if it had been possible, ye would have plucked out your own eyes, and have given them to me. 16 Am I therefore become your enemy because I tell you the truth? 17 They zealously affect you, but not well; for, they would exclude you, that ye may affect them. 18 But it is good to be zealously affected always in a good thing , and not only when I am present with you. 19 My little children, of whom I travail in birth again, until Christ be formed in you, 20 I desire to be present with you now, and to change my voice; for I stand in doubt of you. 21 Tell me, ye that desire to be under the law, do ye not hear the law? 22 For it is written, that Abraham had two sons; the one by a bond-maid, the other by a free-woman. 23 But he who was of the bond-woman, was born according to the flesh; but he of the free-woman was by promise. 24 Which things are an allegory: for these are the two covenants; the one from the mount Sinai, which gendereth to bondage, which is Agar. 25 For this Agar is mount Sinai in Arabia, and answereth to Jerusalem which now is, and is in bondage with her children. 26 But Jerusalem which is above is free, which is the mother of us all. 27 For it is written, Rejoice, thou barren that bearest not; break forth and cry, thou that travailest not: for the desolate hath many more children than she who hath a husband. 28 Now we, brethren, as Isaac was, are the children of promise. 29 But as then he that was born according to the flesh persecuted him that was born according to the Spirit, even so it is now. 30 Nevertheless, what saith the scripture? Cast out the bond-woman and her son: for the son of the bond-woman shall not be heir with the son of the free-woman. 31 So then, brethren, we are not children of the bond-woman, but of the free.

5

1 Stand fast therefore in the liberty with which Christ hath made us free, and be not entangled again with the yoke of bondage. 2 Behold, I Paul say to you, that if ye be circumcised, Christ will profit you nothing. 3 For I testify again to every man that is circumcised, that he is a debtor to do the whole law. 4 Christ is become of no effect to you, whoever of you are justified by the law; ye have fallen from grace. 5 For we through the Spirit wait for the hope of righteousness by faith. 6 For in Jesus Christ neither circumcision availeth any thing, nor uncircumcision; but faith which worketh by love. 7 Ye did run well, who hindered you that ye should not obey the truth? 8 This persuasion cometh not from him that calleth you. 9 A little leaven leaveneth the whole lump. 10 I have confidence in you through the Lord, that ye will be no otherwise minded: but he that troubleth you shall bear his judgment, whoever he may be. 11 And I, brethren, if I yet preach circumcision, why do I yet suffer persecution? then hath the offense of the cross ceased. 12 I would they were even cut off who trouble you. 13 For, brethren, ye have been called to liberty; only use not liberty for an occasion to the flesh, but by love serve one another. 14 For all the law is fulfilled in one word, even in this, Thou shalt love thy neighbor as thyself. 15 But if ye bite and devour one another, take heed that ye be not consumed one by another. 16 This I say then, Walk in the Spirit, and ye will not fulfill the lust of the flesh. 17 For the flesh lusteth against the Spirit, and the Spirit against the flesh: and these are contrary the one to the other; so that ye cannot do the things that ye would. 18 But if ye are led by the Spirit, ye are not under the law. 19 Now the works of the flesh are manifest, which are these , Adultery, fornication, uncleanness, lasciviousness, 20 Idolatry, witchcraft, hatred, contentions, jealousies, wrath, strife, dissensions, heresies, 21 Envyings, murders, drunkenness, revelings, and such like: of which I tell you before, as I have also told you in time past, that they who do such things shall not inherit the kingdom of God. 22 But the fruit of the Spirit is love, joy, peace, long-suffering, gentleness, goodness, faith, 23 Meekness, temperance: against such there is no law. 24 And they that are Christ's have crucified the flesh, with the affections and lusts. 25 If we live in the Spirit, let us also walk in the Spirit. 26 Let us not be desirous of vain-glory, provoking one another, envying one another.

6

1 Brethren, if a man be overtaken in a fault, ye who are spiritual, restore such one in the spirit of meekness; considering thyself, lest thou also be tempted. 2 Bear ye one another's burdens, and so fulfill the law of Christ. 3 For if a man thinketh himself to be something, when he is nothing, he deceiveth himself. 4 But let every man prove his own work, and then shall he have rejoicing in himself alone, and not in another. 5 For every man shall bear his own burden. 6 Let him that is taught in the word communicate to him that teacheth in all good things. 7 Be not deceived; God is not mocked: for whatever a man soweth, that shall he also reap. 8 For he that soweth to his flesh shall from the flesh reap corruption: but he that soweth to the Spirit, shall from the Spirit reap life everlasting. 9 And let us not be weary in well-doing: for in due season we shall reap, if we faint not. 10 As we have therefore opportunity, let us do good to all men , especially to them who are of the household of faith. 11 Ye see how large a letter I have written to you with my own hand. 12 As many as desire to make a fair show in the flesh, they constrain you to be circumcised; only lest they should suffer persecution for the cross of Christ. 13 For neither they themselves who are circumcised keep the law; but desire to have you circumcised, that they may glory in your flesh. 14 But may it never be that I should glory, save in the cross of our Lord Jesus Christ, by whom the world is crucified to me, and I to the world. 15 For in Christ Jesus neither circumcision availeth any thing, nor uncircumcision, but a new creature. 16 And as many as walk according to this rule, peace be on them, and mercy, and upon the Israel of God. 17 From henceforth let no man trouble me: for I bear in my body the marks of the Lord Jesus. 18 Brethren, the grace of our Lord Jesus Christ be with your spirit. Amen.

Hebrews

1
2
3
4
5
6
7
8
9
10

11
12
13

THE EPISTLE OF PAUL THE APOSTLE TO THE HEBREWS

1

1 God, who at sundry times and in divers manners spoke in time past to the fathers by the prophets, 2 Hath in these last days spoken to us by his Son, whom he hath appointed heir of all things, by whom also he made the worlds; 3 Who being the brightness of his glory, and the express image of his person, and upholding all things by the word of his power, when he had by himself made purification of our sins, sat down on the right hand of the Majesty on high; 4 Being made so much better than the angels, as he hath by inheritance obtained a more excellent name than they. 5 For to which of the angels said he at any time, Thou art my Son, this day have I begotten thee? And again, I will be to him a Father, and he shall be to me a Son? 6 And again, when he bringeth in the first-begotten into the world, he saith, And let all the angels of God worship him. 7 And of the angels he saith, Who maketh his angels spirits, and his ministers a flame of fire. 8 But to the Son, he saith , Thy throne, O God, is for ever and ever: a scepter of righteousness is the scepter of thy kingdom. 9 Thou hast loved righteousness, and hated iniquity; therefore God, even thy God, hath anointed thee with the oil of gladness above thy fellows. 10 And, Thou, Lord, in the beginning hast laid the foundation of the earth: and the heavens are the works of thy hands. 11 They shall perish; but thou remainest: and they all shall become old as doth a garment; 12 And as a vesture wilt thou fold them up, and they shall be changed; but thou art the same, and thy years shall not fail. 13 But to which of the angels said he at any time, Sit on my right hand, until I make thy enemies thy footstool? 14 Are they not all ministering spirits, sent forth to minister for them who shall inherit salvation?

2

1 Therefore we ought to give the more earnest heed to the things which we have heard, lest at any time we should let them slip. 2 For if the word spoken by angels was steadfast, and every transgression and disobedience received a just recompense of reward; 3 How shall we escape, if we neglect so great salvation; which at the first began to be spoken by the Lord, and was confirmed to us by them that heard him ; 4 God also bearing them testimony, both with signs and wonders, and with divers miracles, and gifts of the Holy Spirit, according to his own will? 5 For to the angels he hath not put in subjection the world to come, concerning which we speak. 6 But one in a certain place testified, saying, What is man, that thou art mindful of him? or the son of man, that thou visitest him? 7 Thou madest him a little lower than the angels; thou crownedst him with glory and honor, and didst set him over the works of thy hands: 8 Thou hast put all things in subjection under his feet. For in that he put all in subjection under him, he left nothing that is not made subject to him. But now we see not yet all things subjected to him. 9 But we see Jesus, who was made a little lower than the angels for the suffering of death, crowned with glory and honor; that he by the grace of God should taste death for every man. 10 For it became him, for whom are all things, and by whom are all things, in bringing many sons to glory, to make the Captain of their salvation perfect through sufferings. 11 For both he that sanctifieth, and they who are sanctified, are all of one: for which cause he is not ashamed to call them brethren, 12 Saying, I will declare thy name to my brethren, in the midst of the church will I sing praise to thee. 13 And again, I will put my trust in him. And again, Behold, I, and the children which God hath given me. 14 Since then the children are partakers of flesh and blood, he also himself likewise took part of the same; that through death he might destroy him that had the power of death, that is, the devil; 15 And deliver them, who, through fear of death, were all their life-time subject to bondage. 16 For verily he took not on him the nature of angels; but he took on him the seed of Abraham. 17 Wherefore in all things it behooved him to be made like his brethren; that he might be a merciful and faithful High Priest in things pertaining to God, to make reconciliation for the sins of the people. 18 For in that he himself hath suffered, being tempted, he is able to succor them that are tempted.

3

1 Wherefore, holy brethren, partakers of the heavenly calling, consider the Apostle and High Priest of our profession, Christ Jesus; 2 Who was faithful to him that appointed him, as also Moses was faithful in all his house. 3 For this man was counted worthy of more glory than Moses, inasmuch as he who hath built the house, hath more honor than the house. 4 For every house is built by some man ; but he that built all things is God. 5 And Moses verily was faithful in all his house, as a servant, for a testimony of those things which were afterwards to be spoken. 6 But Christ as a son over his own house: whose house are we, if we hold fast the confidence, and the rejoicing of the hope firm to the end. 7 Wherefore (as the Holy Spirit saith, To-day if ye will hear his voice, 8 Harden not your hearts, as in the provocation, in the day of temptation in the wilderness: 9 When your fathers tempted me, proved me, and saw my works forty years. 10 Wherefore I was grieved with that generation, and said, They do always err in their heart; and they have not known my ways. 11 So I swore in my wrath, They shall not enter into my rest.) 12 Take heed, brethren, lest there be in any of you an evil heart of unbelief, in departing from the living God. 13 But exhort one another daily, while it is called To-day; lest any of you be hardened through the deceitfulness of sin. 14 For we are made partakers of Christ, if we hold the beginning of our confidence steadfast to the end; 15 While it is said, To-day if ye will hear his voice, harden not your hearts, as in the provocation. 16 For some, when they had heard, did provoke: yet, not all that came out of Egypt by Moses. 17 But with whom was he grieved forty years? was it not with them that had sinned, whose carcasses fell in the wilderness? 18 And to whom did he swear that they should not enter into his rest, but to them that believed not? 19 So we see that they could not enter in because of unbelief.

4

1 Let us therefore fear, lest a promise being left us of entering into his rest, any of you should seem to come short of it. 2 For to us was the gospel preached, as well as to them: but the word which they heard did not profit them, not being mixed with faith in them that heard it . 3 For we who have believed do enter into rest, as he said, As I have sworn in my wrath, if they shall enter into my rest: although the works were finished from the foundation of the world. 4 For he spoke in a certain place of the seventh day on this wise, And God rested the seventh day from all his works. 5 And in this place again, If they shall enter into my rest. 6 Seeing therefore it remaineth that some must enter into it, and they to whom it was first preached entered not because of unbelief: 7 (Again, he limiteth a certain day, saying in David, To-day, after so long a time; as it is said, To-day, if ye will hear his voice, harden not your hearts. 8 For if Jesus had given them rest, then he would not afterward have spoken of another day. 9 There remaineth therefore a rest to the people of God. 10 For he that hath entered into his rest, he also hath ceased from his own works, as God did from his.) 11 Let us labor therefore to enter into that rest, lest any man fall after the same example of unbelief. 12 For the word of God is living, and powerful, and sharper than any two-edged sword, piercing even to the dividing asunder of soul and spirit, and of the joints and marrow, and is a discerner of the thoughts and intents of the heart. 13 Neither is there any creature that is not manifest in his sight: but all things are naked and opened to the eyes of him with whom we have to do. 14 Seeing then that we have a great High Priest, that hath passed into the heavens, Jesus the Son of God, let us hold fast our profession. 15 For we have not a high priest who cannot be touched with the feeling of our infirmities; but who was in all points tempted as we are , yet without sin. 16 Let us therefore come boldly to the throne of grace, that we may obtain mercy, and find grace to help in time of need.

5

1 For every high priest taken from among men, is ordained for men in things pertaining to God, that he may offer both gifts and sacrifices for sins: 2 Who can have compassion on the ignorant, and on them that are out of the way; for that he himself also is compassed with infirmity. 3 And by reason of this he ought, as for the people, so also for himself, to offer for sins. 4 And no man taketh this honor to himself, but he that is called by God, as was Aaron: 5 So also Christ glorified not himself to be made a high priest; but he that said to him, Thou art my Son, to-day have I begotten thee. 6 As he saith also in another place , Thou art a priest for ever after the order of Melchisedec. 7 Who in the days of his flesh, when he had offered up prayers and supplications with strong crying and tears to him that was able to save him from death, and was heard, in that he feared; 8 Though he was a Son, yet he learned obedience by the things which he suffered; 9 And being made perfect, he became the author of eternal salvation to all them that obey him; 10 Called by God a high priest after the order of Melchisedec. 11 Of whom we have many things to say, and hard to be uttered, seeing ye are dull of hearing. 12 For when for the time ye ought to be teachers, ye have need of one to teach you again which are the first principles of the oracles of God; and are become such as have need of milk, and not of strong food. 13 For every one that useth milk, is unskillful in the word of righteousness: for he is a babe. 14 But strong food belongeth to them that are of full age, even those who by reason of use have their senses exercised to discern both good and evil.

6

1 Therefore leaving the principles of the doctrine of Christ, let us go on to perfection; not laying again the foundation of repentance from dead works, and of faith towards God, 2 Of the doctrine of baptisms, and of laying on of hands, and of the resurrection of the dead, and of eternal judgment. 3 And this will we do, if God permit. 4 For it is impossible for those who have been once enlightened, and have tasted the heavenly gift, and have been made partakers of the Holy Spirit. 5 And have tasted the good word of God, and the powers of the world to come, 6 If they shall fall away, to renew them again to repentance; seeing they crucify to themselves the Son of God afresh, and put him to an open shame. 7 For the earth which drinketh in the rain that cometh often upon it, and bringeth forth herbs fit for them by whom it is dressed, receiveth blessing from God: 8 But that which beareth thorns and briers is rejected, and is nigh to cursing; whose end is to be burned. 9 But, beloved, we are persuaded better things of you, and things that accompany salvation, though we thus speak. 10 For God is not unrighteous to forget your work and labor of love, which ye have shown towards his name, in that ye have ministered to the saints, and do minister. 11 And we desire every one of you to show the same diligence to the full assurance of hope to the end: 12 That ye be not slothful, but followers of them who through faith and patience inherit the promises. 13 For when God made promise to Abraham, because he could swear by no greater, he swore by himself, 14 Saying, Surely blessing I will bless thee, and multiplying I will multiply thee. 15 And so, after he had patiently endured, he obtained the promise. 16 For men verily swear by the greater: and an oath for confirmation is to them an end of all contradiction. 17 Wherein God, willing more abundantly to show to the heirs of promise the immutability of his counsel, confirmed it by an oath: 18 That by two immutable things, in which it was impossible for God to lie, we might have a strong consolation, who have fled for refuge to lay hold upon the hope set before us: 19 Which hope we have as an anchor of the soul, both sure and steadfast, and which entereth into that within the vail; 20 Whither the forerunner hath for us entered, even Jesus, made a high priest for ever after the order of Melchisedec.

7

1 For this Melchisedec, king of Salem, priest of the most high God, who met Abraham returning from the slaughter of the kings, and blessed him; 2 To whom also Abraham gave a tenth part of all; first being by interpretation King of righteousness, and after that also King of Salem, which is, King of peace; 3 Without father, without mother, without descent, having neither beginning of days, nor end of life; but made like to the Son of God; abideth a priest continually. 4 Now consider how great this man was , to whom even the patriarch Abraham gave the tenth of the spoils. 5 And verily they that are of the sons of Levi, who receive the office of the priesthood, have a commandment to take tithes from the people according to the law, that is, from their brethren, though they come from the loins of Abraham: 6 But he whose descent is not counted from them received tithes from Abraham, and blessed him that had the promises. 7 And without all contradiction the less is blessed by the better. 8 And here men that die receive tithes; but there he receiveth them , of whom it is testified that he liveth. 9 And as I may say, Levi also, who receiveth tithes, payed tithes in Abraham. 10 For he was yet in the loins of his father, when Melchisedec met him. 11 If therefore perfection were by the Levitical priesthood (for under it the people received the law) what further need was there that another priest should rise after the order of Melchisedec, and not be called after the order of Aaron? 12 For the priesthood being changed, there is made of necessity a change also of the law. 13 For he of whom these things are spoken pertaineth to another tribe, of which no man gave attendance at the altar. 14 For it is evident that our Lord sprang from Judah; of which tribe Moses spoke nothing concerning priesthood. 15 And it is yet far more evident: for that after the similitude of Melchisedec there ariseth another priest, 16 Who is made, not after the law of a carnal commandment, but after the power of an endless life. 17 For he testifieth, Thou art a priest for ever after the order of Melchisedec. 18 For there is verily a disannulling of the preceding commandment on account of its weakness and unprofitableness. 19 For the law made nothing perfect, but the introduction of a better hope did ; by which we draw nigh to God. 20 And inasmuch as not without an oath he was made priest : 21 (For those priests were made without an oath; but this with an oath, by him that said to him, The Lord swore, and will not repent, Thou art a priest for ever after the order of Melchisedec:) 22 By so much was Jesus made a surety of a better testament. 23 And they truly were many priests, because they were not suffered to continue by reason of death: 24 But this man , because he continueth ever, hath an unchangeable priesthood. 25 Wherefore he is able also to save them to the uttermost that come to God by him, seeing he ever liveth to make intercession for them. 26 For such a high priest became us, who is holy, harmless, undefiled, separate from sinners, and made higher than the heavens; 27 Who needeth not daily, as those high priests, to offer up sacrifice, first for his own sins, and then for the people's: for this he did once, when he offered up himself. 28 For the law maketh men high priests who have infirmity; but the word of the oath, which was after the law, maketh the Son, who is consecrated for evermore.

8

1 Now of the things which we have spoken this is the sum: We have such a high priest, who is set on the right hand of the throne of the Majesty in the heavens; 2 A minister of the sanctuary, and of the true tabernacle, which the Lord pitched, and not man. 3 For every high priest is ordained to offer gifts and sacrifices: wherefore it is of necessity that this man should have somewhat also to offer. 4 For if he were on earth, he would not be a priest, seeing there are priests that offer gifts according to the law: 5 Who serve to the example and shadow of heavenly things, as Moses was admonished by God when he was about to make the tabernacle: for, See (saith he) that thou make all things according to the pattern shown to thee in the mount. 6 But now hath he obtained a more excellent ministry, by how much also he is the mediator of a better covenant, which was established upon better promises. 7 For if that first covenant had been faultless, then would no place have been sought for the second. 8 For finding fault with them, he saith, Behold, the days come, saith the Lord, when I will make a new covenant with the house of Israel and with the house of Judah: 9 Not according to the covenant that I made with their fathers, in the day when I took them by the hand to lead them out of the land of Egypt; because they continued not in my covenant, and I regarded them not, saith the Lord. 10 For this is the covenant that I will make with the house of Israel after those days, saith the Lord; I will put my laws into their mind, and write them in their hearts: and I will be to them a God, and they shall be to me a people: 11 And they shall not teach every man his neighbor, and every man his brother, saying, Know the Lord: for all shall know me, from the least to the greatest. 12 For I will be merciful to their unrighteousness, and their sins and their iniquities will I remember no more. 13 In that he saith, A new covenant , he hath made the first old. Now that which decayeth and groweth old is ready to vanish away.

9

1 Then verily the first covenant had also ordinances of divine service, and a worldly sanctuary. 2 For there was a tabernacle made; the first, in which was the candlestick, and the table, and the show-bread; which is called the sanctuary. 3 And after the second vail, the tabernacle which is called the Holiest of all; 4 Which had the golden censer, and the ark of the covenant overlaid around with gold, in which was the golden pot that had manna, and Aaron's rod that budded, and the tables of the covenant; 5 And over it the cherubim of glory shadowing the mercy-seat; of which we cannot now speak particularly. 6 Now when these things were thus ordained, the priests went always into the first tabernacle, accomplishing the service of God : 7 But into the second went the high priest alone once every year, not without blood, which he offered for himself, and for the errors of the people: 8 The Holy Spirit this signifying, that the way into the holiest of all was not yet made manifest, while the first tabernacle was yet standing: 9 Which was a figure for the time then present, in which were offered both gifts and sacrifices, that could not make him that did the service perfect, as pertaining to the conscience; 10 Which stood only in meats and drinks, and divers washings, and carnal ordinances, imposed on them until the time of reformation. 11 But Christ being come a high priest of good things to come, by a greater and more perfect tabernacle, not made with hands, that is to say, not of this building; 12 Neither by the blood of goats and calves, but by his own blood; he entered in once into the holy place, having obtained eternal redemption for us . 13 For if the blood of bulls and of goats, and the ashes of a heifer sprinkling the unclean, sanctify to the purifying of the flesh: 14 How much more shall the blood of Christ, who through the eternal Spirit offered himself without spot to God, cleanse your conscience from dead works to serve the living God? 15 And for this cause he is the mediator of the new testament, that by means of death, for the redemption of the transgressions that were under the first testament, they who are called may receive the promise of eternal inheritance. 16 For where a testament is , there must also of necessity be the death of the testator. 17 For a testament is of force after men are dead: otherwise it is of no strength at all while the testator liveth. 18 Hence even the first testament was not dedicated without blood. 19 For when Moses had spoken every precept to all the people according to the law, he took the blood of calves and of goats, with water, and scarlet wool, and hyssop, and sprinkled both the book and all the people, 20 Saying, This is the blood of the testament which God hath enjoined to you. 21 Moreover, he sprinkled likewise with blood both the tabernacle, and all the vessels of the ministry. 22 And almost all things are by the law cleansed with blood; and without shedding of blood is no remission. 23 It was therefore necessary that the patterns of things in the heavens should be purified with these; but the heavenly things themselves with better sacrifices than these. 24 For Christ hath not entered into the holy places made with hands, which are the figures of the true; but into heaven itself, now to appear in the presence of God for us: 25 Nor yet that he should offer himself often, as the high priest entereth into the holy place every year with blood of others; 26 For then must he often have suffered since the foundation of the world: but now once in the end of the world hath he appeared to put away sin by the sacrifice of himself. 27 And as it is appointed to men once to die, but after this the judgment: 28 So Christ was once offered to bear the sins of many; and to them that look for him he will appear the second time without sin to salvation.

10

1 For the law having a shadow of good things to come, and not the very image of the things, can never with those sacrifices which they offered year by year continually make the comers to them perfect. 2 For then would they not have ceased to be offered? because that the worshipers once cleansed, would have had no more conscience of sins. 3 But in those sacrifices there is a remembrance again made of sins every year. 4 For it is not possible that the blood of bulls and of goats should take away sins. 5 Wherefore, when he cometh into the world, he saith, Sacrifice and offering thou wouldst not, but a body hast thou prepared me: 6 In burnt-offerings and sacrifices for sin thou hast had no pleasure. 7 Then said I, Lo, I come (in the volume of the book it is written concerning me,) to do thy will, O God. 8 Above, when he said, Sacrifice and offering and burnt-offerings and offering for sin thou wouldst not, neither hadst pleasure in them ; which are offered by the law; 9 Then said he, Lo, I come to do thy will, O God. He taketh away the first, that he may establish the second. 10 By which will we are sanctified through the offering of the body of Jesus Christ once for all . 11 And every priest standeth daily ministering and offering often the same sacrifices, which can never take away sins: 12 But this man, after he had offered one sacrifice for sins, for ever sat down on the right hand of God; 13 From henceforth waiting till his enemies are made his footstool. 14 For by one offering he hath perfected for ever them that are sanctified. 15 Of this the Holy Spirit also is a witness to us: for after that he had said before, 16 This is the covenant that I will make with them after those days, saith the Lord, I will put my laws into their hearts, and in their minds will I write them; 17 And their sins and iniquities will I remember no more. 18 Now where remission of these is , there is no more offering for sin. 19 Having therefore, brethren, boldness to enter into the holiest by the blood of Jesus, 20 By a new and living way, which he hath consecrated for us, through the vail, that is to say, his flesh; 21 And having a high priest over the house of God; 22 Let us draw near with a true heart in full assurance of faith, having our hearts sprinkled from an evil conscience, and our bodies washed with pure water. 23 Let us hold fast the profession of our faith without wavering; for he is faithful that promised: 24 And let us consider one another to excite to love and to good works: 25 Not forsaking the assembling of ourselves, as the manner of some is ; but exhorting one another : and so much the more, as ye see the day approaching. 26 For if we sin willfully after we have received the knowledge of the truth, there remaineth no more sacrifice for sins, 27 But a certain fearful apprehension of judgment and fiery indignation, which shall devour the adversaries. 28 He that despised Moses' law, died without mercy under two or three witnesses: 29 Of how much more severe punishment, suppose ye, shall he be thought worthy, who hath trodden under foot the Son of God, and hath counted the blood of the covenant, by which he was sanctified, an unholy thing, and hath done despite to the Spirit of grace? 30 For we know him that hath said, Vengeance belongeth to me, I will recompense, saith the Lord. And again, The Lord will judge his people. 31 It is a fearful thing to fall into the hands of the living God. 32 But call to remembrance the former days, in which, after ye were illuminated, ye endured a great fight of afflictions; 33 Partly, while ye were made a gazing-stock both by reproaches and afflictions; and partly, while ye became companions of them that were so used. 34 For ye had compassion of me in my bonds, and took joyfully the seizing of your goods, knowing in yourselves that ye have in heaven a better and an enduring substance. 35 Cast not away therefore your confidence, which hath great recompense of reward. 36 For ye have need of patience, that, after ye have done the will of God, ye may receive the promise. 37 For yet a little while, and he that is coming will come, and will not tarry. 38 Now the just shall live by faith: but if any man shall draw back, my soul shall have no pleasure in him. 39 But we are not of them who draw back to perdition; but of them that believe to the saving of the soul.

11

1 Now faith is the substance of things hoped for, the evidence of things not seen. 2 For by it the elders obtained a good report. 3 Through faith we understand that the worlds were framed by the word of God, so that things which are seen were not made of things which appeared. 4 By faith Abel offered to God a more excellent sacrifice than Cain, by which he obtained testimony that he was righteous, God testifying of his gifts: and by it he being dead yet speaketh. 5 By faith Enoch was translated, that he should not see death; and was not found, because God had translated him: for before his translation he had this testimony, that he pleased God. 6 But without faith it is impossible to please him : for he that cometh to God must believe that he is, and that he is a rewarder of them that diligently seek him. 7 By faith Noah, being warned by God of things not seen as yet, moved with fear, prepared an ark to the saving of his house; by which he condemned the world, and became heir of the righteousness which is by faith. 8 By faith Abraham, when he was called to remove into a place which he should afterwards receive for an inheritance, obeyed; and he went out not knowing whither he was going. 9 By faith he sojourned in the land of promise, as in a foreign country, dwelling in tabernacles with Isaac and Jacob, the heirs with him of the same promise: 10 For he looked for a city which hath foundations, whose builder and maker is God. 11 Through faith also Sarah herself received strength to conceive seed, and was delivered of a child when she was past age, because she judged him faithful who had promised. 12 Therefore there sprang even from one, and him as good as dead, so many as the stars of the sky in multitude, and as the sand which is by the sea-shore innumerable. 13 These all died in faith, not having received the promises, but having seen them afar off, and were persuaded of them , and embraced them , and confessed that they were strangers and pilgrims on the earth. 14 For they that say such things declare plainly that they seek a country. 15 And truly, if they had been mindful of that country from whence they came, they might have had opportunity to return. 16 But now they desire a better country , that is, a heavenly: wherefore God is not ashamed to be called their God; for he hath prepared for them a city. 17 By faith Abraham, when he was tried, offered up Isaac: and he that had received the promises offered up his only-begotten son , 18 Of whom it was said, That in Isaac shall thy seed be called: 19 Accounting that God was able to raise him even from the dead; from whence also he received him in a figure. 20 By faith Isaac blessed Jacob and Esau concerning things to come. 21 By faith Jacob, when he was dying, blessed both the sons of Joseph; and worshiped, leaning upon the top of his staff. 22 By faith Joseph, when he died, made mention of the departing of the children of Israel; and gave commandment concerning his bones. 23 By faith Moses when he was born, was hid three months by his parents, because they saw he was a proper child; and they were not afraid of the king's commandment. 24 By faith Moses, when he had come to years, refused to be called the son of Pharaoh's daughter; 25 Choosing rather to suffer affliction with the people of God, than to enjoy the pleasures of sin for a season; 26 Esteeming the reproach of Christ greater riches than the treasures of Egypt: for he had respect to the recompense of the reward. 27 By faith he forsook Egypt, not fearing the wrath of the king: for he endured, as seeing him who is invisible. 28 Through faith he kept the passover, and the sprinkling of blood, lest he that destroyed the first-born should touch them. 29 By faith they passed through the Red sea as by dry land : which the Egyptians essaying to do were drowned. 30 By faith the walls of Jericho fell down after they had been encompassed seven days. 31 By faith the harlot Rahab perished not with them that believed not, as she had received the spies with peace. 32 And what shall I say more? for the time would fail me to tell of Gideon, and of Barak, and of Samson, and of Jephthah, of David also, and Samuel, and of the prophets: 33 Who through faith subdued kingdoms, wrought righteousness, obtained promises, stopped the mouths of lions, 34 Quenched the violence of fire, escaped the edge of the sword, out of weakness were made strong, became valiant in fight, turned to flight the armies of the aliens. 35 Women received their dead raised to life again: and others were tortured, not accepting deliverance; that they might obtain a better resurrection: 36 And others had trial of cruel mockings and scourgings, and, moreover of bonds and imprisonment: 37 They were stoned, they were sawn asunder, were tempted, were slain with the sword: they wandered about in sheep-skins, and goat-skins; being destitute, afflicted, tormented; 38 (Of whom the world was not worthy:) they wandered in deserts, and in mountains, and in dens and caves of the earth. 39 And these all, having obtained a good report through faith, received not the promise: 40 God having provided some better thing for us, that they without us should not be made perfect.

12

1 Wherefore, seeing we also are encompassed with so great a cloud of witnesses, let us lay aside every weight, and the sin which doth so easily beset us , and let us run with patience the race that is set before us, 2 Looking to Jesus the author and finisher of our faith; who for the joy that was set before him endured the cross, despising the shame, and is set down at the right hand of the throne of God. 3 For consider him that endured such contradiction of sinners against himself, lest ye be wearied and faint in your minds. 4 Ye have not yet resisted to blood, striving against sin. 5 And ye have forgotten the exhortation which speaketh to you as to children, My son, despise not thou the chastening of the Lord, nor faint when thou art rebuked by him: 6 For whom the Lord loveth he chasteneth, and scourgeth every son whom he receiveth. 7 If ye endure chastening, God dealeth with you as with sons: for what son is he whom the father chasteneth not? 8 But if ye are without chastisement, of which all are partakers, then are ye bastards and not sons. 9 Furthermore, we have had fathers of our flesh who corrected us , and we gave them reverence: shall we not much rather be in subjection to the Father of spirits, and live? 10 For they verily for a few days chastened us after their own pleasure; but he for our profit, that we might be partakers of his holiness. 11 Now no chastening for the present seemeth to be joyous, but grievous: nevertheless, afterward it yieldeth the peaceable fruit of righteousness to them who are exercised by it. 12 Wherefore lift up the hands which hang down, and the feeble knees; 13 And make straight paths for your feet, lest that which is lame be turned out of the way; but let it rather be healed. 14 Follow peace with all men , and holiness, without which no man shall see the Lord: 15 Looking diligently, lest any man fail of the grace of God; lest any root of bitterness springing up, trouble you , and by it many be defiled; 16 Lest there be any fornicator, or profane person, as Esau, who for one morsel of food sold his birth-right. 17 For ye know that afterward, when he would have inherited the blessing, he was rejected: for he found no place of repentance, though he sought it carefully with tears. 18 For ye are not come to the mount that might be touched, and that burned with fire, nor to blackness, and to darkness, and tempest, 19 And the sound of a trumpet, and the voice of words; which voice they that heard, entreated that the word should not be spoken to them any more: 20 (For they could not endure that which was commanded, And if so much as a beast touch the mountain, it shall be stoned, or thrust through with a dart: 21 And so terrible was the sight, that Moses said, I exceedingly fear and tremble:) 22 But ye are come to mount Sion, and to the city of the living God, the heavenly Jerusalem, and to an innumerable company of angels, 23 To the general assembly and church of the first-born, who are written in heaven, and to God the Judge of all, and to the spirits of just men made perfect, 24 And to Jesus the mediator of the new covenant, and to the blood of sprinkling, that speaketh better things than that of Abel. 25 See that ye refuse not him that speaketh. For if they escaped not who refused him that spoke on earth, much more shall not we escape , if we turn away from him that speaketh from heaven: 26 Whose voice then shook the earth: but now he hath promised, saying, Yet once more I shake not the earth only, but also heaven. 27 And this word , Yet once more, signifieth the removing of those things that are shaken, as of things that are made, that those things which cannot be shaken may remain. 28 Wherefore we receiving a kingdom which cannot be moved, let us have grace, by which we may serve God acceptably, with reverence and godly fear. 29 For our God is a consuming fire.

13

1 Let brotherly love continue. 2 Be not forgetful to entertain strangers: for by this some have entertained angels unawares. 3 Remember them that are in bonds, as bound with them; and them who suffer adversity, as being yourselves also in the body. 4 Marriage is honorable in all, and the bed undefiled: but lewd persons and adulterers God will judge. 5 Let your manner of life be without covetousness; and be content with such things as ye have: for he hath said, I will never leave thee, nor forsake thee. 6 So that we may boldly say, The Lord is my helper, and I will not fear what man shall do to me. 7 Remember them who have the rule over you, who have spoken to you the word of God: whose faith follow, considering the end of their manner of life. 8 Jesus Christ the same yesterday, and to-day, and for ever. 9 Be not carried about with divers and strange doctrines: for it is a good thing that the heart be established with grace; not with meats, which have not profited them that have been occupied in them. 10 We have an altar, of which they have no right to eat who serve the tabernacle. 11 For the bodies of those beasts, whose blood is brought into the sanctuary by the high priest for sin, are burned without the camp. 12 Wherefore Jesus also, that he might sanctify the people with his own blood, suffered without the gate. 13 Let us go forth therefore to him without the camp, bearing his reproach. 14 For here we have no continuing city, but we seek one to come. 15 By him therefore let us offer the sacrifice of praise to God continually, that is, the fruit of our lips, giving thanks to his name. 16 But to do good, and to communicate, forget not: for with such sacrifices God is well pleased. 17 Obey them that have the rule over you, and submit yourselves: for they watch for your souls, as they that must give account, that they may do it with joy, and not with grief: for that is unprofitable for you. 18 Pray for us: for we trust we have a good conscience, in all things willing to live honestly. 19 But I beseech you the rather to do this, that I may be restored to you the sooner. 20 Now the God of peace, that brought again from the dead our Lord Jesus, that great Shepherd of the sheep, through the blood of the everlasting covenant, 21 Make you perfect in every good work to do his will, working in you that which is well-pleasing in his sight, through Jesus Christ; to whom be glory for ever and ever. Amen. 22 And I beseech you, brethren, suffer the word of exhortation: for I have written a letter to you in few words. 23 Know ye, that our brother Timothy is set at liberty; with whom, if he come shortly, I will see you. 24 Salute all them that have the rule over you, and all the saints. They of Italy salute you. 25 Grace be with you all. Amen.

Luke

1
2
3
4
5
6
7
8
9
10

11
12
13
14
15
16
17
18
19
20

21
22
23
24

THE GOSPEL ACCORDING TO ST. LUKE

1

1 Forasmuch as many have taken in hand to set forth in order a declaration of those things which are most surely believed among us, 2 Even as they delivered them to us, who from the beginning were eye-witnesses, and ministers of the word; 3 It seemed good to me also, having had perfect understanding of all things from the very first, to write to thee in order, most excellent Theophilus, 4 That thou mayest know the certainty of those things in which thou hast been instructed. 5 There was in the days of Herod the king of Judea, a certain priest named Zacharias, of the course of Abia: and his wife was of the daughters of Aaron, and her name was Elisabeth. 6 And they were both righteous before God, walking in all the commandments and ordinances of the Lord blameless. 7 And they had no child, because Elisabeth was barren, and they both were far advanced in years. 8 And it came to pass, that, while he executed the priests' office before God in the order of his course, 9 According to the custom of the priests' office, his lot was to burn incense when he went into the temple of the Lord. 10 And the whole multitude of the people were praying without, at the time of incense. 11 And there appeared to him an angel of the Lord, standing on the right side of the altar of incense. 12 And when Zacharias saw him , he was troubled, and fear fell upon him. 13 But the angel said to him, Fear not, Zacharias: for thy prayer is heard; and thy wife Elisabeth shall bear thee a son, and thou shalt call his name John. 14 And thou shalt have joy and gladness, and many shall rejoice at his birth. 15 For he shall be great in the sight of the Lord, and shall drink neither wine nor strong drink; and he shall be filled with the Holy Spirit, even from his mother's womb. 16 And many of the children of Israel shall he turn to the Lord their God. 17 And he shall go before him in the spirit and power of Elijah, to turn the hearts of the fathers to the children, and the disobedient to the wisdom of the just; to make ready a people prepared for the Lord. 18 And Zacharias said to the angel, By what shall I know this? for I am an old man, and my wife far advanced in years. 19 And the angel answering, said to him, I am Gabriel, who stand in the presence of God; and am sent to speak to thee, and to show thee these glad tidings. 20 And behold, thou shalt be dumb, and not able to speak, until the day that these things shall be performed, because thou believest not my words which shall be fulfilled in their season. 21 And the people waited for Zacharias, and marveled that he tarried so long in the temple. 22 And when he came out, he could not speak to them: and they perceived that he had seen a vision in the temple; for he beckoned to them, and remained speechless. 23 And it came to pass, that as soon as the days of his ministration were accomplished, he departed to his own house. 24 And after those days his wife Elisabeth conceived, and secluded herself five months, saying, 25 Thus hath the Lord dealt with me in the days in which he looked on me , to take away my reproach among men. 26 And in the sixth month, the angel Gabriel was sent from God to a city of Galilee, named Nazareth, 27 To a virgin espoused to a man whose name was Joseph, of the house of David; and the virgin's name was Mary. 28 And the angel came to her, and said, Hail, thou that art highly favored, the Lord is with thee: blessed art thou among women. 29 And when she saw him , she was troubled at his saying, and cast in her mind what manner of salutation this should be. 30 And the angel said to her, Fear not, Mary: for thou hast found favor with God. 31 And behold, thou shalt conceive in thy womb, and bring forth a son, and shalt call his name JESUS. 32 He will be great, and will be called the Son of the Highest; and the Lord God will give to him the throne of his father David. 33 And he will reign over the house of Jacob for ever, and of his kingdom there will be no end. 34 Then said Mary to the angel, How shall this be, seeing I know not a man? 35 And the angel answered and said to her, The Holy Spirit will come upon thee, and the power of the Highest will overshadow thee: therefore also that holy thing which shall be born of thee shall be called the Son of God. 36 And behold, thy cousin Elisabeth, she hath also conceived a son in her old age; and this is the sixth month with her who was called barren: 37 For with God nothing will be impossible. 38 And Mary said, Behold the handmaid of the Lord, be it to me according to thy word. And the angel departed from her. 39 And Mary arose in those days, and went into the hill-country with haste, into a city of Judah, 40 And entered into the house of Zacharias, and saluted Elisabeth. 41 And it came to pass, that when Elisabeth heard the salutation of Mary, the babe leaped in her womb: and Elisabeth was filled with the Holy Spirit. 42 And she spoke with a loud voice, and said, Blessed art thou among women, and blessed is the fruit of thy womb. 43 And whence is this to me, that the mother of my Lord should come to me? 44 For lo, as soon as the voice of thy salutation sounded in my ears, the babe leaped in my womb for joy. 45 And blessed is she that believed that there will be a performance of those things which were told her from the Lord. 46 And Mary said, My soul doth magnify the Lord, 47 And my spirit hath rejoiced in God my Savior. 48 For he hath regarded the low estate of his handmaiden: for behold, from henceforth all generations will call me blessed. 49 For he that is mighty hath done to me great things, and holy is his name. 50 And his mercy is on them that fear him, from generation to generation. 51 He hath shown strength with his arm; he hath scattered the proud in the imagination of their hearts. 52 He hath put down the mighty from their seats, and exalted them of low degree. 53 He hath filled the hungry with good things, and the rich he hath sent away empty. 54 He hath sustained his servant Israel, in remembrance of his mercy; 55 As he spoke to our fathers, to Abraham, and to his seed for ever. 56 And Mary abode with her about three months, and returned to her own house. 57 Now Elisabeth's full time came that she should be delivered; and she brought forth a son. 58 And her neighbors and her cousins heard that the Lord had shown great mercy upon her; and they rejoiced with her. 59 And it came to pass, that on the eighth day they came to circumcise the child; and they called him Zacharias, after the name of his father. 60 And his mother answered and said, Not so ; but he shall be called John. 61 And they said to her, There is none of thy kindred that is called by this name. 62 And they made signs to his father, how he would have him called. 63 And he asked for a writing-table, and wrote, saying, His name is John. And they all wondered. 64 And his mouth was opened immediately, and his tongue loosed , and he spoke, and praised God. 65 And fear came on all that dwelt around them; and all these sayings were noised abroad throughout all the hill-country of Judea. 66 And all they that had heard them , laid them up in their hearts, saying, What manner of child will this be! And the hand of the Lord was with him. 67 And his father Zacharias was filled with the Holy Spirit, and prophesied, saying, 68 Blessed be the Lord God of Israel; for he hath visited and redeemed his people. 69 And hath raised up a horn of salvation for us, in the house of his servant David: 70 As he spoke by the mouth of his holy prophets, who have been since the world began: 71 That we should be saved from our enemies, and from the hand of all that hate us; 72 To perform the mercy promised to our fathers, and to remember his holy covenant: 73 The oath which he swore to our father Abraham, 74 That he would grant to us, that we being delivered out of the hand of our enemies, might serve him without fear, 75 In holiness and righteousness before him, all the days of our life. 76 And thou, child, shalt be called the prophet of the Highest, for thou shalt go before the face of the Lord to prepare his ways; 77 To give knowledge of salvation to his people, by the remission of their sins, 78 Through the tender mercy of our God; by which the day-spring from on high hath visited us, 79 To give light to them that sit in darkness and in the shades of death, to guide our feet into the way of peace. 80 And the child grew, and became strong in spirit, and was in the deserts till the day of his showing to Israel.

2

1 And it came to pass in those days, that there went out a decree from Cesar Augustus, that all the world should be taxed. 2 (And this taxing was first made when Cyrenius was governor of Syria.) 3 And all went to be taxed, every one into his own city. 4 And Joseph also went up from Galilee, out of the city of Nazareth, into Judea, to the city of David, which is called Bethlehem; (because he was of the house and lineage of David) 5 To be taxed with Mary his espoused wife, being great with child. 6 And so it was, that while they were there, the days were accomplished that she should be delivered. 7 And she brought forth her first-born son, and wrapped him in swaddling-clothes, and laid him in a manger; because there was no room for them in the inn. 8 And there were in the same country shepherds abiding in the field, keeping watch over their flock by night. 9 And lo, the angel of the Lord came upon them, and the glory of the Lord shone around them; and they were in great fear. 10 And the angel said to them, Fear not: for behold, I bring you good tidings of great joy which shall be to all people. 11 For to you is born this day, in the city of David, a Savior, who is Christ the Lord. 12 And this shall be a sign to you; Ye shall find the babe wrapped in swaddling-clothes, lying in a manger. 13 And suddenly there was with the angel a multitude of the heavenly host praising God, and saying, 14 Glory to God in the highest, and on earth peace, good will towards men. 15 And it came to pass, when the angels had departed from them into heaven, the shepherds said one to another, Let us now go even to Bethlehem, and see this thing which is come to pass, which the Lord hath made known to us. 16 And they came with haste, and found Mary and Joseph, and the babe lying in a manger. 17 And when they had seen it , they made known abroad the saying which was told them concerning this child. 18 And all they that heard it , wondered at those things which were told them by the shepherds. 19 But Mary kept all these things, and pondered them in her heart. 20 And the shepherds returned, glorifying and praising God for all the things that they had heard and seen, as it was told to them. 21 And when eight days were accomplished for the circumcising of the child, his name was called JESUS, who was so named by the angel before he was conceived in the womb. 22 And when the days of her purification according to the law of Moses were accomplished, they brought him to Jerusalem, to present him to the Lord; 23 (As it is written in the law of the Lord, Every male that is the first born of his mother shall be called holy to the Lord) 24 And to offer a sacrifice according to that which is said in the law of the Lord, A pair of turtle-doves, or two young pigeons. 25 And behold, there was a man in Jerusalem, whose name was Simeon; and the same man was just and devout, waiting for the consolation of Israel: and the Holy Spirit was upon him. 26 And it was revealed to him by the Holy Spirit, that he should not see death, before he had seen the Lord's Christ. 27 And he came by the spirit into the temple; and when the parents brought in the child Jesus, to do for him after the custom of the law, 28 Then he took him up in his arms, and blessed God, and said, 29 Lord, now lettest thou thy servant depart in peace, according to thy word: 30 For my eyes have seen thy salvation, 31 Which thou hast prepared before the face of all people; 32 A light to enlighten the Gentiles, and the glory of thy people Israel. 33 And Joseph and his mother marveled at those things which were spoken concerning him. 34 And Simeon blessed them, and said to Mary his mother, Behold, this child is set for the fall and rising again of many in Israel; and for a sign which shall be spoken against; 35 (And a sword shall pierce through thy own soul also) that the thoughts of many hearts may be revealed. 36 And there was one Anna, a prophetess, the daughter of Phanuel, of the tribe of Asher: she was of a great age, and had lived with a husband seven years from her virginity; 37 And she was a widow of about eighty four years, who departed not from the temple, but served God with fastings and prayers night and day. 38 And she coming in that instant, gave thanks likewise to the Lord, and spoke of him to all them that looked for redemption in Jerusalem. 39 And when they had performed all things according to the law of the Lord, they returned into Galilee, to their own city Nazareth. 40 And the child grew, and became strong in spirit, filled with wisdom: and the grace of God was upon him. 41 Now his parents went to Jerusalem every year at the feast of the passover. 42 And when he was twelve years old, they went up to Jerusalem according to the custom of the feast. 43 And when they had fulfilled the days, as they returned, the child Jesus tarried behind in Jerusalem; and Joseph and his mother knew not of it . 44 But they, supposing him to be in the company, went a day's journey; and they sought him among their relations and acquaintance. 45 And when they found him not, they returned to Jerusalem, seeking him. 46 And it came to pass, that after three days they found him in the temple, sitting in the midst of the doctors, both hearing them, and asking them questions. 47 And all that heard him were astonished at his understanding and answers. 48 And when they saw him, they were amazed: and his mother said to him, Son, why hast thou thus dealt with us? behold, thy father and I have sought thee sorrowing. 49 And he said to them, How is it that ye sought me? knew ye not that I must be about my Father's business? 50 And they understood not the saying which he spoke to them. 51 And he went down with them, and came to Nazareth, and was subject to them: but his mother kept all these sayings in her heart. 52 And Jesus increased in wisdom and stature, and in favor with God and man.

3

1 Now in the fifteenth year of the reign of Tiberius Cesar, Pontius Pilate being governor of Judea, and Herod being tetrarch of Galilee, and his brother Philip tetrarch of Iturea and of the region of Trachonitis, and Lysanius the tetrarch of Abilene, 2 Annas and Caiaphas being the high priests, the word of God came to John the son of Zacharias in the wilderness. 3 And he came into all the country about Jordan, preaching the baptism of repentance, for the remission of sins; 4 As it is written in the book of the words of Isaiah the prophet, saying, The voice of one crying in the wilderness, Prepare ye the way of the Lord, make his paths straight. 5 Every valley shall be filled, and every mountain and hill shall be brought low; and the crooked shall be made straight, and the rough ways shall be made smooth; 6 And all flesh shall see the salvation of God. 7 Then said he to the multitude that came forth to be baptized by him, O generation of vipers, who hath warned you to flee from the wrath to come? 8 Bring forth therefore fruits worthy of repentance, and begin not to say within yourselves, We have Abraham for our father: for I say to you, that God is able of these stones to raise up children to Abraham. 9 And now also the ax is laid to the root of the trees: every tree therefore which bringeth not forth good fruit, is hewn down, and cast into the fire. 10 And the people asked him, saying, What shall we do then? 11 He answereth and saith to them, He that hath two coats, let him impart to him that hath none; and he that hath provisions, let him do likewise. 12 Then came also publicans to be baptized, and said to him, Master, what shall we do? 13 And he said to them, Exact no more than that which is appointed you. 14 And the soldiers likewise asked him, saying, And what shall we do? And he said to them, Do violence to no man, neither accuse any falsely, and be content with your wages. 15 And as the people were in expectation, and all men mused in their hearts concerning John, whether he was the Christ, or not; 16 John answered, saying to them all, I indeed baptize you with water; but one mightier than I cometh, the latchet of whose shoes I am not worthy to unloose: he will baptize you with the Holy Spirit, and with fire: 17 Whose fan is in his hand, and he will thoroughly cleanse his floor, and will gather the wheat into his granary; but the chaff he will burn with fire unquenchable. 18 And many other things in his exhortation he preached to the people. 19 But Herod the tetrarch, being reproved by him on account of Herodias, his brother Philip's wife, and for all the evils which Herod had done, 20 Added yet this above all, that he shut up John in prison. 21 Now when all the people were baptized, it came to pass, that Jesus also being baptized, and praying, the heaven was opened, 22 And the Holy Spirit descended in a bodily shape like a dove upon him, and a voice came from heaven, which said, Thou art my beloved Son; in thee I am well pleased. 23 And Jesus himself began to be about thirty years of age, being (as was supposed) the son of Joseph, who was the son of Heli, 24 Who was the son of Matthat, who was the son of Levi, who was the son of Melchi, who was the son of Janna, who was the son of Joseph, 25 Who was the son of Mattathias, who was the son of Amos, who was the son of Naum, who was the son of Esli, who was the son of Nagge, 26 Who was the son of Maath, who was the son of Mattathias, who was the son of Semei, who was the son of Joseph, who was the son of Juda, 27 Who was the son of Joanna, who was the son of Rhesa, who was the son of Zorobabel, who was the son of Salathiel, who was the son of Neri, 28 Who was the son of Melchi, who was the son of Addi, who was the son of Cosam, who was the son of Elmodam, who was the son of Er, 29 Who was the son of Jose, who was the son of Eliezer, who was the son of Jorim, who was the son of Matthat, who was the son of Levi, 30 Who was the son of Simeon, who was the son of Judah, who was the son of Joseph, who was the son of Jonan, who was the son of Eliakim, 31 Who was the son of Melea, who was the son of Menan, who was the son of Mattatha, who was the son of Nathan, who was the son of David, 32 Who was the son of Jesse, who was the son of Obed, who was the son of Booz, who was the son of Salmon, who was the son of Naasson, 33 Who was the son of Aminadab, who was the son of Aram, who was the son of Esrom, who was the son of Phares, who was the son of Judah, 34 Who was the son of Jacob, who was the son of Isaac, who was the son of Abraham, who was the son of Terah, who was the son of Nahor, 35 Who was the son of Serug, who was the son of Reu, who was the son of Peleg, who was the son of Heber, who was the son of Sala, 36 Who was the son of Cainan, who was the son of Arphaxad, who was the son of Shem, who was the son of Noah, who was the son of Lamech, 37 Who was the son of Methuselah, who was the son of Enoch, who was the son of Jared, who was the son of Maleleel, who was the son of Cainan, 38 Who was the son of Enos, who was the son of Seth, who was the son of Adam, who was the son of God.

4

1 And Jesus being full of the Holy Spirit, returned from Jordan, and was led by the Spirit into the wilderness, 2 Being forty days tempted by the devil. And in those days he ate nothing; and when they were ended, he was afterward hungry. 3 And the devil said to him, If thou art the Son of God, command this stone that it be made bread. 4 And Jesus answered him, saying, It is written, That man shall not live by bread alone, but by every word of God. 5 And the devil taking him up upon a high mountain, showed to him all the kingdoms of the world in a moment of time. 6 And the devil said to him, All this power will I give thee, and the glory of them: for that is delivered to me, and to whomsoever I will, I give it. 7 If thou therefore wilt worship me, all shall be thine. 8 And Jesus answered and said to him, Get thee behind me, Satan: for it is written, Thou shalt worship the Lord thy God, and him only shalt thou serve. 9 And he brought him to Jerusalem, and set him on a pinnacle of the temple, and said to him, If thou art the son of God, cast thyself down from hence. 10 For it is written, He will give his angels charge over thee, to keep thee: 11 And in their hands they will bear thee up, lest at any time thou dash thy foot against a stone. 12 And Jesus answering, said to him, It is said, Thou shalt not tempt the Lord thy God. 13 And when the devil had ended all the temptation, he departed from him for a season. 14 And Jesus returned in the power of the spirit into Galilee: and there went out a fame of him through all the surrounding region. 15 And he taught in their synagogues, being glorified by all. 16 And he came to Nazareth, where he had been brought up: and, as his custom was, he went into the synagogue on the sabbath, and stood up to read. 17 And there was delivered to him the book of the prophet Isaiah. And when he had opened the book, he found the place where it was written, 18 The spirit of the Lord is upon me, because he hath anointed me to preach the gospel to the poor; he hath sent me to heal the broken-hearted, to preach deliverance to the captives, and recovering of sight to the blind, to set at liberty them that are bruised, 19 To preach the acceptable year of the Lord. 20 And he closed the book, and he gave it again to the minister, and sat down. And the eyes of all them that were in the synagogue were fastened on him. 21 And he began to say to them, This day is this scripture fulfilled in your ears. 22 And all bore him testimony, and wondered at the gracious words which proceeded out of his mouth. And they said, Is not this Joseph's son? 23 And he said to them, Ye will surely say to me this proverb, Physician, heal thyself: whatever we have heard done in Capernaum, do also here in thy country. 24 And he said, Verily I say to you, No prophet is accepted in his own country. 25 But I tell you in truth, many widows were in Israel in the days of Elijah, when the heaven was shut three years and six months when great famine was throughout all the land: 26 But to none of them was Elijah sent, save to Sarepta, a city of Sidon, to a woman that was a widow. 27 And many lepers were in Israel in the time of Elisha the prophet; and none of them was cleansed, saving Naaman the Syrian. 28 And all they in the synagogue, when they heard these things, were filled with wrath, 29 And rose up, and thrust him out of the city, and led him to the brow of the hill on which their city was built, that they might cast him down headlong. 30 But he passing through the midst of them, went away, 31 And came down to Capernaum, a city of Galilee, and taught them on the sabbath-days. 32 And they were astonished at his doctrine: for his word was with power. 33 And in the synagogue there was a man who had a spirit of an unclean demon; and he cried out with a loud voice, 34 Saying, Let us alone; what have we to do with thee, Jesus of Nazareth? art thou come to destroy us? I know thee who thou art, the Holy One of God. 35 And Jesus rebuked him, saying, Hold thy peace, and come out of him. And when the demon had thrown him in the midst, he came out of him, and hurt him not. 36 And they were all amazed, and spoke among themselves, saying, What a word is this! for with authority and power he commandeth the unclean spirits, and they come out. 37 And the fame of him went out into every place of the surrounding country. 38 And he arose out of the synagogue, and entered into Simon's house. And the mother of Simon's wife was taken with a violent fever; and they besought him for her. 39 And he stood over her, and rebuked the fever; and it left her: and immediately she arose and ministered to them. 40 Now when the sun was setting, all they that had any sick with divers diseases, brought them to him: and he laid his hands on every one of them, and healed them. 41 And demons also came out of many, crying out, and saying, Thou art Christ the Son of God. And he rebuking them , suffered them not to speak: for they knew that he was Christ. 42 And when it was day, he departed, and went into a desert place; and the people sought him, and came to him, and stayed him, that he should not depart from them. 43 And he said to them, I must preach the kingdom of God to other cities also, for therefore am I sent. 44 And he preached in the synagogues of Galilee.

5

1 And it came to pass, that as the people pressed upon him to hear the word of God, he stood by the lake of Gennesaret. 2 And saw two boats standing by the lake: but the fishermen had gone out of them, and were washing their nets. 3 And he entered into one of the boats, which was Simon's, and prayed him that he would thrust out a little from the land. And he sat down, and taught the people out of the boat. 4 Now when he had left speaking, he said to Simon, Lanch out into the deep, and let down your nets for a draught. 5 And Simon answering said to him, Master, we have toiled all the night, and have taken nothing; nevertheless, at thy word I will let down the net. 6 And when they had done this, they inclosed a great multitude of fishes: and their net broke. 7 And they beckoned to their partners, who were in the other boat, that they should come and help them. And they came, and filled both the boats, so that they began to sink. 8 When Simon Peter saw it , he fell down at Jesus' knees, saying, Depart from me; for I am a sinful man, O Lord. 9 For he was astonished, and all that were with him, at the draught of the fishes which they had taken: 10 And so was also James and John the sons of Zebedee, who were partners with Simon. And Jesus said to Simon, Fear not: from henceforth thou shalt catch men. 11 And when they had brought their boats to land, they forsook all, and followed him. 12 And it came to pass, when he was in a certain city, behold, a man full of leprosy: who seeing Jesus, fell on his face, and besought him, saying, Lord, if thou wilt, thou canst make me clean. 13 And he put forth his hand, and touched him, saying, I will: Be thou clean. And immediately the leprosy departed from him. 14 And he charged him to tell no man: but go, and show thyself to the priest, and offer for thy cleansing, according as Moses commanded for a testimony to them. 15 But so much the more a fame of him went abroad: and great multitudes came together to hear and to be healed by him of their infirmities. 16 And he withdrew himself into the wilderness, and prayed. 17 And it came to pass on a certain day, as he was teaching, that there were Pharisees and doctors of the law sitting by, who had come out of every town of Galilee, and Judea, and Jerusalem: and the power of the Lord was present to heal them. 18 And behold, men brought in a bed a man who was taken with the palsy: and they sought means to bring him in, and to lay him before him. 19 And when they could not find by what way they might bring him in, because of the multitude, they went upon the house-top, and let him down through the tiling with his couch, into the midst before Jesus. 20 And when he saw their faith, he said to him, Man, thy sins are forgiven thee. 21 And the scribes and the Pharisees began to reason, saying, Who is this who speaketh blasphemies? Who can forgive sins but God alone? 22 But when Jesus perceived their thoughts, he answering, said to them, What reason ye in your hearts? 23 Which is easier, to say, Thy sins are forgiven thee; or to say, Rise and walk? 24 But that ye may know that the Son of man hath power upon earth to forgive sins, He said to the sick with the palsy, I say to thee, Arise, and take up thy couch, and go into thy house. 25 And immediately he arose before them, and took up that on which he lay, and departed to his own house, glorifying God. 26 And they were all amazed, and they glorified God, and were filled with fear, saying, We have seen strange things to-day. 27 And after these things he went forth, and saw a publican named Levi, sitting at the receipt of custom: and he said to him, Follow me. 28 And he left all, arose, and followed him. 29 And Levi made him a great feast in his own house; and there was a great company of publicans, and of others that sat down with them. 30 But their scribes and Pharisees murmured against his disciples, saying, Why do ye eat and drink with publicans and sinners? 31 And Jesus answering, said to them, They that are well need not a physician; but they that are sick. 32 I came not to call the righteous, but sinners to repentance. 33 And they said to him, Why do the disciples of John fast often, and make prayers, and likewise the disciples of the Pharisees; but thine eat and drink? 34 And he said to them, Can ye make the children of the bride-chamber fast, while the bridegroom is with them? 35 But the days will come, when the bridegroom shall be taken from them, and then they will fast in those days. 36 And he spoke also a parable to them: No man putteth a piece of a new garment upon an old: if otherwise, then both the new maketh a rent, and the piece that was taken out of the new, agreeth not with the old. 37 And no man putteth new wine into old bottles; else the new wine will burst the bottles, and be spilled, and the bottles will perish. 38 But new wine must be put into new bottles, and both are preserved. 39 No man also having drank old wine , immediately desireth new: for he saith, The old is better.

6

1 And it came to pass on the second sabbath after the first, that he went through corn-fields; and his disciples plucked the ears of corn, and ate, rubbing them in their hands. 2 And certain of the Pharisees said to them, Why do ye that which it is not lawful to do on the sabbath-days? 3 And Jesus answering them, said, Have ye not read so much as this, what David did, when himself was hungry, and they who were with him; 4 How he went into the house of God, and took and ate the show-bread, and gave also to them that were with him, which it is not lawful to eat but for the priests alone? 5 And he said to them, That the Son of man is Lord also of the sabbath. 6 And it came to pass also on another sabbath, that he entered into the synagogue, and taught: and there was a man whose right hand was withered: 7 And the scribes and Pharisees watched him, to see whether he would heal on the sabbath; that they might find an accusation against him. 8 But he knew their thoughts, and said to the man who had the withered hand, Rise, and stand forth in the midst. And he arose, and stood forth. 9 Then said Jesus to them, I will ask you one thing; Is it lawful on the sabbath-days to do good, or to do evil? to save life, or to destroy it ? 10 And looking around upon them all, he said to the man, Stretch forth thy hand. And he did so: and his hand was restored whole as the other. 11 And they were filled with madness; and communed one with another what they might do to Jesus. 12 And it came to pass in those days, that he went out to a mountain to pray, and continued all night in prayer to God. 13 And when it was day, he called to him his disciples: and of them he chose twelve, whom also he named Apostles; 14 Simon (whom he also named Peter) and Andrew his brother, James and John, and Philip and Bartholomew, 15 Matthew and Thomas, James the son of Alpheus, and Simon called Zelotes, 16 And Judas the brother of James, and Judas Iscariot, who also was the traitor. 17 And he came down with them, and stood in the plain; and the company of his disciples, and a great multitude of people out of all Judea and Jerusalem, and from the sea-coast of Tyre and Sidon, who came to hear him, and to be healed of their diseases; 18 And they that were afflicted with unclean spirits: and they were healed. 19 And the whole multitude sought to touch him; for there went virtue out of him, and healed them all. 20 And he lifted up his eyes on his disciples, and said, Blessed are ye poor: for yours is the kingdom of God. 21 Blessed are ye that hunger now: for ye shall be filled. Blessed are ye that weep now: for ye shall laugh. 22 Blessed are ye when men shall hate you, and when they shall separate you from their company , and shall reproach you , and cast out your name as evil, on account of the son of man. 23 Rejoice ye in that day, and leap for joy: for behold, your reward is great in heaven: for in the like manner did their fathers to the prophets. 24 But woe to you that are rich! for ye have received your consolation. 25 Woe to you that are full! for ye shall hunger. Woe to you that laugh now! for ye shall mourn and weep. 26 Woe to you, when all men shall speak well of you! for so did their fathers to the false prophets. 27 But I say to you who hear, Love your enemies, do good to them who hate you, 28 Bless them that curse you, and pray for them who despitefully use you. 29 And to him that smiteth thee on the one cheek, offer also the other; and him that taketh away thy cloke, forbid not to take thy coat also. 30 Give to every man that asketh of thee; and of him that taketh away thy goods, ask them not again. 31 And as ye would that men should do to you, do ye also to them likewise. 32 For if ye love them who love you, what thanks have ye? for sinners also love those that love them. 33 And if ye do good to them who do good to you, what thanks have ye? for sinners also do even the same. 34 And if ye lend to them from whom ye hope to receive, what thanks have ye? for sinners also lend to sinners, to receive as much in return. 35 But love ye your enemies, and do good, and lend, hoping for nothing again; and your reward shall be great, and ye shall be the children of the Highest: for he is kind to the unthankful and to the evil. 36 Be ye therefore merciful, as your Father also is merciful. 37 Judge not, and ye shall not be judged: condemn not, and ye shall not be condemned: forgive, and ye shall be forgiven: 38 Give, and it shall be given to you; good measure, pressed down, and shaken together, and running over, shall men give into your bosom. For with the same measure that ye give to others , it shall be measured to you again. 39 And he spoke a parable to them; Can the blind lead the blind? will they not both fall into the ditch? 40 The disciple is not above his master: but every one that is perfect, shall be as his master. 41 And why beholdest thou the mote that is in thy brother's eye, but perceivest not the beam that is in thy own eye? 42 Either how canst thou say to thy brother, Brother, let me pull out the mote that is in thy eye, when thou thyself beholdest not the beam that is in thy own eye? Thou hypocrite, cast out first the beam out of thy own eye, and then shalt thou see clearly to pull out the mote that is in thy brother's eye. 43 For a good tree bringeth not forth corrupt fruit; neither doth a corrupt tree bring forth good fruit. 44 For every tree is known by its own fruit: for from thorns men do not gather figs, nor from a bramble bush do they gather grapes. 45 A good man out of the good treasure of his heart, bringeth forth that which is good; and an evil man out of the evil treasure of his heart, bringeth forth that which is evil: for from the abundance of the heart his mouth speaketh. 46 And why call ye me Lord, Lord, and do not the things which I say? 47 Whoever cometh to me, and heareth my sayings, and doeth them, I will show you to whom he is like. 48 He is like a man who built a house, and digged deep, and laid the foundation on a rock: and when the flood arose, the stream beat vehemently upon that house, and could not shake it: for it was founded upon a rock. 49 But he that heareth, and doeth not, is like a man that, without a foundation, built a house on the earth, against which the stream beat vehemently, and immediately it fell, and the ruin of that house was great.

7

1 Now when he had ended all his sayings in the audience of the people, he entered into Capernaum. 2 And a certain centurion's servant, who was dear to him, was sick, and ready to die. 3 And when he heard of Jesus, he sent to him the elders of the Jews, beseeching him that he would come and heal his servant. 4 And when they came to Jesus, they besought him earnestly, saying, That he was worthy for whom he should do this: 5 For he loveth our nation, and he hath built us a synagogue. 6 Then Jesus went with them. And when he was now not far from the house, the centurion sent friends to him, saying to him, Lord, trouble not thyself: for I am not worthy that thou shouldest enter under my roof; 7 Wherefore neither thought I myself worthy to come to thee; but say in a word, and my servant shall be healed. 8 For I also am a man set under authority, having under me soldiers, and I say to one, Go, and he goeth; and to another, Come, and he cometh; and to my servant, Do this, and he doeth it . 9 When Jesus heard these things, he marveled at him, and turned himself about and said to the people that followed him, I say to you, I have not found so great faith, no, not in Israel. 10 And they that were sent, returning to the house, found the servant well that had been sick. 11 And it came to pass the day after, that he went into a city called Nain: and many of his disciples went with him, and many people. 12 Now when he came nigh to the gate of the city, behold, there was a dead man carried out, the only son of his mother, and she was a widow: and many people of the city were with her. 13 And when the Lord saw her, he had compassion on her, and said to her, Weep not. 14 And he came and touched the bier: And they that bore him stood still. And he said, Young man, I say to thee, Arise. 15 And he that was dead sat up, and began to speak, and he delivered him to his mother. 16 And there came a fear on all: and they glorified God, saying, That a great prophet hath risen among us; and, That God hath visited his people. 17 And this rumor of him went forth throughout all Judea, and throughout all the neighboring region. 18 And the disciples of John informed him of all these things. 19 And John calling two of his disciples sent them to Jesus, saying, Art thou he that should come? or look we for another? 20 When the men had come to him, they said, John the Baptist hath sent us to thee, saying, Art thou he that should come? or look we for another? 21 And in that same hour he cured many of their infirmities, and diseases, and of evil spirits; and to many that were blind he gave sight. 22 Then Jesus answering, said to them, Go, and tell John what things ye have seen and heard; that the blind see, the lame walk, lepers are cleansed, the deaf hear, the dead are raised, to the poor the gospel is preached. 23 And blessed is he , to whom I shall not be a stumbling block. 24 And when the messengers of John had departed, he began to speak to the people concerning John, What went ye out into the wilderness to see? A reed shaken with the wind? 25 But what went ye out to see? A man clothed in soft raiment? behold, they who are gorgeously appareled, and live delicately, are in kings' courts. 26 But what went ye out to see? A prophet? Yes, I say to you, and much more than a prophet. 27 This is he , concerning whom it is written, Behold, I send my messenger before thy face, who shall prepare thy way before thee. 28 For I say to you, Among those that are born of women, there is not a greater prophet than John the Baptist: but he that is least in the kingdom of God, is greater than he. 29 And all the people that heard him , and the publicans, justified God, being baptized with the baptism of John. 30 But the Pharisees and lawyers rejected the counsel of God against themselves, being not baptized by him. 31 And the Lord said, To what then shall I liken the men of this generation? and to what are they like? 32 They are like children sitting in the market-place, and calling one to another, and saying, We have piped to you, and ye have not danced; we have mourned to you, and ye have not wept. 33 For John the Baptist came neither eating bread, nor drinking wine; and ye say, He hath a demon. 34 The Son of man is come eating and drinking; and ye say, Behold, a gluttonous man, and a wine-bibber, a friend of publicans and sinners. 35 But wisdom is justified by all her children. 36 And one of the Pharisees desired him that he would eat with him. And he went into the Pharisee's house, and sat down at table. 37 And behold, a woman in the city, who was a sinner, when she knew that Jesus sat at table in the Pharisee's house, brought an alabaster-box of ointment, 38 And stood at his feet behind him weeping, and began to wash his feet with tears, and wiped them with the hairs of her head, and kissed his feet, and anointed them with the ointment. 39 Now when the Pharisee who had invited him, saw it , he spoke within himself, saying, This man, if he were a prophet, would have known who, and what manner of woman this is that toucheth him, for she is a sinner. 40 And Jesus answering, said to him, Simon, I have somewhat to say to thee. And he saith, Master, speak. 41 There was a certain creditor, who had two debtors: the one owed five hundred pence, and the other fifty. 42 And when they had nothing to pay, he frankly forgave them both. Tell me therefore, which of them will love him most? 43 Simon answered and said, I suppose that he , to whom he forgave most. And he said to him, Thou hast rightly judged. 44 And he turned to the woman, and said to Simon, Seest thou this woman? I entered into thy house, thou gavest me no water for my feet: but she hath washed my feet with tears, and wiped them with the hairs of her head. 45 Thou gavest me no kiss: but this woman, since the time I came in, hath not ceased to kiss my feet. 46 My head with oil thou didst not anoint: but this woman hath anointed my feet with ointment. 47 Wherefore I say to thee, Her sins, which are many, are forgiven; for she loved much: but to whom little is forgiven, the same loveth little. 48 And he said to her, Thy sins are forgiven. 49 And they that sat at table with him, began to say within themselves, Who is this that forgiveth sins also? 50 And he said to the woman, Thy faith hath saved thee; go in peace.

8

1 And it came to pass afterward, that he went throughout every city and village, preaching and showing the glad tidings of the kingdom of God: and the twelve were with him, 2 And certain women, who had been healed of evil spirits and infirmities, Mary called Magdalene, out of whom went seven demons. 3 And Joanna the wife of Chuza Herod's steward, and Susanna, and many others, who ministered to him of their substance. 4 And when many people were collected, and had come to him out of every city, he spoke by a parable: 5 A sower went out to sow his seed: and as he sowed, some fell by the way side; and it was trodden down, and the fowls of the air devoured it. 6 And some fell upon a rock; and as soon as it was sprung up, it withered, because it lacked moisture. 7 And some fell among thorns; and the thorns sprang up with it, and choked it. 8 And other fell on good ground, and sprang up, and bore fruit a hundred-fold. And when he had said these things, he cried, He that hath ears to hear, let him hear. 9 And his disciples asked him, saying, What doth this parable mean? 10 And he said, To you it is given to know the mysteries of the kingdom of God: but to others in parables; that seeing they may not see, and hearing they may not understand. 11 Now the parable is this: The seed is the word of God. 12 Those by the way side, are they that hear; then cometh the devil, and taketh away the word out of their hearts, lest they should believe and be saved. 13 They on the rock are they , who, when they hear, receive the word with joy; and these have no root, who for a while believe, and in time of temptation fall away. 14 And that which fell among thorns are they, who, when they have heard, go forth, and are choked with cares and riches and pleasures of this life, and bring no fruit to perfection. 15 But that on the good ground are they, who in an honest and good heart, having heard the word, keep it , and bring forth fruit with patience. 16 No man, when he hath lighted a candle, covereth it with a vessel, or putteth it under a bed; but setteth it on a candlestick, that they who enter in may see the light. 17 For nothing is secret, that shall not be made manifest; neither any thing hid, that shall not be known, and come abroad. 18 Take heed therefore how ye hear: for whoever hath, to him shall be given; and whoever hath not, from him shall be taken even that which he seemeth to have. 19 Then came to him his mother and his brethren, and could not come near to him for the crowd. 20 And it was told to him by certain , who said, Thy mother and thy brethren stand without, desiring to see thee. 21 And he answered and said to them, My mother and my brethren are these who hear the word of God, and do it. 22 Now it came to pass on a certain day, that he went into a boat with his disciples: and he said to them, Let us go over to the other side of the lake. And they lanched forth. 23 But as they sailed, he fell asleep: and there came down a storm of wind on the lake; and they were filled with water , and were in jeopardy. 24 And they came to him, and awoke him, saying, Master, master, we perish. Then he arose, and rebuked the wind, and the raging of the water: and they ceased, and there was a calm. 25 And he said to them, Where is your faith? And they being afraid, wondered, saying one to another, What manner of man is this! for he commandeth even the winds and water, and they obey him. 26 And they arrived at the country of the Gadarenes, which is over against Galilee. 27 And when he went forth to land, there met him out of the city a certain man, who had demons a long time, and wore no clothes, neither abode in any house, but in the tombs. 28 When he saw Jesus, he cried out, and fell down before him, and with a loud voice said, What have I to do with thee, Jesus, thou Son of God most high? I beseech thee torment me not. 29 (For he had commanded the unclean spirit to come out of the man. For often it had caught him, and he was kept bound with chains, and in fetters: and he broke the bands, and was driven by the demon into the wilderness.) 30 And Jesus asked him, saying, What is thy name? And he said, Legion: because many demons had entered into him. 31 And they besought him, that he would not command them to go out into the deep. 32 And there was there a herd of many swine feeding on the mountain: and they besought him that he would suffer them to enter into them. And he suffered them. 33 Then the demons went out of the man, and entered into the swine: and the herd ran violently down a steep place into the lake, and were choked. 34 When they that fed them saw what was done, they fled, and went and told it in the city and in the country. 35 Then they went out to see what was done; and came to Jesus, and found the man out of whom the demons had departed, sitting at the feet of Jesus, clothed, and in his right mind: and they were afraid. 36 They also who saw it , told them by what means he that was possessed by the demons was healed. 37 Then the whole multitude of the surrounding country of the Gadarenes, besought him to depart from them: for they were taken with great fear. And he went into the boat, and returned. 38 Now the man out of whom the demons had departed, besought him that he might be with him. But Jesus sent him away, saying, 39 Return to thy own house, and show how great things God hath done to thee. And he went away and published throughout the whole city, how great things Jesus had done to him. 40 And it came to pass, that, when Jesus had returned, the people gladly received him: for they were all waiting for him. 41 And behold, there came a man named Jairus, and he was a ruler of the synagogue: and he fell down at the feet of Jesus, and besought him that he would come into his house: 42 For he had one daughter only, about twelve years of age, and she lay dying. (But as he was going, the people thronged him. 43 And a woman having an issue of blood twelve years, who had spent all her living upon physicians, neither could be healed by any, 44 Came behind him , and touched the border of his garment: and immediately her issue of blood stanched. 45 And Jesus said, Who touched me? When all denied, Peter, and they that were with him, said, Master, the multitude throng thee, and press thee , and sayest thou, Who touched me? 46 And Jesus said, Somebody hath touched me: for I perceive that virtue hath gone out of me. 47 And when the woman saw that she was not hid, she came trembling, and falling down before him, she declared to him before all the people for what cause she had touched him, and how she was healed immediately. 48 And he said to her, Daughter, be of good comfort: thy faith hath made thee whole; go in peace. 49 While he was yet speaking, there cometh one from the house of the ruler of the synagogue, saying to him, Thy daughter is dead: trouble not the Master. 50 But when Jesus heard it , he answered him, saying, Fear not: believe only, and she shall be healed. 51 And when he came into the house, he suffered no man to go in, save Peter, and James, and John, and the father and the mother of the maiden. 52 And all wept and bewailed her: but he said, Weep not: she is not dead, but sleepeth. 53 And they derided him, knowing that she was dead. 54 And he put them all out, and took her by the hand, and called, saying, Maid, arise. 55 And her spirit came again, and she arose immediately: and he commanded to give her food. 56 And her parents were astonished: but he charged them that they should tell no man what was done.

9

1 Then he called his twelve disciples together, and gave them power and authority over all demons, and to cure diseases. 2 And he sent them to preach the kingdom of God, and to heal the sick. 3 And he said to them, Take nothing for your journey, neither staffs, nor bag, neither bread, neither money; neither have two coats apiece. 4 And into whatever house ye enter, there abide, and thence depart. 5 And whoever will not receive you, when ye go out of that city, shake off the very dust from your feet for a testimony against them. 6 And they departed, and went through the towns, preaching the gospel, and healing every where. 7 Now Herod the tetrarch heard of all that was done by him: and he was perplexed, because that it was said by some, that John had risen from the dead; 8 And by some, that Elijah had appeared; and by others, that one of the ancient prophets had risen again. 9 And Herod said, John have I beheaded; but who is this of whom I hear such things? And he desired to see him. 10 And the apostles, when they had returned, told him all that they had done. And he took them, and went aside privately into a desert place, belonging to the city called Bethsaida. 11 And the people, when they knew it , followed him: and he received them, and spoke to them of the kingdom of God, and healed them that had need of healing. 12 And when the day began to decline, then came the twelve, and said to him, Send the multitude away, that they may go into the towns and country around, and lodge, and get victuals: for we are here in a desert place. 13 But he said to them, Give ye them to eat. And they said, We have no more than five loaves and two fishes; except we should go and buy provisions for all this people. 14 For they were about five thousand men. And he said to his disciples, Make them sit down by fifties in a company. 15 And they did so, and made them all sit down. 16 Then he took the five loaves, and the two fishes, and looking up to heaven, he blessed them, and broke, and gave to the disciples to set before the multitude. 17 And they ate, and were all satisfied: and there was taken up of fragments that remained to them, twelve baskets. 18 And it came to pass, as he was in retirement praying, his disciples were with him; and he asked them, saying, Who say the people that I am? 19 They answering, said, John the Baptist; but some say , Elijah; and others say , that one of the ancient prophets is risen again. 20 He said to them, But who say ye that I am? Peter answering, said, Christ of God. 21 And he strictly charged them, and commanded them to tell no man that thing, 22 Saying, The Son of man must suffer many things, and be rejected by the elders, and chief priests, and scribes, and be put to death, and be raised the third day. 23 And he said to them all, If any man will come after me, let him deny himself, and take up his cross daily, and follow me. 24 For whoever will save his life, shall lose it: but whoever will lose his life for my sake, the same shall save it. 25 For what is a man profited, if he shall gain the whole world, and lose himself, or be cast away? 26 For whoever shall be ashamed of me, and of my words, of him will the Son of man be ashamed, when he shall come in his own glory, and in that of his Father, and of the holy angels. 27 But I tell you in truth, there are some standing here who shall not taste death till they see the kingdom of God. 28 And it came to pass, about eight days after these sayings, he took Peter, and John, and James, and went up upon a mountain to pray. 29 And as he prayed, the fashion of his countenance was altered, and his raiment was white and glistening. 30 And behold, there talked with him two men, who were Moses and Elijah. 31 Who appeared in glory, and spoke of his decease which he should accomplish at Jerusalem. 32 But Peter and they that were with him were heavy with sleep: and when they were awake, they saw his glory, and the two men that stood with him. 33 And it came to pass, as they departed from him, Peter said to Jesus, Master, it is good for us to be here: and let us make three tabernacles; one for thee, and one for Moses, and one for Elijah: not knowing what he said. 34 While he was thus speaking, there came a cloud and overshadowed them: and they feared as they entered into the cloud. 35 And there came a voice out of the cloud, saying, This is my beloved Son: hear him. 36 And when the voice was past, Jesus was found alone. And they kept it close, and told no man in those days any of those things which they had seen. 37 And it came to pass, that on the next day, when they had come down from the hill, many people met him. 38 And behold, a man of the company cried out, saying, Master, I beseech thee look upon my son: for he is my only child. 39 And lo, a spirit taketh him, and he suddenly crieth out; and it teareth him that he foameth, and bruising him, hardly departeth from him. 40 And I besought thy disciples to cast him out, and they could not. 41 And Jesus answering, said, O faithless and perverse generation, how long shall I be with you, and suffer you? Bring thy son hither. 42 And as he was yet coming, the demon threw him down, and tore him . And Jesus rebuked the unclean spirit, and healed the child, and delivered him again to his father. 43 And they were all amazed at the mighty power of God. But while they were all wondering at all things which Jesus did, he said to his disciples, 44 Let these sayings sink down into your ears: for the Son of man will be delivered into the hands of men. 45 But they understood not this saying, and it was hid from them, that they perceived it not: and they feared to ask him concerning that saying. 46 Then there arose a reasoning among them, which of them should be greatest. 47 And Jesus perceiving the thought of their heart, took a child, and set him by him, 48 And said to them, Whoever shall receive this child in my name, receiveth me; and whoever shall receive me, receiveth him that sent me: for he that is least among you all, the same shall be great. 49 And John answered and said, Master, we saw one casting out demons in thy name; and we forbad him, because he followeth not with us. 50 And Jesus said to him, Forbid him not: for he that is not against us, is for us. 51 And it came to pass, when the time was come that he should be received up, he steadfastly set his face to go to Jerusalem, 52 And sent messengers before his face: and they went and entered into a village of the Samaritans, to make ready for him. 53 And they did not receive him, because his face was as though he would go to Jerusalem. 54 And when his disciples James and John saw this , they said, Lord, wilt thou that we command fire to come down from heaven, and consume them, even as Elijah did? 55 But he turned, and rebuked them, and said, Ye know not what manner of spirit ye are of. 56 For the Son of man is not come to destroy men's lives, but to save them . And they went to another village. 57 And it came to pass, that as they were going in the way, a certain man said to him, Lord, I will follow thee whithersoever thou goest. 58 And Jesus said to him, Foxes have holes, and birds of the air have nests; but the Son of man hath not where to lay his head. 59 And he said to another, Follow me. But he said, Lord, suffer me first to go and bury my father. 60 Jesus said to him, Let the dead bury their dead: but go thou and preach the kingdom of God. 61 And another also said, Lord, I will follow thee; but let me first go and bid them farewell who are at my house. 62 And Jesus said to him, No man having put his hand to the plow, and looking back, is fit for the kingdom of God.

10

1 After these things, the Lord appointed other seventy also, and sent them two and two before his face into every city, and place, whither he himself would come. 2 Therefore said he to them, The harvest truly is great, but the laborers are few: pray ye therefore the Lord of the harvest, that he would send forth laborers into his harvest. 3 Go: behold, I send you forth as lambs among wolves. 4 Carry neither purse, nor sack, nor shoes: and salute no man by the way. 5 And into whatever house ye enter, first say, Peace be to this house. 6 And if the son of peace be there, your peace shall rest upon it: if not, it shall turn to you again. 7 And in the same house remain, eating and drinking such things as they give: for the laborer is worthy of his hire. Go not from house to house. 8 And into whatever city ye enter, and they receive you, eat such things as are set before you. 9 And heal the sick that are therein, and say to them, The kingdom of God is come nigh to you. 10 But into whatever city ye enter, and they receive you not, go out into the streets of the same, and say, 11 Even the very dust of your city which cleaveth on us, we do wipe off against you: notwithstanding, be ye sure of this, that the kingdom of God is come nigh to you. 12 But I say to you, that it shall be more tolerable in that day for Sodom than for that city. 13 Woe to thee, Chorazin! woe to thee Bethsaida! for if the mighty works had been done in Tyre and Sidon, which have been done in you, they had a great while ago repented sitting in sackcloth and ashes. 14 But it shall be more tolerable for Tyre and Sidon at the judgment, than for you. 15 And thou, Capernaum, which art exalted to heaven, shall be thrust down to hell. 16 He that heareth you, heareth me; and he that despiseth you, despiseth me; and he that despiseth me, despiseth him that sent me. 17 And the seventy returned with joy, saying, Lord, even the demons are subject to us through thy name. 18 And he said to them, I beheld Satan as lightning fall from heaven. 19 Behold, I give to you power to tread on serpents and scorpions, and over all the power of the enemy: and nothing shall by any means hurt you. 20 Notwithstanding in this rejoice not, that the spirits are subject to you; but rather rejoice, because your names are written in heaven. 21 In that hour Jesus rejoiced in spirit, and said, I thank thee, O Father, Lord of heaven and earth, that thou hast hid these things from the wise and prudent, and hast revealed them to babes: even so, Father; for so it seemed good in thy sight. 22 All things are delivered to me by my Father: and no man knoweth who the Son is, but the Father; and who the Father is, but the Son, and he to whom the Son will reveal him . 23 And he turned himself to his disciples, and said privately, Blessed are the eyes which see the things that ye see. 24 For I tell you, that many prophets and kings have desired to see the things which ye see, and have not seen them ; and to hear the things which ye hear, and have not heard them . 25 And behold, a certain lawyer stood up, and tempted him, saying, Master, what shall I do to inherit eternal life? 26 He said to him, What is written in the law? how readest thou? 27 And he answering said, Thou shalt love the Lord thy God with all thy heart, and with all thy soul, and with all thy strength, and with all thy mind; and thy neighbor as thyself. 28 And he said to him, Thou hast answered right: this do, and thou shalt live. 29 But he, willing to justify himself, said to Jesus, And who is my neighbor? 30 And Jesus answering said, A certain man went down from Jerusalem to Jericho, and fell among robbers, who stripped him of his raiment, and wounded him , and departed, leaving him half dead. 31 And by chance there came down a certain priest that way; and when he saw him, he passed by on the other side. 32 And likewise a Levite, when he was at the place, came and looked on him , and passed by on the other side. 33 But a certain Samaritan, as he journeyed, came were he was: and when he saw him, he had compassion on him , 34 And went to him , and bound up his wounds, pouring in oil and wine, and set him on his own beast, and brought him to an inn, and took care of him. 35 And on the morrow, when he departed, he took out two pence, and gave them to the host, and said to him, Take care of him: and whatever thou spendest more, when I come again, I will repay thee. 36 Which now of these three, thinkest thou, was neighbor to him that fell among the robbers? 37 And he said, He that showed mercy on him. Then said Jesus to him, Go, and do thou likewise. 38 Now it came to pass, as they were going, he entered into a certain village: and a certain woman, named Martha, received him into her house. 39 And she had a sister called Mary, who also sat at Jesus' feet, and heard his word. 40 But Martha was cumbered about much serving, and came to him, and said, Lord, dost thou not care that my sister hath left me to serve alone? bid her therefore that she help me. 41 And Jesus answered, and said to her, Martha, Martha, thou art anxious, and troubled about many things: 42 But one thing is needful; and Mary hath chosen that good part, which shall not be taken away from her.

11

1 And it came to pass, that as he was praying in a certain place, when he ceased, one of his disciples said to him, Lord, teach us to pray, as John also taught his disciples. 2 And he said to them, When ye pray, say, Our Father who art in heaven, Hallowed be thy name. Thy kingdom come. Thy will be done, as in heaven, so on earth. 3 Give us day by day our daily bread. 4 And forgive us our sins; for we also forgive every one that is indebted to us. And lead us not into temptation; but deliver us from evil. 5 And he said to them, Which of you shall have a friend, and shall go to him at midnight, and say to him, Friend, lend me three loaves: 6 For a friend of mine in his journey is come to me, and I have nothing to set before him? 7 And he from within shall answer and say, Trouble me not: the door is now shut, and my children are with me in bed; I cannot rise and give thee. 8 I say to you, Though he will not rise and give him, because he is his friend, yet because of his importunity he will rise and give him as many as he needeth. 9 And I say to you, Ask, and it shall be given you; seek, and ye shall find; knock, and the door shall be opened to you. 10 For every one that asketh, receiveth; and he that seeketh, findeth; and to him that knocketh, the door shall be opened. 11 If a son shall ask bread of any of you that is a father, will he give him a stone? or if he shall ask a fish, will he for a fish give him a serpent? 12 Or if he shall ask an egg, will he offer him a scorpion? 13 If ye then, being evil, know how to give good gifts to your children: how much more will your heavenly Father give the Holy Spirit to them that ask him? 14 And he was casting out a demon, and it was dumb. And it came to pass when the demon was gone out, the dumb spoke; and the people wondered. 15 But some of them said, He casteth out demons through Beelzebub, the chief of the demons. 16 And others tempting him , sought from him a sign from heaven. 17 But he, knowing their thoughts, said to them, Every kingdom divided against itself is brought to desolation; and a house divided against a house falleth. 18 If Satan also is divided against himself, how shall his kingdom stand? because ye say that I cast out demons through Beelzebub. 19 And if I by Beelzebub cast out demons, by whom do your sons cast them out? therefore shall they be your judges. 20 But if I with the finger of God cast out demons, no doubt the kingdom of God is come upon you. 21 When a strong man armed keepeth his palace, his goods are in peace: 22 But when a stronger than he shall come upon him, and overcome him, he taketh from him all his armor in which he trusted, and divideth his spoils. 23 He that is not with me is against me: and he that gathereth not with me scattereth. 24 When the unclean spirit is gone out of a man, he walketh through dry places, seeking rest: and finding none, he saith, I will return to my house whence I came out. 25 And when he cometh, he findeth it swept and garnished. 26 Then he goeth and taketh to him seven other spirits more wicked than himself; and they enter in, and dwell there: and the last state of that man is worse than the first. 27 And it came to pass, as he was speaking these things, a certain woman of the company lifted up her voice, and said to him, Blessed is the womb that bore thee, and the paps which nourished thee. 28 But he said, Yes, rather blessed are they that hear the word of God, and keep it. 29 And when the people were assembled in crowds, he began to say, This is an evil generation: they seek a sign; and there shall no sign be given to it, but the sign of Jonah the prophet. 30 For as Jonah was a sign to the Ninevites, so also shall the Son of man be to this generation. 31 The queen of the south shall rise up in the judgment with the men of this generation, and condemn them: for she came from the utmost parts of the earth, to hear the wisdom of Solomon; and behold, a greater than Solomon is here. 32 The men of Nineveh shall rise up in the judgment with this generation, and shall condemn it: for they repented at the preaching of Jonah; and behold, a greater than Jonah is here. 33 No man when he hath lighted a candle, putteth it in a secret place, neither under a close vessel, but on a candlestick, that they who come in may see the light. 34 The light of the body is the eye: therefore when thy eye is single, thy whole body also is full of light; but when thy eye is evil, thy body also is full of darkness. 35 Take heed therefore, that the light which is in thee be not darkness. 36 If thy whole body therefore be full of light, having no part dark, the whole shall be full of light; as when the bright shining of a candle doth give thee light. 37 And as he was speaking, a certain Pharisee besought him to dine with him: and he went in, and sat down to eat. 38 And when the Pharisee saw it , he marveled that he had not first washed before dinner. 39 And the Lord said to him, Now do ye Pharisees make clean the outside of the cup and the platter; but your inward part is full of ravening and wickedness. 40 Ye fools, did not he that made that which is without, make that which is within also? 41 But rather give alms of such things as ye have; and behold, all things are clean to you. 42 But woe to you, Pharisees! for ye tithe mint, and rue, and all manner of herbs, and pass over judgment and the love of God: these ought ye to have done, and not to leave the others undone. 43 Woe to you, Pharisees! for ye love the uppermost seats in the synagogues, and greetings in the markets. 44 Woe to you, scribes and Pharisees, hypocrites! for ye are as graves which appear not, and the men that walk over them are not aware of them . 45 Then answered one of the lawyers, and said to him, Master, thus saying, thou reproachest us also. 46 And he said, Woe to you also, ye lawyers, for ye load men with burdens grievous to be borne, and ye yourselves touch not the burdens with one of your fingers. 47 Woe to you! for ye build the sepulchers of the prophets, and your fathers killed them. 48 Truly ye bear testimony, that ye allow the deeds of your fathers: for they indeed killed them, and ye build their sepulchers. 49 Therefore also said the wisdom of God, I will send them prophets and apostles, and some of them they will slay and persecute: 50 That the blood of all the prophets, which hath been shed from the foundation of the world, may be required of this generation; 51 From the blood of Abel to the blood of Zacharias, who perished between the altar and the temple: verily I say to you, It shall be required of this generation. 52 Woe to you, lawyers! for ye have taken away the key of knowledge: ye have not entered in yourselves, and them that were entering in ye hindered. 53 And as he said these things to them, the scribes and the Pharisees began to urge him vehemently, and to solicit him to speak of many things; 54 Laying wait for him, and seeking to catch something from his mouth, that they might accuse him.

12

1 In the mean time, when there was gathered an innumerable multitude of people, so that they trod one upon another, he began to say to his disciples first of all, Beware ye of the leaven of the Pharisees, which is hypocrisy. 2 For there is nothing covered, that shall not be revealed; neither hid, that shall not be known. 3 Therefore, whatever ye have spoken in darkness, shall be heard in the light; and that which ye have spoken in the ear in closets, shall be proclaimed upon the house-tops. 4 And I say to you, my friends, Be not afraid of them that kill the body, and after that have no more that they can do. 5 But I will forewarn you whom ye shall fear: Fear him, who after he hath killed, hath power to cast into hell; yes, I say to you, Fear him. 6 Are not five sparrows sold for two farthings, and not one of them is forgotten before God? 7 But even the very hairs of your head are all numbered. Fear not therefore: ye are of more value than many sparrows. 8 Also I say to you, Whoever shall confess me before men, him will the Son of man also confess before the angels of God. 9 But he that denieth me before men, shall be denied before the angels of God. 10 And whoever shall speak a word against the Son of man, it shall be forgiven him: but to him that blasphemeth against the Holy Spirit, it shall not be forgiven. 11 And when they bring you to the synagogues, and before magistrates, and powers, be not solicitous how or what thing ye shall answer, or what ye shall say: 12 For the Holy Spirit will teach you in the same hour what ye ought to say. 13 And one of the company said to him, Master, speak to my brother, that he divide the inheritance with me. 14 And he said to him, Man, who made me a judge, or a divider over you? 15 And he said to them, Take heed, and beware of covetousness: for a man's life consisteth not in the abundance of the things which he possesseth. 16 And he spoke a parable to them, saying, The ground of a certain rich man brought forth plentifully: 17 And he thought within himself, saying, What shall I do, because I have no room where to deposit my fruits? 18 And he said, This will I do: I will pull down my barns, and build greater; and there will I deposit all my fruits and my goods. 19 And I will say to my soul, Soul, thou hast abundance of goods laid up for many years; take thy ease, eat, drink, and be merry. 20 But God said to him, Thou fool, this night thy soul shall be required of thee: then whose shall those things be which thou hast provided? 21 So is he that layeth up treasure for himself, and is not rich towards God. 22 And he said to his disciples, Therefore I say to you, Be not anxious for your life, what ye shall eat; neither for the body, what ye shall put on. 23 The life is more than food, and the body is more than raiment. 24 Consider the ravens: for they neither sow nor reap: which neither have store-house, nor barn; and God feedeth them: How much more are ye better than the fowls? 25 And which of you by solicitude can add to his stature one cubit? 26 If ye then are not able to do that thing which is least, why are ye anxious for the rest? 27 Consider the lilies how they grow: They toil not, they spin not; and yet I say to you, that Solomon in all his glory was not arrayed like one of these. 28 If then God so clothe the grass, which is to-day in the field, and to-morrow is cast into the oven; how much more will he clothe you, O ye of little faith? 29 And seek ye not what ye shall eat, or what ye shall drink, neither be ye of doubtful mind. 30 For all these things do the nations of the world seek after: and your Father knoweth that ye have need of these things. 31 But rather seek ye the kingdom of God, and all these things shall be added to you. 32 Fear not, little flock; for it is your Father's good pleasure to give you the kingdom. 33 Sell what ye have, and give alms: provide yourselves bags which become not old, a treasure in the heavens that faileth not, where no thief approacheth, neither moth corrupteth. 34 For where your treasure is, there will your heart be also. 35 Let your loins be girt, and your lights burning; 36 And ye yourselves like men that wait for their lord, when he shall return from the wedding; that, when he cometh and knocketh, they may open to him immediately. 37 Blessed are those servants, whom the lord when he cometh shall find watching: verily I say to you, that he will gird himself, and make them to sit down to eat, and will come forth and serve them. 38 And if he shall come in the second watch, or come in the third watch, and find them so, blessed are those servants. 39 And this know, that if the master of the house knew at what hour the thief would come, he would watch, and not suffer his house to be broken through. 40 Be ye therefore ready also: for the Son of man cometh at an hour when ye think not. 41 Then Peter said to him, Lord, speakest thou this parable to us, or even to all? 42 And the Lord said, Who then is that faithful and wise steward, whom his lord shall make ruler over his household, to give them their portion of provisions in due season? 43 Blessed is that servant, whom his lord when he cometh shall find so doing. 44 In truth I say to you, that he will make him ruler over all that he hath. 45 But if that servant shall say in his heart, My lord delayeth his coming; and shall begin to beat the men-servants, and maidens, and to eat and drink, and to be drunken? 46 The lord of that servant will come in a day when he looketh not for him , and at an hour when he is not aware, and will cut him asunder, and will appoint him his portion with the unbelievers. 47 And that servant who knew his lord's will, and prepared not himself , neither did according to his will, shall be beaten with many stripes . 48 But he that knew not, and committed things worthy of stripes, shall be beaten with few stripes . For to whomsoever much is given, of him shall much be required: and to whom men have committed much, from him they will ask the more. 49 I am come to send fire on the earth, and what will I, if it is already kindled? 50 But I have a baptism to be baptized with; and how am I straitened till it shall be accomplished! 51 Suppose ye that I am come to give peace on earth? I tell you, No; but rather division: 52 For from henceforth there will be five in one house divided, three against two, and two against three. 53 The father will be divided against the son, and the son against the father; the mother against the daughter, and the daughter against the mother; the mother-in-law against her daughter-in-law, and the daughter-in-law against her mother-in-law. 54 And he said also to the people, When ye see a cloud rising in the west, immediately ye say, There cometh a shower; and so it is. 55 And when ye perceive the south wind blowing, ye say, There will be heat; and it cometh to pass. 56 Ye hypocrites, ye can discern the face of the sky, and of the earth; but how is it, that ye do not discern this time? 57 And why even of yourselves judge ye not what is right? 58 When thou goest with thy adversary to the magistrate, as thou art in the way, give diligence that thou mayest be delivered from him; lest he draw thee before the judge, and the judge deliver thee to the officer, and the officer cast thee into prison. 59 I tell thee, thou shalt not depart thence, till thou hast paid the very last mite.

13

1 There were present at that season some that told him of the Galileans, whose blood Pilate had mingled with their sacrifices. 2 And Jesus answering, said to them, Suppose ye that these Galileans were sinners above all the Galileans, because they suffered such things? 3 I tell you, No; but except ye repent, ye shall all likewise perish. 4 Or those eighteen, upon whom the tower in Siloam fell, and killed them, think ye that they were sinners above all men that dwelt in Jerusalem? 5 I tell you, No; but, except ye repent, ye shall all likewise perish. 6 He spoke also this parable: A certain man had a fig-tree planted in his vineyard; and he came and sought fruit on it, and found none. 7 Then said he to the dresser of his vineyard, Behold, these three years I come seeking fruit on this fig-tree, and find none: cut it down; why cumbereth it the ground? 8 And he answering, said to him, Lord, let it alone this year also, till I shall dig about it, and dung it : 9 And if it shall bear fruit, well : and if not, then after that thou shalt cut it down. 10 And he was teaching in one of the synagogues on the sabbath. 11 And behold, there was a woman who had a spirit of infirmity eighteen years, and was bowed together, and could in no wise raise herself . 12 And when Jesus saw her, he called her to him , and said to her, Woman, thou art loosed from thy infirmity. 13 And he laid his hands on her: and immediately she was made straight, and glorified God. 14 And the ruler of the synagogue answered with indignation, because Jesus had healed on the sabbath, and said to the people, There are six days in which men ought to work: in them therefore come and be healed, and not on the sabbath. 15 The Lord then answered him, and said, Thou hypocrite, doth not each one of you on the sabbath loose his ox or his ass from the stall, and lead him away to watering? 16 And ought not this woman, being a daughter of Abraham, whom Satan hath bound, lo, these eighteen years, to be loosed from this bond on the Sabbath? 17 And when he had said these things, all his adversaries were ashamed: and all the people rejoiced for all the glorious things that were done by him. 18 Then said he, To what is the kingdom of God like? and to what shall I resemble it? 19 It is like a grain of mustard-seed, which a man took, and cast into his garden, and it grew, and became a great tree; and the fowls of the air lodged in the branches of it. 20 And again he said, To what shall I liken the kingdom of God? 21 It is like leaven, which a woman took and hid in three measures of meal, till the whole was leavened. 22 And he went through the cities and villages, teaching, and journeying towards Jerusalem. 23 Then said one to him, Lord, are there few that are saved? And he said to them, 24 Strive to enter in at the strait gate: for many, I say to you, will seek to enter in, and shall not be able. 25 When once the master of the house hath risen, and hath shut the door, and ye begin to stand without, and to knock at the door, saying, Lord, Lord, open to us; and he will answer and say to you, I know you not whence ye are: 26 Then ye will begin to say, We have eaten and drank in thy presence, and thou hast taught in our streets. 27 But he will say, I tell you, I know you not whence ye are: depart from me, all ye workers of iniquity. 28 There shall be weeping and gnashing of teeth when ye shall see Abraham, and Isaac, and Jacob, and all the prophets in the kingdom of God, and you yourselves excluded. 29 And they will come from the east, and from the west, and from the north, and from the south, and will sit down in the kingdom of God. 30 And behold, there are last, who shall be first; and there are first who shall be last. 31 The same day there came certain of the Pharisees, saying to him, Go out, and depart hence; for Herod will kill thee. 32 And he said to them, Go ye and tell that fox, Behold, I cast out demons, and I do cures to-day and to-morrow, and the third day I shall be perfected. 33 Nevertheless, I must walk to-day and to-morrow, and the day following: for it cannot be that a prophet should perish out of Jerusalem. 34 O Jerusalem, Jerusalem, that killest the prophets, and stonest them that are sent to thee; how often would I have gathered thy children, as a hen gathereth her brood under her wings, and ye would not! 35 Behold, your house is left to you desolate. And verily I say to you, ye shall not see me, until the time shall come when ye shall say, Blessed is he that cometh in the name of the Lord.

14

1 And it came to pass, as he went into the house of one of the chief Pharisees to eat bread on the sabbath, that they watched him. 2 And behold, there was a certain man before him who had the dropsy. 3 And Jesus answering, spoke to the lawyers and Pharisees, saying, Is it lawful to heal on the sabbath? 4 And they held their peace. And he took him and healed him, and let him go; 5 And answered them, saying, Which of you shall have an ass or an ox fallen into a pit, and will not forthwith pull him out on the sabbath? 6 And they could not answer him again to these things. 7 And he put forth a parable to those who were invited, when he marked how they chose out the chief rooms; saying to them, 8 When thou art invited by any man to a wedding, sit not down in the highest room, lest a more honorable man than thou be invited by him; 9 And he that invited thee and him, shall come and say to thee, Give this man place; and thou begin with shame to take the lowest room. 10 But when thou art invited, go and sit down in the lowest room; that when he that invited thee cometh, he may say to thee, Friend, go up higher: then shalt thou have honor in the presence of them that sit at table with thee. 11 For whoever exalteth himself shall be abased, and he that humbleth himself shall be exalted. 12 Then said he also to him that invited him, When thou makest a dinner or a supper, call not thy friends, nor thy brethren, neither thy kinsmen, nor thy rich neighbors; lest they also invite thee again, and a recompense be made thee. 13 But when thou makest a feast, call the poor, the maimed, the lame, the blind: 14 And thou shalt be blessed: for they cannot recompense thee: for thou shalt be recompensed at the resurrection of the just. 15 And when one of them that sat at table with him heard these things, he said to him, Blessed is he that shall eat bread in the kingdom of God. 16 Then said he to him, A certain man made a great supper, and invited many: 17 And sent his servant at supper-time, to say to them that were invited, Come, for all things are now ready. 18 And they all with one consent began to make excuse. The first said to him, I have bought a piece of ground, and I must needs go and see it: I pray thee have me excused. 19 And another said, I have bought five yoke of oxen, and I go to prove them: I pray thee have me excused. 20 And another said, I have married a wife: and therefore I cannot come. 21 So that servant came, and showed his lord these things. Then the master of the house being angry, said to his servant, Go out quickly into the streets and lanes of the city, and bring in hither the poor, and the maimed, and the halt, and the blind. 22 And the servant said, Lord, it is done as thou hast commanded, and yet there is room. 23 And the lord said to the servant, Go out into the highways and hedges, and compel them to come in, that my house may be filled. 24 For I say to you, that none of those men who were invited, shall taste my supper. 25 And there went great multitudes with him: and he turned, and said to them, 26 If any man cometh to me, and hateth not his father, and mother, and wife, and children, and brethren, and sisters, yes, and his own life also, he cannot be my disciple. 27 And whoever doth not bear his cross, and come after me, cannot be my disciple. 28 For which of you intending to build a tower, sitteth not down first, and counteth the cost, whether he hath sufficient to finish it ? 29 Lest perhaps after he hath laid the foundation, and is not able to finish it , all that behold it begin to mock him, 30 Saying, This man began to build, and was not able to finish. 31 Or what king going to make war against another king, sitteth not down first, and consulteth whether he is able with ten thousand to meet him that cometh against him with twenty thousand? 32 Or else, while the other is yet a great way off, he sendeth an embassy, and desireth conditions of peace. 33 So likewise, whoever he is of you that forsaketh not all that he hath, he cannot be my disciple. 34 Salt is good: but if the salt hath lost its savor, with what shall it be seasoned? 35 It is neither fit for the land, nor yet for the dunghill, but men cast it out. He that hath ears to hear, let him hear.

15

1 Then drew near to him all the publicans and sinners to hear him. 2 And the Pharisees and scribes murmured, saying, This man receiveth sinners, and eateth with them. 3 And he spoke this parable to them, saying, 4 What man of you having a hundred sheep, if he loseth one of them, doth not leave the ninety and nine in the wilderness, and go after that which is lost, until he findeth it? 5 And when he hath found it , he layeth it on his shoulders, rejoicing. 6 And when he cometh home, he calleth together his friends and neighbors, saying to them, Rejoice with me; for I have found my sheep which was lost. 7 I say to you, that likewise joy shall be in heaven over one sinner that repenteth, more than over ninety and nine just persons, who need no repentance. 8 Either what woman having ten pieces of silver, if she loseth one piece, doth not light a candle, and sweep the house, and seek diligently till she findeth it ? 9 And when she hath found it , she calleth her friends and her neighbors together, saying, Rejoice with me; for I have found the piece which I had lost. 10 Likewise, I say to you, There is joy in the presence of the angels of God over one sinner that repenteth. 11 And he said, A certain man had two sons: 12 And the younger of them said to his father, Father, give me the portion of goods that falleth to me . And he divided to them his living. 13 And not many days after, the younger son gathered all together, and took his journey into a far country, and there wasted his substance with riotous living. 14 And when he had spent all, there arose a severe famine in that land; and he began to be in want. 15 And he went and joined himself to a citizen of that country; and he sent him into his fields to feed swine. 16 And he would fain have filled his belly with the husks that the swine did eat; and no man gave to him. 17 And when he came to himself, he said, How many hired servants of my father have bread enough and to spare, and I am perishing with hunger! 18 I will arise and go to my father, and will say to him, Father, I have sinned against heaven, and before thee, 19 And am no more worthy to be called thy son: make me as one of thy hired servants. 20 And he arose, and came to his father. But when he was yet a great way off, his father saw him, and had compassion, and ran, and fell on his neck, and kissed him. 21 And the son said to him, Father, I have sinned against heaven, and in thy sight, and am no more worthy to be called thy son. 22 But the father said to his servants, Bring forth the best robe, and put it on him, and put a ring on his hand, and shoes on his feet: 23 And bring hither the fatted calf, and kill it ; and let us eat, and be merry: 24 For this my son was dead, and is alive again; he was lost, and is found. And they began to be merry. 25 Now his elder son was in the field: and as he came and drew nigh to the house, he heard music and dancing. 26 And he called one of the servants, and asked what these things meant. 27 And he said to him, Thy brother is come; and thy father hath killed the fatted calf, because he hath received him in health. 28 And he was angry, and would not go in; therefore his father came out, and entreated him. 29 And he answering, said to his father, Lo, these many years do I serve thee, neither have I at any time transgressed thy commandment; and yet thou never gavest me a kid, that I might make merry with my friends: 30 But as soon as this thy son had come, who hath devoured thy living with harlots, thou hast killed for him the fatted calf. 31 And he said to him, Son, thou art ever with me: and all that I have is thine. 32 It was meet that we should make merry, and be glad: for this thy brother was dead, and is alive again; and was lost, and is found.

16

1 And he said also to his disciples, There was a certain rich man who had a steward; and the same was accused to him that he had wasted his goods. 2 And he called him, and said to him, How is it that I hear this of thee? give an account of thy stewardship: for thou mayest be no longer steward. 3 Then the steward said within himself, What shall I do? for my lord taketh from me the stewardship: I cannot dig; I am ashamed to beg. 4 I am resolved what to do, that when I am removed from the stewardship, they may receive me into their houses. 5 So he called every one of his lord's debtors, and said to the first, How much owest thou to my lord? 6 And he said, A hundred measures of oil. And he said to him, Take thy bill, and sit down quickly, and write fifty. 7 Then said he to another, And how much owest thou? And he said, A hundred measures of wheat. And he said to him, Take thy bill, and write eighty. 8 And the lord commended the unjust steward, because he had done wisely: for the children of this world are in their generation wiser than the children of light. 9 And I say to you, Make to yourselves friends of the mammon of unrighteousness; that when ye fail, they may receive you into everlasting habitations. 10 He that is faithful in that which is least, is faithful also in much; and he that is unjust in the least, is unjust also in much. 11 If therefore ye have not been faithful in the unrighteous mammon, who will commit to your trust the true riches ? 12 And if ye have not been faithful in that which is another man's, who will give you that which is your own? 13 No servant can serve two masters: for either he will hate the one, and love the other; or else he will hold to the one, and despise the other. Ye cannot serve God and mammon. 14 And the Pharisees also, who were covetous, heard all these things, and they derided him. 15 And he said to them, Ye are they who justify yourselves before men; but God knoweth your hearts: for that which is highly esteemed among men, is abomination in the sight of God. 16 The law and the prophets were until John: since that time the kingdom of God is preached, and every man presseth into it. 17 And it is easier for heaven and earth to pass away, than one tittle of the law to fail. 18 Whoever putteth away his wife, and marrieth another, committeth adultery; and whoever marrieth her that is put away from her husband, committeth adultery. 19 There was a certain rich man, who was clothed in purple and fine linen, and fared sumptuously every day: 20 And there was a certain beggar named Lazarus, who was laid at his gate, full of sores, 21 And desiring to be fed with the crumbs which fell from the rich man's table: moreover, the dogs came and licked his sores. 22 And it came to pass, that the beggar died, and was carried by angels into Abraham's bosom. The rich man also died, and was buried: 23 And in hell he lifted up his eyes, being in torments, and seeth Abraham afar off, and Lazarus in his bosom. 24 And he cried, and said, Father Abraham, have mercy on me, and send Lazarus, that he may dip the tip of his finger in water, and cool my tongue: for I am tormented in this flame. 25 But Abraham said, Son, remember that thou in thy life-time receivedst thy good things, and likewise Lazarus evil things: but now he is comforted, and thou art tormented. 26 And besides all this, between us and you there is a great gulf fixed: so that they who would pass from hence to you, cannot; neither can they pass to us, that would come from thence. 27 Then he said, I pray thee therefore, father, that thou wouldst send him to my father's house: 28 For I have five brethren; that he may testify to them, lest they also come into this place of torment. 29 Abraham saith to him, They have Moses and the prophets; let them hear them. 30 And he said, No, father Abraham: but if one shall go to them from the dead, they will repent. 31 And he said to him, If they hear not Moses and the prophets, neither will they be persuaded, though one shall rise from the dead.

17

1 Then he said to the disciples, It is impossible but that causes of sin will come: but woe to him by whom they come! 2 It were better for him that a millstone were hanged about his neck, and he cast into the sea, than that he should cause one of these little ones to fall into sin. 3 Take heed to yourselves: If thy brother shall trespass against thee, rebuke him; and if he shall repent forgive him. 4 And if he shall trespass against thee seven times in a day, and seven times in a day shall turn again to thee, saying, I repent; thou shalt forgive him. 5 And the apostles said to the Lord, Increase our faith. 6 And the Lord said, If ye had faith as a grain of mustard-seed, ye might say to this sycamine-tree, Be thou plucked up by the root, and be thou planted in the sea; and it would obey you. 7 But which of you having a servant plowing, or feeding cattle, will say to him immediately, when he is come from the field, Go and sit down to eat? 8 And will not rather say to him, Make ready wherewith I may sup, and gird thyself, and serve me, till I have eaten and drank; and afterward thou shalt eat and drink? 9 Doth he thank that servant, because he did the things that were commanded him? I suppose not. 10 So likewise ye, when ye shall have done all the things which are commanded you, say, We are unprofitable servants: we have done that which it was our duty to do. 11 And it came to pass, as he went to Jerusalem, that he passed through the midst of Samaria and Galilee. 12 And as he entered into a certain village, there met him ten men that were lepers, who stood at a distance. 13 And they lifted up their voices, and said, Jesus, Master, have mercy on us. 14 And when he saw them , he said to them, Go, show yourselves to the priests. And it came to pass, that as they were going, they were cleansed. 15 And one of them, when he saw that he was healed, turned back, and with a loud voice glorified God, 16 And fell down on his face at his feet, giving him thanks: and he was a Samaritan. 17 And Jesus answering said, Were there not ten cleansed? but where are the nine? 18 There are not found returning to give glory to God, save this stranger. 19 And he said to him, Arise, depart: thy faith hath made thee whole. 20 And when he was asked by the Pharisees, when the kingdom of God should come, he answered them and said, The kingdom of God cometh not with observation. 21 Neither will they say, Lo here! or lo there! for behold, the kingdom of God is within you. 22 And he said to his disciples, The days will come, when ye will desire to see one of the days of the son of man, and ye shall not see it . 23 And they will say to you, See here; or, see there: go not after them , nor follow them. 24 For as the lightning that lighteneth from the one part under heaven, shineth to the other part under heaven; so shall also the Son of man be in his day. 25 But first he must suffer many things, and be rejected by this generation. 26 And as it was in the days of Noah, so shall it be also in the days of the Son of man. 27 They ate, they drank, they married wives, they were given in marriage, until the day that Noah entered into the ark; and the flood came, and destroyed them all. 28 Likewise also as it was in the days of Lot: they ate, they drank, they bought, they sold, they planted, they built; 29 But the same day that Lot went out of Sodom, it rained fire and brimstone from heaven, and destroyed them all: 30 Even thus shall it be in the day when the Son of man is revealed. 31 In that day, he who shall be upon the house-top, and his furniture in the house, let him not come down to take it away: and he that is in the field, let him likewise not return back. 32 Remember Lot's wife. 33 Whoever shall seek to save his life, shall lose it; and whoever shall lose his life, shall preserve it. 34 I tell you, in that night there will be two men in one bed; the one will be taken, and the other will be left. 35 Two women will be grinding together; the one will be taken, and the other left. 36 Two men will be in the field; the one will be taken, and the other left. 37 And they answered and said to him, Where Lord? And he said to them, Wherever the body is , thither will the eagles be collected.

18

1 And he spoke a parable to them to this end , that men ought always to pray, and not to faint; 2 Saying, There was in a city a judge, who feared not God, neither regarded man. 3 And there was a widow in that city; and she came to him, saying, Avenge me of my adversary. 4 And he would not for a while: but afterward he said within himself, Though I fear not God, nor regard man; 5 Yet because this widow troubleth me, I will avenge her, lest by her continual coming she weary me. 6 And the Lord said, Hear what the unjust judge saith. 7 And will not God avenge his own elect, who cry day and night to him, though he beareth long with them? 8 I tell you that he will avenge them speedily. Nevertheless, when the Son of man cometh, will he find faith on the earth? 9 And he spoke this parable to certain who trusted in themselves that they were righteous, and despised others: 10 Two men went up into the temple to pray; the one a Pharisee, and the other a publican. 11 The Pharisee stood and prayed thus with himself, God, I thank thee, that I am not as other men are , extortioners, unjust, adulterers, or even as this publican. 12 I fast twice in the week, I give tithes of all that I possess. 13 And the publican, standing afar off, would not lift up so much as his eyes to heaven, but smote upon his breast, saying, God be merciful to me a sinner. 14 I tell you, this man went down to his house justified rather than the other: for every one that exalteth himself shall be abased; and he that humbleth himself shall be exalted. 15 And they brought to him also infants, that he would touch them: but when his disciples saw it , they rebuked them. 16 But Jesus called them to him , and said, Suffer little children to come to me, and forbid them not: for of such is the kingdom of God. 17 Verily I say to you, Whoever shall not receive the kingdom of God as a little child, shall in no wise enter into it. 18 And a certain ruler asked him, saying, Good Master, what shall I do to inherit eternal life? 19 And Jesus said to him, Why callest thou me good? none is good, save one, that is God. 20 Thou knowest the commandments, Do not commit adultery, Do not kill, Do not steal, Do not bear false witness, Honor thy father and thy mother. 21 And he said, All these have I kept from my youth. 22 Now when Jesus heard these things, he said to him, Yet lackest thou one thing: sell all that thou hast, and distribute to the poor, and thou shalt have treasure in heaven: and come, follow me. 23 And when he heard this, he was very sorrowful: for he was very rich. 24 And when Jesus saw that he was very sorrowful, he said, How hardly will they that have riches enter into the kingdom of God! 25 For it is easier for a camel to go through a needle's eye, than for a rich man to enter into the kingdom of God. 26 And they that heard it , said, Who then can be saved? 27 Then he said, The things which are impossible with men, are possible with God. 28 Then Peter said, Lo, we have left all, and followed thee. 29 And he said to them, Verily I say to you, there is no man that hath left house, or parents, or brethren, or wife, or children for the sake of the kingdom of God, 30 Who shall not receive manifold more in this present time, and in the world to come life everlasting. 31 Then he took the twelve, and said to them, Behold, we go up to Jerusalem, and all things that are written by the prophets concerning the Son of man shall be accomplished. 32 For he will be delivered to the Gentiles, and will be mocked, and spitefully treated, and spitted on; 33 And they will scourge him , and put him to death: and the third day he will rise again. 34 And they understood none of these things: and this saying was hid from them, neither knew they the things which were spoken. 35 And it came to pass, that as he had come nigh to Jericho, a certain blind man sat by the way side begging; 36 And hearing the multitude passing by, he asked what it meant. 37 And they told him, that Jesus of Nazareth was passing by. 38 And he cried, saying, Jesus, thou son of David, have mercy on me. 39 And they who went before rebuked him, that he should hold his peace: but he cried so much the more, Thou son of David, have mercy on me. 40 And Jesus stood and commanded him to be brought to him: and when he had come near, he asked him, 41 Saying, What wilt thou that I shall do to thee? And he said, Lord, that I may receive my sight. 42 And Jesus said to him, Receive thy sight: thy faith hath saved thee. 43 And immediately he received his sight, and followed him, glorifying God: and all the people, when they saw it , gave praise to God.

19

1 And Jesus entered and passed through Jericho. 2 And behold, there was a man named Zaccheus, who was the chief among the publicans, and he was rich. 3 And he sought to see Jesus who he was; and could not for the crowd, because he was little of stature. 4 And he ran before, and climbed up upon a sycamore-tree to see him; for he was to pass that way . 5 And when Jesus came to the place, he looked up, and saw him, and said to him, Zaccheus, make haste, and come down: for to-day I must abide at thy house. 6 And he made haste, and came down, and received him joyfully. 7 And when they saw it , they all murmured, saying, That he was gone to be guest with a man that is a sinner. 8 And Zaccheus stood, and said to the Lord; Behold, Lord, the half of my goods I give to the poor; and if I have taken any thing from any man by false accusation, I restore him four-fold. 9 And Jesus said to him, This day is salvation come to this house, forasmuch as he also is a son of Abraham. 10 For the Son of man is come to seek and to save that which was lost. 11 And as they heard these things, he added and spoke a parable, because he was nigh to Jerusalem, and because they thought that the kingdom of God would immediately appear. 12 He said therefore, A certain nobleman went into a far country to receive for himself a kingdom, and to return. 13 And he called his ten servants, and delivered them ten pounds, and said to them, Occupy till I come. 14 But his citizens hated him, and sent a message after him, saying, We will not have this man to reign over us. 15 And it came to pass, that when he had returned, having received the kingdom, then he commanded these servants to be called to him, to whom he had given the money, that he might know how much every man had gained by trading. 16 Then came the first, saying, Lord, thy pound hath gained ten pounds. 17 And he said to him, Well, thou good servant: because thou hast been faithful in a very little, have thou authority over ten cities. 18 And the second came, saying, Lord, thy pound hath gained five pounds. 19 And he said likewise to him, Be thou also over five cities. 20 And another came, saying, Lord, behold, here is thy pound, which I have kept laid up in a napkin: 21 For I feared thee, because thou art an austere man: thou takest up what thou layedst not down, and reapest what thou didst not sow. 22 And he saith to him, Out of thy own mouth will I judge thee, thou wicked servant. Thou knewest me to be an austere man, taking up what I laid not down, and reaping what I did not sow: 23 Why then gavest thou not my money into the bank, that at my coming I might have required my own with interest? 24 And he said to them that stood by, Take from him the pound, and give it to him that hath ten pounds. 25 (And they said to him, Lord, he hath ten pounds.) 26 For I say to you, That to every one who hath shall be given; and from him that hath not, even what he hath shall be taken away from him. 27 But those my enemies, who would not that I should reign over them, bring hither, and slay them before me. 28 And when he had thus spoken, he went before, ascending towards Jerusalem. 29 And it came to pass, when he had come nigh to Bethphage and Bethany, at the mount called the mount of Olives, he sent two of his disciples, 30 Saying, Go ye into the village over against you ; in which at your entering ye will find a colt tied, on which yet never man sat: loose him, and bring him hither . 31 And if any man shall ask you, Why do ye loose him ? thus shall ye say to him, Because the Lord hath need of him. 32 And they that were sent, went and found even as he had said to them. 33 And as they were loosing the colt, the owners of it said to them, Why loose ye the colt? 34 And they said, The Lord hath need of him. 35 And they brought him to Jesus: and they cast their garments upon the colt, and they set Jesus upon him. 36 And as he went, they spread their clothes in the way. 37 And when he had come nigh, even now at the descent of the mount of Olives, the whole multitude of the disciples began to rejoice and praise God with a loud voice, for all the mighty works that they had seen. 38 Saying, Blessed be the King that cometh in the name of the Lord: Peace in heaven, and glory in the highest. 39 And some of the Pharisees from among the multitude said to him, Master, rebuke thy disciples. 40 And he answered and said to them, I tell you, that if these should hold their peace, the stones would immediately cry out. 41 And when he had come near, he beheld the city, and wept over it, 42 Saying, If thou hadst known, even thou, at least in this thy day, the things which belong to thy peace! but now they are hid from thy eyes. 43 For the days shall come upon thee, that thy enemies shall cast a trench about thee, and encompass thee, and keep thee in on every side, 44 And shall lay thee even with the ground, and thy children within thee: and they shall not leave in thee one stone upon another: because thou knewest not the time of thy visitation. 45 And he went into the temple, and began to cast out them that sold in it, and them that bought, 46 Saying to them, It is written, My house is the house of prayer, but ye have made it a den of thieves. 47 And he taught daily in the temple. But the chief priests, and the scribes, and the chief of the people sought to destroy him, 48 And could not find what they might do: for all the people were very attentive to hear him.

20

1 And it came to pass, that on one of those days, as he was teaching the people in the temple, and preaching the gospel, the chief priests and the scribes came upon him , with the elders, 2 And spoke to him, saying, Tell us, By what authority doest thou these things? or who is he that gave thee this authority? 3 And he answered and said to them, I will also ask you one thing; and answer me: 4 The baptism of John, was it from heaven, or from men? 5 And they reasoned with themselves, saying, If we shall say, From heaven; he will say, Why then believed ye him not? 6 But if we say, From men; all the people will stone us: for they are persuaded that John was a prophet. 7 And they answered, that they could not tell whence it was . 8 And Jesus said to them, Neither do I tell you by what authority I do these things. 9 Then he began to speak to the people this parable; A certain man planted a vineyard, and let it to husbandmen, and went into a far country for a long time. 10 And at the season he sent a servant to the husbandmen, that they should give him of the fruit of the vineyard: but the husbandmen beat him, and sent him away empty. 11 And again he sent another servant: and they beat him also, and treated him shamefully, and sent him away empty. 12 And again he sent the third: and they wounded him also, and cast him out. 13 Then said the lord of the vineyard, What shall I do? I will send my beloved son: it may be when they see him they will reverence him. 14 But when the husbandmen saw him, they reasoned among themselves, saying, This is the heir; come, let us kill him, that the inheritance may be ours. 15 So they cast him out of the vineyard, and killed him . What therefore will the lord of the vineyard do to them? 16 He will come and destroy these husbandmen, and will give the vineyard to others. And when they heard it , they said, may that never be. 17 And he beheld them, and said, What is this then that is written, The stone which the builders rejected, the same is become the head of the corner? 18 Whoever shall fall upon that stone, shall be broken: but on whomsoever it shall fall, it will grind him to powder. 19 And the chief priests and the scribes the same hour sought to lay hands on him; and they feared the people: for they perceived that he had spoken this parable against them. 20 And they watched him , and sent forth spies, who should feign themselves just men, that they might take hold of his words, that so they might deliver him to the power and authority of the governor. 21 And they asked him, saying, Master, we know that thou sayest and teachest rightly, neither acceptest thou the person of any , but teachest the way of God truly: 22 Is it lawful for us to give tribute to Cesar, or not? 23 But he perceived their craftiness, and said to them, Why tempt ye me? 24 Show me a penny. Whose image and superscription hath it? They answered and said, Cesar's. 25 And he said to them, Render therefore to Cesar the things which are Cesar's, and to God the things which are God's. 26 And they could not take hold of his words before the people: and they marveled at his answer, and held their peace. 27 Then came to him certain of the Sadducees (who deny that there is any resurrection) and they asked him, 28 Saying, Master, Moses wrote to us, If any man's brother should die, having a wife, and he should die without children, that his brother should take his wife, and raise up seed to his brother. 29 There were therefore seven brothers: and the first took a wife, and died without children. 30 And the second took her for a wife, and he died childless. 31 And the third took her; and in like manner the seven also: And they left no children, and died. 32 Last of all the woman died also. 33 Therefore in the resurrection, whose wife of them is she? for seven had her to wife. 34 And Jesus answering, said to them, The children of this world marry, and are given in marriage: 35 But they who shall be accounted worthy to obtain that world, and the resurrection from the dead, neither marry, nor are given in marriage. 36 Neither can they die any more: for they are equal to the angels; and are the children of God, being the children of the resurrection. 37 Now that the dead are raised, even Moses showed at the bush, when he calleth the Lord the God of Abraham, and the God of Isaac, and the God of Jacob. 38 For he is not a God of the dead, but of the living: for all live to him. 39 Then certain of the scribes answering, said, Master, thou hast well said. 40 And after that, they durst not ask him any question at all. 41 And he said to them, How say they that Christ is David's son? 42 And David himself saith in the book of Psalms, The LORD said to my Lord, Sit thou on my right hand, 43 Till I make thy enemies thy footstool. 44 David therefore calleth him Lord, how is he then his son? 45 Then in the audience of all the people, he said to his disciples, 46 Beware of the scribes, who desire to walk in long robes, and love greetings in the markets, and the highest seats in the synagogues, and the chief rooms at feasts; 47 Who devour widows' houses, and for a show make long prayers: the same shall receive greater damnation.

21

1 And he looked up, and saw rich men casting their gifts into the treasury. 2 And he saw also a certain poor widow, casting in thither two mites. 3 And he said, Of a truth I say to you, that this poor widow hath cast in more than they all. 4 For all these have of their abundance cast in to the offerings of God: but she of her penury hath cast in all the living that she had. 5 And as some spoke of the temple, that it was adorned with goodly stones, and gifts, he said, 6 As for these things which ye behold, the days will come, in which there shall not be left one stone upon another, that will not be thrown down. 7 And they asked him, saying, Master, but when will these things be? and what sign will there be when these things shall come to pass? 8 And he said, Take heed that ye be not deceived: for many will come in my name, saying, I am Christ ; and the time draweth near: therefore go ye not after them. 9 But when ye shall hear of wars, and commotions, be not terrified: for these things must first come to pass: but the end is not immediately. 10 Then said he to them, Nation will rise against nation, and kingdom against kingdom: 11 And great earthquakes will be in divers places, and famines, and pestilences: and fearful sights, and great signs will there be from heaven. 12 But before all these they will lay their hands on you, and persecute you , delivering you up to the synagogues, and into prisons, being brought before kings and rulers for my name's sake. 13 And it shall turn to you for a testimony. 14 Settle it therefore in your hearts, not to meditate before what ye shall answer. 15 For I will give you a mouth and wisdom, which all your adversaries shall not be able to gainsay nor resist. 16 And ye will be betrayed both by parents, and brethren, and kinsmen, and friends; and some of you will they cause to be put to death. 17 And ye will be hated by all men for my name's sake. 18 But there shall not a hair of your head perish. 19 In your patience possess ye your souls. 20 And when ye shall see Jerusalem compassed with armies, then know that its desolation is nigh. 21 Then let them who are in Judea flee to the mountains; and let them who are in the midst of it depart from it ; and let not them that are in the countries enter into it. 22 For these are the days of vengeance, that all things which are written may be fulfilled. 23 But woe to them that are with child, and to them that nurse infants in those days! for there shall be great distress in the land, and wrath upon this people. 24 And they shall fall by the edge of the sword, and shall be led away captive into all nations: and Jerusalem shall be trodden down by the Gentiles, until the times of the Gentiles shall be fulfilled. 25 And there shall be signs in the sun, and in the moon, and in the stars; and upon the earth distress of nations, with perplexity; the sea and the waves roaring; 26 Men's hearts failing them for fear, and for apprehension of those things which are coming on the earth: for the powers of heaven shall be shaken. 27 And then shall they see the Son of man coming in a cloud, with power and great glory. 28 And when these things begin to come to pass, then look up, and lift up your heads: for your redemption draweth nigh. 29 And he spoke to them a parable; Behold the fig-tree, and all the trees; 30 When they now shoot forth, ye see and know of your ownselves that summer is now nigh at hand. 31 So likewise ye, when ye see these things come to pass, know that the kingdom of God is nigh at hand. 32 Verily I say to you, This generation shall not pass away, till all be fulfilled. 33 Heaven and earth shall pass away: but my word shall not pass away. 34 And take heed to yourselves, lest at any time your hearts be overcharged with surfeiting and drunkenness, and cares of this life, and so that day come upon you unawares. 35 For as a snare shall it come on all them that dwell on the face of the whole earth. 36 Watch ye therefore, and pray always, that ye may be accounted worthy to escape all these things that shall come to pass, and to stand before the Son of man. 37 And in the day-time he was teaching in the temple; and at night he went out, and abode in the mount that is called the mount of Olives. 38 And all the people came early in the morning to him in the temple, to hear him.

22

1 Now the feast of unleavened bread drew nigh, which is called the Passover. 2 And the chief priests and scribes sought how they might kill him: for they feared the people. 3 Then Satan entered into Judas surnamed Iscariot, being of the number of the twelve. 4 And he went, and communed with the chief priests and captains, how he might betray him to them. 5 And they were glad, and covenanted to give him money. 6 And he promised, and sought opportunity to betray him to them in the absence of the multitude. 7 Then came the day of unleavened bread, when the passover must be killed. 8 And he sent Peter and John, saying, Go and prepare for us the passover, that we may eat. 9 And they said to him, Where wilt thou that we prepare? 10 And he said to them, Behold, when ye have entered into the city, there shall a man meet you, bearing a pitcher of water; follow him into the house where he entereth. 11 And ye shall say to the master of the house, The Master saith to thee, Where is the guest-chamber, where I may eat the passover with my disciples? 12 And he will show you a large upper room furnished: there make ready. 13 And they went and found as he had said to them: and they made ready the passover. 14 And when the hour was come, he sat down, and the twelve apostles with him. 15 And he said to them, I have earnestly desired to eat this passover with you before I suffer. 16 For I say to you, I will not any more eat of it until it shall be fulfilled in the kingdom of God. 17 And he took the cup, and gave thanks, and said, Take this, and divide it among yourselves. 18 For I say to you, I will not drink of the fruit of the vine, until the kingdom of God shall come. 19 And he took bread, and gave thanks, and broke it , and gave to them, saying, This is my body which is given for you: this do in remembrance of me. 20 Likewise also the cup after supper, saying, This cup is the new testament in my blood, which is shed for you. 21 But behold, the hand of him that betrayeth me is with me on the table. 22 And truly the Son of man goeth as it was determined: but woe to that man by whom he is betrayed! 23 And they began to inquire among themselves, which of them it was that should do this thing. 24 And there was also a strife among them, which of them should be accounted the greatest. 25 And he said to them, The kings of the Gentiles exercise lordship over them; and they that exercise authority upon them, are called benefactors. 26 But ye shall not be so: but he that is greatest among you, let him be as the younger; and he that is chief, as he that doth serve. 27 For which is greater, he that sitteth at table, or he that serveth? is not he that sitteth at table? but I am among you as he that serveth. 28 Ye are they who have continued with me in my temptations. 29 And I appoint to you a kingdom, as my Father hath appointed to me; 30 That ye may eat and drink at my table in my kingdom, and sit on thrones, judging the twelve tribes of Israel. 31 And the Lord said, Simon, Simon, behold, Satan hath desired to have you, that he may sift you as wheat: 32 But I have prayed for thee, that thy faith fail not; and when thou art converted, strengthen thy brethren. 33 And he said to him, Lord, I am ready to go with thee both into prison, and to death. 34 And he said, I tell thee, Peter, the cock will not crow this day, before thou wilt thrice deny that thou knowest me. 35 And he said to them, When I sent you without purse, and sack, and shoes, lacked ye any thing? And they said, Nothing. 36 Then said he to them, But now he that hath a purse, let him take it , and likewise his sack: and he that hath no sword, let him sell his garment, and buy one. 37 For I say to you, that this which is written must yet be accomplished in me, And he was reckoned among the transgressors: for the things concerning me have an end. 38 And they said, Lord, behold, here are two swords. And he said to them, It is enough. 39 And he came out, and went, as he was wont, to the mount of Olives; and his disciples also followed him. 40 And when he was at the place, he said to them, Pray, that ye enter not into temptation. 41 And he was withdrawn from them about a stone's cast, and kneeled down, and prayed. 42 Saying, Father, if thou art willing, remove this cup from me: nevertheless not my will, but thine be done. 43 And there appeared to him an angel from heaven, strengthening him. 44 And being in an agony, he prayed more earnestly: and his sweat was as it were great drops of blood falling to the ground. 45 And when he arose from prayer, and had come to his disciples, he found them sleeping for sorrow: 46 And said to them, Why sleep ye? rise and pray, lest ye enter into temptation. 47 And while he was yet speaking, behold a multitude, and he that was called Judas, one of the twelve, went before them, and drew near to Jesus to kiss him. 48 But Jesus said to him, Judas, betrayest thou the Son of man with a kiss? 49 When they who were about him, saw what would follow, they said to him, Lord, shall we smite with the sword? 50 And one of them smote the servant of the high priest, and cut off his right ear. 51 And Jesus answered and said, Suffer ye thus far. And he touched his ear, and healed him. 52 Then Jesus said to the chief priests, and captains of the temple, and the elders who had come to him, Are ye come out as against a thief, with swords and staffs? 53 When I was daily with you in the temple, ye stretched forth no hands against me: but this is your hour, and the power of darkness. 54 Then they took him, and led him , and brought him into the high priest's house. And Peter followed at a distance. 55 And when they had kindled a fire in the midst of the hall, and were set down together, Peter sat down among them. 56 But a certain maid beheld him as he sat by the fire, and earnestly looked upon him, and said, This man was also with him. 57 And he denied him, saying, Woman, I know him not. 58 And after a little while another saw him, and said, Thou art also of them. And Peter said, Man, I am not. 59 And about the space of one hour after, another confidently affirmed, saying, In truth this man also was with him; for he is a Galilean. 60 And Peter said, Man, I know not what thou sayest. And immediately, while he was yet speaking, the cock crowed. 61 And the Lord turned, and looked upon Peter. And Peter remembered the word of the Lord, how he had said to him, Before the cock shall crow, thou wilt deny me thrice. 62 And Peter went out, and wept bitterly. 63 And the men that held Jesus, mocked him, and smote him . 64 And when they had blindfolded him, they struck him on the face, and asked him, saying, Prophesy, who is it that smote thee? 65 And many other things blasphemously they spoke against him. 66 And as soon as it was day, the elders of the people, and the chief priests, and the scribes came together, and led him into their council, 67 Saying, Art thou the Christ? tell us. And he said to them, If I tell you, ye will not believe. 68 And if I also ask you , ye will not answer me, nor let me go. 69 Hereafter will the Son of man sit on the right hand of the power of God. 70 Then said they all, Art thou then the Son of God? And he said to them, Ye say that I am. 71 And they said, What need have we of any further testimony? for we ourselves have heard from his own mouth.

23

1 And the whole multitude of them arose, and led him to Pilate. 2 And they began to accuse him, saying, We found this man perverting the nation, and forbidding to give tribute to Cesar, saying, that he himself is Christ a king. 3 And Pilate asked him, saying, Art thou the King of the Jews? And he answered him and said, Thou sayest it . 4 Then said Pilate to the chief priests, and to the people, I find no fault in this man. 5 And they were the more fierce, saying, He stirreth up the people, teaching throughout all Judea, beginning from Galilee to this place. 6 When Pilate heard of Galilee, he asked whether the man was a Galilean. 7 And as soon as he knew that he belonged to Herod's jurisdiction, he sent him to Herod, who himself was also at Jerusalem at that time. 8 And when Herod saw Jesus, he was exceeding glad: for he had been for a long time, desirous to see him, because he had heard many things of him; and he hoped to see some miracle done by him. 9 Then he questioned with him in many words; but he answered him nothing. 10 And the chief priests and scribes stood and vehemently accused him. 11 And Herod with his troops set him at naught, and mocked him , and arrayed him in a gorgeous robe, and sent him again to Pilate. 12 And the same day Pilate and Herod were made friends together; for before they were at enmity between themselves. 13 And Pilate, when he had called together the chief priests, and the rulers, and the people, 14 Said to them, Ye have brought this man to me, as one that perverteth the people: and behold, I, having examined him before you, have found no fault in this man, touching those things of which ye accuse him; 15 No, nor yet Herod: for I sent you to him; and lo, nothing worthy of death is done to him: 16 I will therefore chastise him, and release him . 17 (For of necessity he must release one to them at the feast.) 18 And they cried out all at once, saying, Away with this man , and release to us Barabbas: 19 (Who, for a certain sedition made in the city, and for murder, was cast into prison.) 20 Pilate therefore, willing to release Jesus, spoke again to them. 21 But they cried, saying, Crucify, crucify him. 22 And he said to them the third time, Why, what evil hath he done? I have found no cause of death in him; I will therefore chastise him, and let him go. 23 And they were urgent with loud voices, requiring that he might be crucified: and the voices of them, and of the chief priests prevailed. 24 And Pilate gave sentence that it should be as they required. 25 And he released to them him that for sedition and murder had been cast into prison, whom they had desired; but he delivered Jesus to their will. 26 And as they led him away, they laid hold upon one Simon a Cyrenian, coming out of the country, and on him they laid the cross, that he might bear it after Jesus. 27 And there followed him a great company of people, and of women, who also bewailed and lamented him. 28 But Jesus turning to them, said, Daughters of Jerusalem, weep not for me, but weep for yourselves, and for your children. 29 For behold, the days are coming, in which they shall say, Blessed are the barren, and the wombs that never bore, and the breasts which never nourished infants. 30 Then shall they begin to say to the mountains, Fall on us; and to the hills, Cover us. 31 For if they do these things in a green tree, what will be done in the dry? 32 And two others, who were malefactors, were led with him to be put to death. 33 And when they had come to the place which is called Calvary, there they crucified him, and the malefactors; one on the right hand, and the other on the left. 34 Then said Jesus, Father, forgive them: for they know not what they do. And they parted his raiment, and cast lots. 35 And the people stood beholding. And the rulers also with them derided him , saying, He saved others; let him save himself, if he is Christ the chosen of God. 36 And the soldiers also mocked him, coming to him, and offering him vinegar, 37 And saying, If thou art the King of the Jews, save thyself. 38 And a superscription also was written over him, in letters of Greek, and Latin, and Hebrew, THIS IS THE KING OF THE JEWS. 39 And one of the malefactors, who were hanged, railed on him, saying, If thou art Christ, save thyself and us. 40 But the other answering, rebuked him, saying, Dost not thou fear God, seeing thou art in the same condemnation? 41 And we indeed justly; for we receive the due reward of our deeds: but this man hath done nothing amiss. 42 And he said to Jesus, Lord, remember me when thou comest into thy kingdom. 43 And Jesus said to him, Verily I say to thee, This day shalt thou be with me in paradise. 44 And it was about the sixth hour, and there was a darkness over all the land until the ninth hour. 45 And the sun was darkened, and the vail of the temple was rent in the midst. 46 And when Jesus had cried with a loud voice, he said, Father, into thy hands I commend my spirit: and having said thus, he expired. 47 Now when the centurion saw what was done, he glorified God, saying, Certainly this was a righteous man. 48 And all the people that came together to that sight, beholding the things which were done, smote their breasts, and returned. 49 And all his acquaintance, and the women that followed him from Galilee, stood afar off beholding these things. 50 And behold, there was a man named Joseph, a counselor: and he was a good man, and a just: 51 (The same had not consented to the counsel and deed of them) he was of Arimathea, a city of the Jews; who also himself waited for the kingdom of God. 52 This man went to Pilate, and begged the body of Jesus. 53 And he took it down, and wrapped it in linen, and laid it in a sepulcher that was hewn in stone, in which man was never before laid. 54 And that day was the preparation, and the sabbath drew on. 55 And the women also, who came with him from Galilee, followed after, and beheld the sepulcher, and how his body was laid. 56 And they returned, and prepared spices and ointments; and rested on the sabbath, according to the commandment.

24

1 Now upon the first day of the week, very early in the morning, they came to the sepulcher, bringing the spices which they had prepared, and certain others with them. 2 And they found the stone rolled away from the sepulcher. 3 And they entered in, and found not the body of the Lord Jesus. 4 And it came to pass, as they were much perplexed at this, behold, two men stood by them in shining garments. 5 And as they were afraid, and bowed down their faces to the earth, they said to them, Why seek ye the living among the dead? 6 He is not here, but is risen. Remember how he spoke to you when he was yet in Galilee, 7 Saying, The Son of man must be delivered into the hands of sinful men, and be crucified, and the third day rise again. 8 And they remembered his words, 9 And returned from the sepulcher, and told all these things to the eleven, and to all the rest. 10 It was Mary Magdalene, and Joanna, and Mary the mother of James, and other women that were with them, who told these things to the apostles. 11 And their words seemed to them as idle tales, and they believed them not. 12 Then Peter arose, and ran to the sepulcher, and stooping down, he beheld the linen clothes laid by themselves, and departed, wondering in himself at that which had come to pass. 13 And behold, two of them went that same day to a village called Emmaus, which was from Jerusalem about sixty furlongs. 14 And they talked together of all these things which had happened. 15 And it came to pass, that, while they communed together , and reasoned, Jesus himself drew near, and went with them. 16 But their eyes were held, that they should not know him. 17 And he said to them, What manner of communications are these that ye have one to another, as ye walk, and are sad? 18 And one of them, whose name was Cleopas, answering, said to him, Art thou only a stranger in Jerusalem, and hast not known the things which have come to pass there in these days? 19 And he said to them, What things? And they said to him, Concerning Jesus of Nazareth, who was a prophet mighty in deed and word before God, and all the people: 20 And how the chief priests and our rulers delivered him to be condemned to death, and crucified him. 21 But we trusted that it had been he who would have redeemed Israel: and besides all this, to-day is the third day since these things were done. 22 Yes, and certain women also of our company made us astonished, who were early at the sepulcher. 23 And when they found not his body, they came, saying, that they had also seen a vision of angels, who said that he was alive. 24 And certain of them who were with us, went to the sepulcher, and found it even so as the women had said: but him they saw not. 25 Then he said to them, O fools, and slow of heart to believe all that the prophets have spoken! 26 Ought not Christ to suffer these things, and to enter into his glory? 27 And beginning at Moses, and all the prophets, he expounded to them in all the scriptures the things concerning himself. 28 And they drew nigh to the village whither they were going: and he made as though he would go further. 29 But they constrained him, saying, Abide with us: for it is towards evening, and the day is far spent. And he went in to tarry with them. 30 And it came to pass, as he sat at table with them, he took bread, and blessed it , and broke, and gave to them. 31 And their eyes were opened, and they knew him: and he vanished out of their sight. 32 And they said one to another, Did not our heart burn within us while he talked with us by the way, and while he opened to us the scriptures? 33 And they rose the same hour, and returned to Jerusalem, and found the eleven assembled, and them that were with them, 34 Saying, The Lord is risen indeed, and hath appeared to Simon. 35 And they told what things were done in the way, and how he was known to them in breaking of bread. 36 And as they were thus speaking, Jesus himself stood in the midst of them, and saith to them, Peace be to you. 37 But they were terrified and affrighted, and supposed that they had seen a spirit. 38 And he said to them, Why are ye troubled? and why do thoughts arise in your hearts? 39 Behold my hands and my feet, that it is I myself: handle me, and see; for a spirit hath not flesh and bones, as ye see me have. 40 And when he had thus spoken, he showed them his hands and his feet. 41 And while they yet believed not for joy, and wondered, he said to them, Have ye here any thing for food? 42 And they gave him a piece of a broiled fish, and a honey-comb. 43 And he took it , and ate before them. 44 And he said to them, These are the words which I spoke to you, while I was yet with you, that all things must be fulfilled, which were written in the law of Moses, and in the prophets, and in the psalms, concerning me. 45 Then he opened their understanding, that they might understand the scriptures, 46 And said to them, Thus it is written, and thus it behooved Christ to suffer, and to rise from the dead the third day: 47 And that repentance and remission of sins should be preached in his name among all nations, beginning at Jerusalem. 48 And ye are witnesses of these things. 49 And behold, I send the promise of my Father upon you: but tarry ye in the city of Jerusalem, until ye are endued with power from on high. 50 And he led them out as far as to Bethany: and he lifted up his hands, and blessed them. 51 And it came to pass, while he was blessing them, he was parted from them, and carried up into heaven. 52 And they worshiped him, and returned to Jerusalem with great joy: 53 And were continually in the temple, praising and blessing God. Amen.

Matthew

1
2
3
4
5
6
7
8
9
10

11
12
13
14
15
16
17
18
19
20

21
22
23
24
25
26
27
28

THE GOSPEL ACCORDING TO ST. MATTHEW

1

1 The book of the generation of Jesus Christ, the son of David, the son of Abraham. 2 Abraham begat Isaac; and Isaac begat Jacob; and Jacob begat Judah and his brethren; 3 And Judah begat Phares and Zara of Thamar; and Phares begat Esrom; and Esrom begat Aram; 4 And Aram begat Aminadab; and Aminadab begat Naasson; and Naasson begat Salmon; 5 And Salmon begat Booz of Rachab; and Booz begat Obed of Ruth; and Obed begat Jesse; 6 And Jesse begat David the king; and David the king begat Solomon of her that had been the wife of Uriah; 7 And Solomon begat Roboam; and Roboam begat Abia; and Abia begat Asa; 8 And Asa begat Josaphat; and Josaphat begat Joram; and Joram begat Ozias; 9 And Ozias begat Joatham; and Joatham begat Achaz; and Achaz begat Ezekias; 10 And Ezekias begat Manasses; and Manasses begat Amon; and Amon begat Josias; 11 And Josias begat Jechonias and his brethren, about the time they were carried away to Babylon: 12 And after they were brought to Babylon, Jechonias begat Salathiel; and Salathiel begat Zorobabel; 13 And Zorobabel begat Abiud; and Abiud begat Eliakim; and Eliakim begat Azor; 14 And Azor begat Zadok; and Zadok begat Achim; and Achim begat Eliud; 15 And Eliud begat Eleazar; and Eleazar begat Matthan; and Matthan begat Jacob; 16 And Jacob begat Joseph the husband of Mary, of whom was born Jesus, who is called Christ. 17 So all the generations from Abraham to David are fourteen generations; and from David until the carrying away into Babylon are fourteen generations; and from the carrying away into Babylon to Christ are fourteen generations. 18 Now the birth of Jesus Christ was in this manner: When his mother Mary was espoused to Joseph, before they came together, she was found with child by the Holy Spirit. 19 Then Joseph her husband, being a just man , and not willing to make her a public example, purposed to put her away privately. 20 But while he thought on these things, the angel of the Lord appeared to him in a dream, saying, Joseph, thou son of David, fear not to take to thee Mary thy wife: for that which is conceived in her is by the Holy Spirit. 21 And she shall bring forth a son, and thou shalt call his name JESUS: for he shall save his people from their sins. 22 Now all this was done, that it might be fulfilled which was spoken from the Lord by the prophet, saying, 23 Behold, a virgin shall be with child, and shall bring forth a son, and they shall call his name Emmanuel, which being interpreted is, God with us. 24 Then Joseph, being raised from sleep, did as the angel of the Lord had bidden him, and took to him his wife: 25 And knew her not till she had brought forth her first-born son: and he called his name JESUS.

2

1 Now, after Jesus was born in Bethlehem of Judea in the days of Herod the king, behold, there came wise men from the east to Jerusalem, 2 Saying, Where is he that is born king of the Jews? for we have seen his star in the east, and have come to worship him. 3 When Herod the king had heard these things , he was troubled, and all Jerusalem with him. 4 And when he had assembled all the chief priests and scribes of the people, he inquired of them where Christ should be born. 5 And they said to him, In Bethlehem of Judea: for thus it is written by the prophet, 6 And thou Bethlehem, in the land of Judah, art not the least among the princes of Judah: for out of thee shall come a Governor, that shall rule my people Israel. 7 Then Herod, when he had privately called the wise men, inquired of them diligently what time the star appeared. 8 And he sent them to Bethlehem, and said, Go, and search diligently for the young child; and when ye have found him , bring me word again, that I may come and worship him also. 9 When they had heard the king, they departed; and lo, the star, which they saw in the east, went before them, till it came and stood over where the young child was. 10 When they saw the star, they rejoiced with exceeding great joy. 11 And when they had come into the house, they saw the young child with Mary his mother, and fell down, and worshiped him: and when they had opened their treasures, they presented to him gifts; gold, and frankincense, and myrrh. 12 And being warned by God in a dream that they should not return to Herod, they departed into their own country another way. 13 And when they had departed, behold, the angel of the Lord appeareth to Joseph in a dream, saying, Arise, and take the young child and his mother, and flee into Egypt, and be thou there until I bring thee word: for Herod will seek the young child to destroy him. 14 When he arose, he took the young child and his mother by night, and departed into Egypt: 15 And was there until the death of Herod: that it might be fulfilled which was spoken from the Lord by the prophet, saying, Out of Egypt have I called my son. 16 Then Herod, when he saw that he was mocked by the wise men, was exceeding wroth, and sent forth, and slew all the children that were in Bethlehem, and in all its borders, from two years old and under, according to the time which he had diligently inquired of the wise men. 17 Then was fulfilled that which was spoken by Jeremiah the prophet, saying, 18 In Rama was there a voice heard, lamentation, and weeping, and great mourning, Rachel weeping for her children, and would not be comforted, because they are not. 19 But when Herod was dead, behold, an angel of the Lord appeareth in a dream to Joseph in Egypt, 20 Saying, Arise, and take the young child and his mother, and go into the land of Israel: for they are dead who sought the young child's life. 21 And he arose, and took the young child and his mother, and came into the land of Israel. 22 But when he heard that Archelaus reigned in Judea in the room of his father Herod, he was afraid to go thither: notwithstanding, being warned by God in a dream, he turned aside into the parts of Galilee: 23 And he came and dwelt in a city called Nazareth: that it might be fulfilled which was spoken by the prophets, He shall be called a Nazarene.

3

1 In those days came John the Baptist, preaching in the wilderness of Judea, 2 And saying, Repent ye: for the kingdom of heaven is at hand. 3 For this is he that was spoken of by the prophet Isaiah, saying, The voice of one crying in the wilderness, Prepare ye the way of the Lord, make his paths straight. 4 And the same John had his raiment of camel's hair, and a leathern girdle about his loins; and his food was locusts and wild honey. 5 Then went out to him Jerusalem, and all Judea, and all the region about Jordan, 6 And were baptized by him in Jordan, confessing their sins. 7 But when he saw many of the Pharisees and Sadducees come to his baptism, he said to them, O generation of vipers, who hath warned you to flee from the wrath to come? 8 Bring forth therefore fruits meet for repentance: 9 And think not to say within yourselves, We have Abraham for our father: for I say to you, that God is able of these stones to raise up children to Abraham. 10 And now also the ax is laid to the root of the trees: therefore every tree which bringeth not forth good fruit is hewn down, and cast into the fire. 11 I indeed baptize you with water to repentance: but he that cometh after me is mightier than I, whose shoes I am not worthy to bear: he shall baptize you with the Holy Spirit, and with fire: 12 Whose winnowing fan is in his hand, and he will thoroughly cleanse his floor, and gather his wheat into the granary; but he will burn the chaff with unquenchable fire. 13 Then cometh Jesus from Galilee to Jordan to John, to be baptized by him. 14 But John forbad him, saying, I have need to be baptized by thee, and comest thou to me? 15 And Jesus answering said to him, Suffer it to be so now: for thus it becometh us to fulfill all righteousness. Then he suffered him. 16 And Jesus, when he was baptized, went up immediately out of the water: and lo, the heavens were opened to him, and he saw the Spirit of God descending like a dove, and lighting upon him: 17 And lo, a voice from heaven, saying, This is my beloved Son, in whom I am well pleased.

4

1 Then was Jesus led by the Spirit into the wilderness, to be tempted by the devil. 2 And when he had fasted forty days and forty nights, he was afterward hungry. 3 And when the tempter came to him, he said, If thou art the son of God, command that these stones be made bread. 4 But he answered and said, It is written, Man shall not live by bread alone, but by every word that proceedeth out of the mouth of God. 5 Then the devil taketh him up into the holy city, and setteth him on a pinnacle of the temple, 6 And saith to him, If thou art the Son of God, cast thyself down, for it is written, He shall give his angels charge concerning thee: and in their hands they shall uphold thee, lest at any time thou dash thy foot against a stone. 7 Jesus said to him, It is written again, Thou shalt not tempt the Lord thy God. 8 Again, the devil taketh him up upon an exceeding high mountain, and showeth him all the kingdoms of the world, and the glory of them, 9 And saith to him, All these things will I give thee, if thou wilt fall down and worship me. 10 Then saith Jesus to him, Be gone, Satan: for it is written, Thou shalt worship the Lord thy God, and him only shalt thou serve. 11 Then the devil leaveth him, and behold, angels came and ministered to him. 12 Now when Jesus had heard that John was cast into prison, he departed into Galilee. 13 And leaving Nazareth, he came and dwelt in Capernaum, which is upon the sea coast, in the borders of Zabulon and Nephthalim; 14 That it might be fulfilled which was spoken by Isaiah the prophet, saying, 15 The land of Zabulon, and the land of Nephthalim, by the way of the sea, beyond Jordan, Galilee of the Gentiles: 16 The people who sat in darkness, saw great light; and to them who sat in the region and shades of death, light hath arisen. 17 From that time Jesus began to preach, and to say, Repent: for the kingdom of heaven is at hand. 18 And Jesus, walking by the sea of Galilee, saw two brethren, Simon called Peter, and Andrew his brother, casting a net into the sea: for they were fishers. 19 And he saith to them, Follow me, and I will make you fishers of men. 20 And they immediately left their nets, and followed him. 21 And going on from thence, he saw other two brethren, James the son of Zebedee, and John his brother, in a boat with Zebedee their father, mending their nets: and he called them. 22 And they immediately left the boat, and their father, and followed him. 23 And Jesus went about all Galilee, teaching in their synagogues, and preaching the gospel of the kingdom, and healing all manner of sickness, and all manner of disease among the people. 24 And his fame spread throughout all Syria: and they brought to him all sick people that were taken with diverse diseases and torments, and those who were possessed with demons, and those who were lunatic, and those that had the palsy; and he healed them. 25 And there followed him great multitudes of people from Galilee, and from Decapolis, and from Jerusalem, and from Judea, and from beyond Jordan.

5

1 And seeing the multitudes, he ascended a mountain: and when he was seated, his disciples came to him. 2 And he opened his mouth, and taught them, saying, 3 Blessed are the poor in spirit: for theirs is the kingdom of heaven. 4 Blessed are they that mourn: for they shall be comforted. 5 Blessed are the meek: for they shall inherit the earth. 6 Blessed are they who hunger and thirst for righteousness: for they shall be filled. 7 Blessed are the merciful: for they shall obtain mercy. 8 Blessed are the pure in heart: for they shall see God. 9 Blessed are the peace-makers: for they shall be called children of God. 10 Blessed are they who are persecuted for righteousness' sake: for theirs is the kingdom of heaven. 11 Blessed are ye when men shall revile you, and persecute you , and shall say all manner of evil against you falsely, for my sake. 12 Rejoice, and be exceeding glad: for great is your reward in heaven: for so they persecuted the prophets who were before you. 13 Ye are the salt of the earth: but if the salt hath lost its savor, with what shall it be salted? it is thenceforth good for nothing, but to be cast out, and to be trodden under foot by men. 14 Ye are the light of the world. A city that is set on a hill cannot be hid. 15 Neither do men light a candle, and put it under a close vessel, but on a candlestick: and it giveth light to all that are in the house. 16 Let your light so shine before men, that they may see your good works, and glorify your Father who is in heaven. 17 Think not that I am come to destroy the law, or the prophets: I am not come to destroy, but to fulfill. 18 For verily I say to you, Till heaven and earth shall pass away, one jot or one tittle shall in no wise pass from the law, till all be fulfilled. 19 Whoever therefore shall break one of these least commandments, and shall teach men so, he shall be called the least in the kingdom of heaven: but whoever shall do, and teach them , the same shall be called great in the kingdom of heaven. 20 For I say to you, That except your righteousness shall exceed the righteousness of the scribes and Pharisees, ye shall in no case enter into the kingdom of heaven. 21 Ye have heard that it was said to them of old time, Thou shalt not kill; and whoever shall kill, shall be in danger of the judgment: 22 But I say to you, That whoever is angry with his brother without a cause, shall be in danger of the judgment: and whoever shall say to his brother, Raca, shall be in danger of the council: but whoever shall say, Thou fool, shall be in danger of hell-fire. 23 Therefore if thou shalt bring thy gift to the altar, and there remember that thy brother hath something against thee; 24 Leave there thy gift before the altar, and go thy way; first be reconciled to thy brother, and then come and offer thy gift. 25 Agree with thy adversary quickly, while thou art in the way with him; lest at any time the adversary deliver thee to the judge, and the judge deliver thee to the officer, and thou be cast into prison. 26 Verily, I say to thee, thou shalt by no means come out thence, till thou hast paid the uttermost penny. 27 Ye have heard that it was said to them of old time, Thou shalt not commit adultery: 28 But I say to you, That whoever looketh on a woman to lust after her, hath committed adultery with her already in his heart. 29 And if thy right eye shall cause thee to sin, pluck it out, and cast it from thee: for it is profitable for thee that one of thy members should perish, and not that thy whole body should be cast into hell. 30 And if thy right hand shall cause thee to sin, cut it off, and cast it from thee: for it is profitable for thee that one of thy members should perish, and not that thy whole body should be cast into hell. 31 It hath been said, Whoever shall put away his wife, let him give her a writing of divorcement: 32 But I say to you, That whoever shall put away his wife, saving for the cause of lewdness, causeth her to commit adultery: and whoever shall marry her that is divorced, committeth adultery. 33 Again, ye have heard that it hath been said to them of old time, Thou shalt not forswear thyself, but shalt perform to the Lord thy oaths: 34 But I say to you, Swear not at all: neither by heaven; for it is God's throne: 35 Nor by the earth; for it is his footstool: neither by Jerusalem; for it is the city of the great King, 36 Neither shalt thou swear by thy head, because thou canst not make one hair white or black. 37 But let your communication be, Yea, yea, Nay, nay: for whatever is more than these cometh of evil. 38 Ye have heard that it hath been said, An eye for an eye, and a tooth for a tooth. 39 But I say to you, That ye resist not evil: but whoever shall strike thee on thy right cheek, turn to him the other also. 40 And if any man will sue thee at the law, and take away thy coat, let him have thy cloke also. 41 And whoever shall constrain thee to go one mile, go with him two. 42 Give to him that asketh thee, and from him that would borrow of thee, turn not thou away. 43 Ye have heard that it hath been said, Thou shalt love thy neighbor, and hate thy enemy: 44 But I say to you, Love your enemies, bless them that curse you, do good to them that hate you, and pray for them who despitefully use you, and persecute you; 45 That ye may be the children of your Father who is in heaven: for he maketh his sun to rise on the evil and on the good, and sendeth rain on the just and on the unjust. 46 For if ye love them who love you, what reward have ye? do not even the publicans the same? 47 And if ye salute your brethren only, what do ye more than others ? do not even the publicans so? 48 Be ye therefore perfect, even as your Father who is in heaven is perfect.

6

1 Take heed that ye do not your alms before men, to be seen by them: otherwise ye have no reward from your Father who is in heaven. 2 Therefore, when thou doest thy alms, do not sound a trumpet before thee, as the hypocrites do, in the synagogues, and in the streets, that they may have glory from men. Verily, I say to you, they have their reward. 3 But when thou doest alms, let not thy left hand know what thy right hand doeth: 4 That thy alms may be in secret; and thy Father who seeth in secret, himself will reward thee openly. 5 And when thou prayest, thou shalt not be as the hypocrites are : for they love to pray standing in the synagogues, and in the corners of the streets, that they may be seen by men. Verily, I say to you, they have their reward. 6 But thou, when thou prayest, enter into thy closet, and when thou hast shut thy door, pray to thy Father who is in secret, and thy Father who seeth in secret, will reward thee openly. 7 But when ye pray, use not vain repetitions, as the heathen do: for they think that they shall be heard for their much speaking. 8 Therefore be ye not like them: for your Father knoweth what things ye need before ye ask him. 9 After this manner therefore pray ye: Our Father who art in heaven, Hallowed be thy name. 10 Thy kingdom come. Thy will be done on earth as it is in heaven. 11 Give us this day our daily bread. 12 And forgive us our debts, as we forgive our debtors. 13 And lead us not into temptation, but deliver us from evil. For thine is the kingdom, and the power, and the glory, for ever. Amen. 14 For, if ye forgive men their trespasses, your heavenly Father will also forgive you: 15 But if ye forgive not men their trespasses, neither will your Father forgive your trespasses. 16 Moreover, when ye fast, be not as the hypocrites, of a sad countenance: for they disfigure their faces, that they may appear to men to fast. Verily, I say to you, they have their reward. 17 But thou, when thou fastest, anoint thy head, and wash thy face; 18 That thou mayest not appear to men to fast, but to thy Father, who is in secret: and thy Father, who seeth in secret, shall reward thee openly. 19 Lay not up for yourselves treasures upon earth, where moth and rust doth corrupt, and where thieves break through and steal: 20 But lay up for yourselves treasures in heaven, where neither moth nor rust doth corrupt, and where thieves do not break through nor steal. 21 For where your treasure is, there will your heart be also. 22 The light of the body is the eye: if therefore thy eye is good, thy whole body will be full of light. 23 But if thy eye be evil, thy whole body will be full of darkness. If therefore the light that is in thee is darkness, how great is that darkness! 24 No man can serve two masters: for either he will hate the one, and love the other; or else he will hold to the one, and despise the other. Ye cannot serve God and mammon. 25 Therefore I say to you, Be not anxious for your life, what ye shall eat, or what ye shall drink; nor yet for your body, what ye shall put on. Is not the life more than food, and the body than raiment? 26 Behold the fowls of the air: for they sow not, neither do they reap, nor gather into barns; yet your heavenly Father feedeth them. Are ye not much better than they? 27 Which of you by anxious care can add one cubit to his stature? 28 And why are ye anxious for raiment? Consider the lilies of the field how they grow? they toil not, neither do they spin? 29 And yet I say to you, that even Solomon in all his glory was not arrayed like one of these. 30 Wherefore, if God so clotheth the grass of the field, which to-day is, and to-morrow is cast into the oven, will he not much more clothe you, O ye of little faith? 31 Therefore be not anxious, saying, What shall we eat? or what shall we drink? or, with what shall we be clothed? 32 (For after all these things do the Gentiles seek) for your heavenly Father knoweth that ye have need of all these things. 33 But seek ye first the kingdom of God, and his righteousness, and all these things shall be added to you. 34 Therefore be not anxious for the morrow: for the morrow will be solicitous for the things of itself. Sufficient to the day is its own evil.

7

1 Judge not, that ye be not judged. 2 For with what judgment ye judge, ye shall be judged: and the measure which ye give, shall be measured to you again. 3 And why beholdest thou the mote that is in thy brother's eye, but considerest not the beam that is in thy own eye? 4 Or how wilt thou say to thy brother, Let me pull out the mote out of thy eye; and behold, a beam is in thy own eye? 5 Thou hypocrite, first cast out the beam out of thy own eye; and then shalt thou see clearly to cast out the mote out of thy brother's eye. 6 Give not that which is holy to dogs, neither cast ye your pearls before swine, lest they trample them under their feet, and turn again and rend you. 7 Ask, and it shall be given you; seek, and ye shall find; knock, and the door shall be opened to you: 8 For every one that asketh, receiveth; and he that seeketh, findeth; and to him that knocketh, the door shall be opened. 9 Or what man is there of you, who, if his son shall ask bread, will give him a stone? 10 Or if he shall ask a fish, will he give him a serpent? 11 If ye then being evil know how to give good gifts to your children, how much more shall your Father who is in heaven give good things to them that ask him? 12 Therefore all things whatever ye would that men should do to you, do ye even so to them: for this is the law and the prophets. 13 Enter ye in at the strait gate; for wide is the gate, and broad is the way, that leadeth to destruction, and many there are who go in by it. 14 Because strait is the gate, and narrow is the way, which leadeth to life, and few there are that find it. 15 Beware of false prophets, who come to you in sheep's clothing, but inwardly they are ravening wolves. 16 Ye shall know them by their fruits: Do men gather grapes from thorns, or figs from thistles: 17 Even so every good tree bringeth forth good fruit; but a corrupt tree bringeth forth evil fruit. 18 A good tree cannot bring forth evil fruit, neither can a corrupt tree bring forth good fruit. 19 Every tree that bringeth not forth good fruit is hewn down, and cast into the fire. 20 Wherefore by their fruits ye shall know them, 21 Not every one that saith to me, Lord, Lord, shall enter into the kingdom of heaven; but he that doeth the will of my Father who is in heaven. 22 Many will say to me in that day, Lord, Lord, have we not prophesied in thy name? and in thy name have cast out demons? and in thy name done many wonderful works? 23 And then will I profess to them, I never knew you: depart from me, ye that work iniquity. 24 Therefore whoever heareth these sayings of mine, and doeth them, I will liken him to a wise man, who built his house upon a rock: 25 And the rain descended, and the floods came, and the winds blew, and beat upon that house; and it fell not: for it was founded upon a rock. 26 And every one that heareth these sayings of mine, and doeth them not, shall be likened to a foolish man, who built his house upon the sand: 27 And the rain descended, and the floods came, and the winds blew, and beat upon that house; and it fell, and great was the fall of it. 28 And it came to pass when Jesus had ended these sayings, the people were astonished at his doctrine. 29 For he taught them as one having authority, and not as the scribes.

8

1 When he had come down from the mountain, great multitudes followed him. 2 And behold, there came a leper and worshiped him, saying, Lord, if thou wilt, thou canst make me clean. 3 And Jesus put forth his hand, and touched him, saying, I will; be thou clean. And immediately his leprosy was cleansed. 4 And Jesus saith to him, See thou tell no man; but go, show thyself to the priest, and offer the gift that Moses commanded, for a testimony to them. 5 And when Jesus had entered into Capernaum, there came to him a centurion, beseeching him, 6 And saying, Lord, my servant lieth at home sick with the palsy, grievously tormented. 7 And Jesus saith to him, I will come and heal him. 8 The centurion answered and said, Lord, I am not worthy that thou shouldst come under my roof: but speak the word only, and my servant will be healed. 9 For I am a man under authority, having soldiers under me: and I say to this man , Go, and he goeth; and to another, Come, and he cometh; and to my servant, Do this, and he doeth it . 10 When Jesus heard it , he marveled, and said to them that followed, Verily I say to you, I have not found so great faith, no, not in Israel. 11 And I say to you, that many shall come from the east and the west, and shall sit down with Abraham, and Isaac, and Jacob in the kingdom of heaven. 12 But the children of the kingdom shall be cast out into utter darkness: there shall be weeping and gnashing of teeth. 13 And Jesus said to the centurion, Depart; and as thou hast believed, so be it done to thee. And his servant was healed in the same hour. 14 And when Jesus had come into Peter's house, he saw his wife's mother laid, and sick with a fever. 15 And he touched her hand, and the fever left her: and she arose, and ministered to them. 16 When the evening was come, they brought to him many that were possessed with demons: and he cast out the spirits with his word, and healed all that were sick; 17 That it might be fulfilled which was spoken by Isaiah the prophet, saying, He himself took our infirmities, and bore our sicknesses. 18 Now when Jesus saw great multitudes about him, he gave commandment to depart to the other side. 19 And a certain scribe came, and said to him, Master, I will follow thee whithersoever thou goest. 20 And Jesus saith to him, The foxes have holes, and the birds of the air have nests; but the Son of man hath not where to lay his head. 21 And another of his disciples said to him, Lord, suffer me first to go and bury my father. 22 But Jesus said to him, Follow me; and let the dead bury their dead. 23 And when he had entered into a boat, his disciples followed him. 24 And behold, there arose a great tempest in the sea, insomuch that the boat was covered with the waves: but he was asleep. 25 And his disciples came to him , and awoke him, saying, Lord, save us: we perish. 26 And he saith to them, Why are ye fearful, O ye of little faith? Then he arose, and rebuked the winds and the sea; and there was a great calm. 27 But the men marveled, saying, What manner of man is this, that even the winds and the sea obey him! 28 And when he had come to the other side, into the country of the Gergesenes, there met him two possessed with demons, coming out of the tombs, exceeding fierce, so that no man might pass by that way. 29 And behold, they cried out, saying, What have we to do with thee, Jesus, thou Son of God? art thou come hither to torment us before the time? 30 And there was a good way off from them a herd of many swine, feeding. 31 So the demons besought him, saying, If thou expellest us, suffer us to go away into the herd of swine. 32 And he said to them, Go. And when they had come out, they went into the herd of swine: and behold, the whole herd of swine ran violently down a steep place into the sea, and perished in the waters. 33 And they that kept them, fled, and went into the city, and told every thing; and what had befallen to the possessed with demons. 34 And behold, the whole city came out to meet Jesus: and when they saw him, they besought him that he would depart out of their borders.

9

1 And he entered into a boat, and passed over, and came into his own city. 2 And behold, they brought to him a man sick with the palsy, lying on a bed: and Jesus, seeing their faith, said to the sick of the palsy, Son, be of good cheer; thy sins are forgiven thee. 3 And behold, certain of the scribes said within themselves, This man blasphemeth. 4 And Jesus, knowing their thoughts, said, Why think ye evil in your hearts? 5 For which is easier, to say, Thy sins are forgiven thee; or to say, Arise, and walk? 6 But that ye may know that the Son of man hath power on earth to forgive sins, (then saith he to the sick with the palsy,) Arise, take up thy bed, and go to thy house. 7 And he arose, and departed to his house. 8 But when the multitude saw it , they marveled, and glorified God, who had given such power to men. 9 And as Jesus was passing from thence, he saw a man named Matthew, sitting at the receipt of custom: and he saith to him, Follow me. And he arose, and followed him. 10 And it came to pass, as Jesus sat at table in the house, behold, many publicans and sinners came and sat down with him and his disciples. 11 And when the Pharisees saw it , they said to his disciples, Why eateth your Master with publicans and sinners? 12 But when Jesus heard that , he said to them, They that are in health need not a physician, but they that are sick. 13 But go ye and learn what that meaneth, I will have mercy, and not sacrifice: for I am not come to call the righteous, but sinners to repentance. 14 Then came to him the disciples of John, saying, Why do we and the Pharisees fast often, but thy disciples fast not? 15 And Jesus said to them, Can the children of the bride-chamber mourn, as long as the bridegroom is with them? but the days will come, when the bridegroom shall be taken from them, and then they will fast. 16 No man putteth a piece of new cloth to an old garment: for that which is put in to fill it up, taketh from the garment, and the tear is made worse. 17 Neither do men put new wine into old bottles: else the bottles break, and the wine runneth out, and the bottles perish: but they put new wine into new bottles, and both are preserved. 18 While he was speaking these things to them, behold, there came a certain ruler, and worshiped him, saying, My daughter is even now dead: but come and lay thy hand upon her, and she will live. 19 And Jesus arose, and followed him, and so did his disciples. 20 (And behold, a woman who was diseased with an issue of blood twelve years, came behind him , and touched the hem of his garment. 21 For she said within herself, If I may but touch his garment, I shall be whole. 22 But Jesus turned himself about, and when he saw her, he said, Daughter, be of good comfort; thy faith hath made thee whole. And the woman was made whole from that hour.) 23 And when Jesus came into the ruler's house, and saw the minstrels and the people making a noise, 24 He said to them, Give place: for the maid is not dead, but sleepeth. And they derided him. 25 But when the people were put forth, he went in, and took her by the hand, and the maid arose. 26 And the fame of this went abroad into all that land. 27 And when Jesus departed thence, two blind men followed him, crying, and saying, Thou son of David, have mercy on us. 28 And when he had come into the house, the blind men came to him: and Jesus saith to them, Believe ye that I am able to do this? They said to him, Yes, Lord. 29 Then he touched their eyes, saying, According to your faith, be it to you. 30 And their eyes were opened; and Jesus strictly charged them, saying, See that no man know it . 31 But they, when they had departed, spread abroad his fame in all that country. 32 As thy went out, behold, they brought to him a mute man possessed with a demon. 33 And when the demon was cast out, the mute spoke: and the multitudes marveled, saying, It was never so seen in Israel. 34 But the Pharisees said, He casteth out demons, through the prince of the demons. 35 And Jesus went about all the cities and villages, teaching in their synagogues, and preaching the gospel of the kingdom, and healing every sickness, and every disease among the people. 36 But when he saw the multitudes, he was moved with compassion on them, because they fainted, and were scattered abroad, as sheep having no shepherd. 37 Then saith he to his disciples, The harvest truly is plentiful, but the laborers are few. 38 Pray ye therefore the Lord of the harvest, that he will send forth laborers into his harvest.

10

1 And when he had called to him his twelve disciples, he gave them power against unclean spirits, to cast them out, and to heal all manner of sickness, and all manner of disease. 2 Now the names of the twelve apostles are these; The first, Simon, who is called Peter, and Andrew his brother; James the son of Zebedee, and John his brother; 3 Philip, and Bartholomew; Thomas, and Matthew the publican; James the son of Alpheus, and Lebbeus, whose surname was Thaddeus; 4 Simon the Canaanite, and Judas Iscariot, who also betrayed him. 5 These twelve Jesus sent forth, and commanded them, saying, Go not into the way of the Gentiles, and enter ye not into any city of the Samaritans. 6 But go rather to the lost sheep of the house of Israel. 7 And as ye go, proclaim, saying, The kingdom of heaven is at hand. 8 Heal the sick, cleanse the lepers, raise the dead, cast out demons: freely ye have received, freely give. 9 Provide neither gold, nor silver, nor brass in your purses; 10 Nor bag for your journey, neither two coats, neither shoes, nor a staff: for the workman is worthy of his food. 11 And into whatever city or town ye shall enter, inquire who in it is worthy, and there abide till ye go thence. 12 And when ye come into a house, salute it. 13 And if the house be worthy, let your peace come upon it: but if it be not worthy, let your peace return to you. 14 And whoever shall not receive you, nor hear your words, when ye depart from that house, or city, shake off the dust of your feet. 15 Verily, I say to you, It shall be more tolerable for the land of Sodom and Gomorrah, in the day of judgment, than for that city. 16 Behold, I send you forth as sheep in the midst of wolves: be ye therefore wise as serpents, and harmless as doves. 17 But beware of men: for they will deliver you to the councils, and they will scourge you in their synagogues. 18 And ye will be brought before governors and kings for my sake, for a testimony against them and the Gentiles. 19 But when they deliver you up, be not anxious how or what ye shall speak, for it shall be given to you in that same hour what ye shall speak. 20 For it is not ye that speak, but the Spirit of your Father which speaketh in you. 21 And the brother will deliver up the brother to death, and the father the child: and the children will rise up against their parents, and cause them to be put to death. 22 And ye will be hated by all men for my name's sake: but he that endureth to the end shall be saved. 23 But when they persecute you in this city, flee ye into another: for verily I say to you, Ye shall not have gone over the cities of Israel till the Son of man shall have come. 24 The disciple is not above his teacher, nor the servant above his lord. 25 It is enough for the disciple that he should be as his teacher, and the servant as his lord: if they have called the master of the house Beelzebub, how much more will they call them of his household? 26 Fear them not therefore: for there is nothing covered, that shall not be revealed; and hid, that shall not be known. 27 What I tell you in darkness, that speak ye in light: and what ye hear in the ear, that preach ye upon the house-tops. 28 And fear not them who kill the body, but are not able to kill the soul: but rather fear him who is able to destroy both soul and body in hell. 29 Are not two sparrows sold for a penny? and not one of them shall fall on the ground without your Father. 30 But the very hairs of your head are all numbered. 31 Fear ye not therefore, ye are of more value than many sparrows. 32 Whoever therefore shall confess me before men, him will I also confess before my Father who is in heaven. 33 But whoever shall deny me before men, him will I also deny before my Father who is in heaven. 34 Think not that I am come to send peace on earth: I came not to send peace, but a sword. 35 For I am come to set a man against his father, and the daughter against her mother, and the daughter-in-law against her mother-in-law. 36 And a man's foes will be they of his own household. 37 He that loveth father or mother more than me, is not worthy of me: and he that loveth son or daughter more than me, is not worthy of me. 38 And he that taketh not his cross, and followeth me, is not worthy of me. 39 He that findeth his life shall lose it: and he that loseth his life for my sake, shall find it. 40 He that receiveth you, receiveth me, and he that receiveth me, receiveth him that sent me. 41 He that receiveth a prophet in the name of a prophet, shall receive a prophet's reward; and he that receiveth a righteous man in the name of a righteous man, shall receive a righteous man's reward. 42 And whoever shall give to drink to one of these little ones, a cup of cold water only, in the name of a disciple, verily, I say to you, he shall in no wise lose his reward.

11

1 And it came to pass when Jesus had made an end of commanding his twelve disciples, he departed thence to teach and to preach in their cities. 2 Now when John had heard in the prison the works of Christ, he sent two of his disciples, 3 And said to him, Art thou he that should come, or do we look for another? 4 Jesus answered and said to them, Go and show John again those things which ye hear and see: 5 The blind receive their sight, and the lame walk, the lepers are cleansed, and the deaf hear, the dead are raised, and the poor have the gospel preached to them. 6 And blessed is he to whom I shall not be the cause of his falling into sin. 7 And as they departed, Jesus began to say to the multitudes concerning John, What went ye out into the wilderness to see? a reed shaken with the wind? 8 But what went ye out to see? A man clothed in soft raiment? Behold, they that wear soft clothing are in kings' houses. 9 But what went ye out to see? A prophet? yes, I say to you, and more than a prophet. 10 For this is he concerning whom it is written, Behold, I send my messenger before thy face, who shall prepare thy way before thee. 11 Verily, I say to you, among them that are born of women, there hath not risen a greater than John the Baptist: notwithstanding, he that is least in the kingdom of heaven, is greater than he. 12 And from the days of John the Baptist, until now, the kingdom of heaven suffereth violence, and the violent take it by force. 13 For all the prophets and the law prophesied until John. 14 And if ye will receive it , this is Elijah who was to come. 15 He that hath ears to hear, let him hear. 16 But to what shall I liken this generation? It is like to children sitting in the markets, and calling to their fellows, 17 And saying, We have piped to you, and ye have not danced; We have mourned to you, and ye have not lamented. 18 For John came neither eating nor drinking, and they say, He hath a demon. 19 The Son of man came eating and drinking, and they say, Behold, a man gluttonous, and a wine-bibber, a friend of publicans and sinners. But wisdom is justified by her children. 20 Then he began to rebuke the cities in which most of his mighty works had been done, because they repented not. 21 Woe to thee, Chorazin; woe to thee, Bethsaida: for if the mighty works which have been done in you had been done in Tyre and Sidon, they would have repented long ago in sackcloth and ashes. 22 But I say to you, It shall be more tolerable for Tyre and Sidon at the day of judgment, than for you. 23 And thou, Capernaum, which art exalted to heaven, shalt be brought down to hell: for if the mighty works which have been done in thee, had been done in Sodom, it would have remained until this day. 24 But I say to you, that it shall be more tolerable for the land of Sodom, in the day of judgment, than for thee. 25 At that time Jesus answered and said, I thank thee, O Father, Lord of heaven and earth, because thou hast hid these things from the wise and prudent, and hast revealed them to babes. 26 Even so, Father, for so it seemed good in thy sight. 27 All things are delivered to me by my Father; and no man knoweth the Son, but the Father; neither knoweth any man the Father, save the Son, and he to whomsoever the Son will reveal him . 28 Come to me, all ye that labor, and are heavy laden, and I will give you rest. 29 Take my yoke upon you, and learn from me: for I am meek and lowly in heart; and ye shall find rest to your souls. 30 For my yoke is easy, and my burden is light.

12

1 At that time Jesus went on the sabbath through the grainfields, and his disciples were hungry, and began to pluck the heads of grain, and to eat. 2 But when the Pharisees saw it, they said to him, Behold, thy disciples do that which it is not lawful to do on the sabbath. 3 But he said to them, Have ye not read what David did when he was hungry, and they that were with him; 4 How he entered into the house of God, and ate the show-bread, which it was not lawful for him to eat, neither for them who were with him, but only for the priests? 5 Or have ye not read in the law, that on the sabbath the priests in the temple profane the sabbath, and are blameless? 6 But I say to you, that in this place is one greater than the temple. 7 But if ye had known what this meaneth, I will have mercy, and not sacrifice, ye would not have condemned the guiltless. 8 For the Son of man is Lord even of the sabbath. 9 And when he had departed thence, he went into their synagogue. 10 And behold, there was a man who had his hand withered. And they asked him, saying, Is it lawful to heal on the sabbath? that they might accuse him. 11 And he said to them, What man shall there be among you, that shall have one sheep, and if it shall fall into a pit on the sabbath, will he not lay hold on it, and lift it out? 12 How much then is a man better than a sheep? wherefore it is lawful to do well on the sabbath days. 13 Then saith he to the man, Stretch out thy hand. And he stretched it out; and it was restored to a sound state like the other. 14 Then the Pharisees went out, and held a council against him, how they might destroy him. 15 But when Jesus knew it , he withdrew himself from thence: and great multitudes followed him, and he healed them all. 16 And charged them that they should not make him known: 17 That it might be fulfilled which was spoken by Isaiah the prophet, saying, 18 Behold, my servant, whom I have chosen; my beloved, in whom my soul is well pleased: I will put my spirit upon him, and he shall show judgment to the Gentiles. 19 He shall not contend, nor cry; neither shall any man hear his voice in the streets. 20 A bruised reed shall he not break, and smoking flax shall he not quench, till he shall send forth judgment to victory. 21 And in his name shall the Gentiles trust. 22 Then was brought to him one possessed with a demon, blind and mute; and he healed him, so that the blind and mute both spoke and saw. 23 And all the people were amazed, and said, Is not this the son of David? 24 But when the Pharisees heard it , they said, This man doth not cast out demons, but by Beelzebub the prince of the demons. 25 And Jesus knew their thoughts, and said to them, Every kingdom divided against itself, is brought to desolation; and every city or house divided against itself, shall not stand. 26 And if Satan casteth out Satan, he is divided against himself; how then shall his kingdom stand? 27 And if I by Beelzebub cast out demons, by whom do your children expel them ? therefore they shall be your judges. 28 But if I cast out demons by the Spirit of God, then the kingdom of God is come to you. 29 Or else, how can one enter into a strong man's house, and seize his goods, except he shall first bind the strong man? and then he will plunder his house. 30 He that is not with me, is against me; and he that gathereth not with me, scattereth abroad. 31 Wherefore I say to you, All manner of sin and blasphemy shall be forgiven to men: but the blasphemy against the Holy Spirit shall not be forgiven to men. 32 And whoever speaketh a word against the Son of man, it shall be forgiven him: but whoever speaketh against the Holy Spirit, it shall not be forgiven him, neither in this world, neither in the world to come. 33 Either make the tree good, and its fruit good; or else make the tree corrupt, and its fruit corrupt: for the tree is known by its fruit. 34 O generation of vipers, how can ye, being evil, speak good things? for out of the abundance of the heart, the mouth speaketh. 35 A good man, out of the good treasure of the heart, bringeth forth good things: and an evil man, out of the evil treasure, bringeth forth evil things. 36 But I say to you, That for every idle word that men shall speak, they shall give account in the day of judgment. 37 For by thy words thou shalt be justified, and by thy words thou shalt be condemned. 38 Then certain of the scribes and of the Pharisees answered, saying, Master, we would see a sign from thee. 39 But he answered and said to them, An evil and adulterous generation seeketh for a sign, and there shall no sign be given to it, but the sign of the prophet Jonah. 40 For as Jonah was three days and three nights in the whale's belly: so shall the Son of man be three days and three nights in the heart of the earth. 41 The men of Nineveh shall rise in judgment with this generation, and shall condemn it: because they repented at the preaching of Jonah; and behold, a greater than Jonah is here. 42 The queen of the south shall rise up in the judgment with this generation, and shall condemn it: for she came from the uttermost parts of the earth to hear the wisdom of Solomon; and behold, a greater than Solomon is here. 43 When the unclean spirit is gone out of a man, he walketh through dry places, seeking rest, and he findeth none. 44 Then he saith, I will return into my house from whence I came out; and when he is come, he findeth it empty, swept, and put in order. 45 Then goeth he, and taketh with himself seven other spirits more wicked than himself, and they enter in and dwell there: and the last state of that man is worse than the first. Even so shall it be also to this wicked generation. 46 While he was yet speaking to the people, behold, his mother and his brethren stood without, desiring to speak with him. 47 Then one said to him, Behold, thy mother and thy brethren stand without, desiring to speak with thee. 48 But he answered and said to him that told him, Who is my mother? and who are my brethren? 49 And he stretched forth his hand towards his disciples, and said, Behold my mother and my brethren! 50 For whoever shall do the will of my Father who is in heaven, the same is my brother, and sister, and mother.

13

1 The same day Jesus went out of the house, and sat by the sea side. 2 And great multitudes were gathered to him, so that he went into a boat, and sat down; and the whole multitude stood on the shore. 3 And he spoke many things to them in parables, saying, Behold, a sower went forth to sow; 4 And when he sowed, some seeds fell by the way side, and the fowls came and devoured them: 5 Some fell upon stony places, where they had not much earth: and forthwith they sprung up, because they had no deepness of earth: 6 And when the sun had risen, they were scorched; and because they had not root, they withered. 7 And some fell among thorns; and the thorns sprung up, and choked them: 8 But others fell into good ground, and brought forth fruit, some a hundred-fold, some sixty-fold, some thirty-fold. 9 Who hath ears to hear, let him hear. 10 And the disciples came, and said to him, Why speakest thou to them in parables? 11 He answered and said to them, Because it is given to you to know the mysteries of the kingdom of heaven, but to them it is not given. 12 For whoever hath, to him shall be given, and he shall have more abundance: but whoever hath not, from him shall be taken away even that which he hath. 13 Therefore I speak to them in parables: because they seeing see not; and hearing they hear not, neither do they understand. 14 And in them is fulfilled the prophecy of Isaiah, which saith, By hearing ye shall hear, and shall not understand; and seeing ye shall see, and shall not perceive: 15 For this people's heart is become gross, and their ears are dull of hearing, and their eyes they have closed; lest at any time they should see with their eyes, and hear with their ears, and should understand with their heart, and should be converted, and I should heal them. 16 But blessed are your eyes, for they see: and your ears, for they hear. 17 For verily I say to you, That many prophets and righteous men have desired to see the things which ye see, and have not seen them ; and to hear the things which ye hear, and have not heard them . 18 Hear ye therefore the parable of the sower. 19 When any one heareth the word of the kingdom, and understandeth it not, then cometh the wicked one , and catcheth away that which was sown in his heart. This is he who received seed by the way side. 20 But he that received the seed into stony places, the same is he that heareth the word, and immediately with joy receiveth it; 21 Yet he hath not root in himself, but endureth for a while: for when tribulation or persecution ariseth because of the word, forthwith he is offended. 22 He also that received seed among the thorns is he that heareth the word; and the care of this world, and the deceitfulness of riches choke the word, and he becometh unfruitful. 23 But he that receiveth seed into the good ground is he that heareth the word, and understandeth it ; who also beareth fruit, and bringeth forth, some a hundred fold, some sixty, some thirty. 24 Another parable he proposed to them, saying, The kingdom of heaven is likened to a man who sowed good seed in his field: 25 But while men slept, his enemy came and sowed tares among the wheat, and departed. 26 But when the blade had sprung up, and brought forth fruit, then appeared the tares also. 27 So the servants of the householder came and said to him, Sir, didst thou not sow good seed in thy field? from whence then hath it tares? 28 He said to them, An enemy hath done this. The servants said to him, Wilt thou then that we go and gather them? 29 But he said, No; lest while ye gather the tares, ye root up also the wheat with them. 30 Let both grow together until the harvest: and in the time of harvest I will say to the reapers, Gather ye first the tares, and bind them in bundles to burn them: but gather the wheat into my barn. 31 Another parable he proposed to them, saying, The kingdom of heaven is like a grain of mustard-seed, which a man took, and sowed in his field: 32 Which indeed is the least of all seeds: but when it is grown, it is the greatest among herbs, and becometh a tree, so that the birds of the air come and lodge on its branches. 33 Another parable he spoke to them; The kingdom of heaven is like leaven, which a woman took, and hid in three measures of meal, till the whole was leavened. 34 All these things Jesus spoke to the multitude in parables; and without a parable he spoke not to them: 35 That it might be fulfilled which was spoken by the prophet, saying, I will open my mouth in parables; I will utter things which have been kept secret from the foundation of the world. 36 Then Jesus sent the multitude away, and went into the house: and his disciples came to him, saying, Declare to us the parable of the tares of the field. 37 He answered and said to them, He that soweth the good seed is the Son of man; 38 The field is the world; the good seed are the children of the kingdom; but the tares are the children of the wicked one ; 39 The enemy that sowed them is the devil; the harvest is the end of the world; and the reapers are the angels. 40 As therefore the tares are gathered and burned in the fire; so shall it be in the end of this world. 41 The Son of man shall send forth his angels, and they shall gather out of his kingdom all things that offend, and them who do iniquity; 42 And shall cast them into a furnace of fire: there shall be wailing and gnashing of teeth. 43 Then shall the righteous shine as the sun in the kingdom of their Father. Who hath ears to hear, let him hear. 44 Again, the kingdom of heaven is like treasure hid in a field; which, when a man hath found, he hideth, and for joy thereof goeth and selleth all that he hath, and buyeth that field. 45 Again, the kingdom of heaven is like a merchant seeking goodly pearls: 46 Who, when he had found one pearl of great price, went and sold all that he had, and bought it. 47 Again, the kingdom of heaven is like a net, that was cast into the sea, and gathered of every kind: 48 Which, when it was full, they drew to the shore, and sat down, and gathered the good into vessels, but cast away the bad. 49 So shall it be at the end of the world: the angels shall come forth, and sever the wicked from among the just, 50 And shall cast them into the furnace of fire: there shall be wailing and gnashing of teeth. 51 Jesus saith to them, Have ye understood all these things? They say to him, Yes, Lord. 52 Then said he to them, Therefore every scribe who is instructed to the kingdom of heaven, is like a man that is a householder, who bringeth forth out of his treasure things new and old. 53 And it came to pass, that when Jesus had finished these parables, he departed thence. 54 And when he had come into his own country, he taught them in their synagogue, so that they were astonished, and said, Whence hath this man this wisdom, and these mighty works? 55 Is not this the carpenter's son? is not his mother called Mary? and his brethren, James, and Joses, and Simon, and Judas? 56 And his sisters, are they not all with us? Whence then hath this man all these things? 57 And they were offended in him. But Jesus said to them, A prophet is not without honor, save in his own country, and in his own house. 58 And he did not many mighty works there, because of their unbelief.

14

1 At that time Herod the Tetrarch heard of the fame of Jesus, 2 And said to his servants, This is John the Baptist; he hath risen from the dead; and therefore mighty works do show forth themselves in him. 3 For Herod had laid hold on John, and bound him, and put him in prison for the sake of Herodias, his brother Philip's wife. 4 For John had said to him, It is not lawful for thee to have her. 5 And when he would have put him to death, he feared the multitude, because they counted him as a prophet. 6 But when Herod's birth-day was kept, the daughter of Herodias danced before them, and pleased Herod. 7 Upon which he promised with an oath to give her whatever she would ask. 8 And she, being before instructed by her mother, said, Give me here the head of John the Baptist in a dish. 9 And the king was sorry: nevertheless for the sake of the oath, and of them who sat with him at table, he commanded it to be given her . 10 And he sent, and beheaded John in the prison. 11 And his head was brought in a dish, and given to the damsel: and she brought it to her mother. 12 And his disciples came, and took up the body, and buried it, and went and told Jesus. 13 When Jesus heard of it , he departed thence in a boat, into a desert place apart: and when the people had heard of it , they followed him on foot out of the cities. 14 And Jesus went forth, and saw a great multitude, and was moved with compassion towards them, and he healed their sick. 15 And when it was evening, his disciples came to him, saying, This is a desert place, and the time is now past; send the multitude away, that they may go into the villages, and buy themselves victuals. 16 But Jesus said to them, They need not depart; give ye them to eat. 17 And they say to him, We have here but five loaves, and two fish. 18 He said, Bring them hither to me. 19 And he commanded the multitude to sit down on the grass, and took the five loaves, and the two fish, and looking up to heaven, he blessed, and broke, and gave the loaves to his disciples, and the disciples to the multitude. 20 And they all ate, and were satisfied: and they took up of the fragments that remained twelve baskets full. 21 And they that had eaten were about five thousand men, besides women and children. 22 And immediately Jesus constrained his disciples to get into a boat, and to go before him to the other side, while he sent the multitudes away. 23 And when he had sent the multitudes away, he ascended a mountain apart to pray: and when the evening was come, he was there alone. 24 But the boat was now in the midst of the sea, tossed with waves: for the wind was contrary. 25 And in the fourth watch of the night Jesus went to them, walking on the sea. 26 And when the disciples saw him walking on the sea, they were troubled, saying, It is a spirit; and they cried out for fear. 27 But immediately Jesus spoke to them, saying, Be of good cheer; it is I; be not afraid. 28 And Peter answered him and said, Lord, if it is thou, bid me come to thee on the water. 29 And he said, Come. And when Peter had come down out of the boat, he walked on the water, to go to Jesus. 30 But when he saw the wind boisterous, he was afraid; and beginning to sink, he cried, saying, Lord, save me. 31 And immediately Jesus stretched forth his hand, and caught him, and said to him, O thou of little faith, Why didst thou doubt? 32 And when they had come into the boat, the wind ceased. 33 Then they that were in the boat came and worshiped him, saying, In truth thou art the son of God. 34 And when they had gone over, they came into the land of Gennesaret. 35 And when the men of that place had knowledge of him, they sent out into all the surrounding country, and brought to him all that were diseased; 36 And besought him that they might only touch the hem of his garment: and as many as touched were restored to health.

15

1 Then came to Jesus scribes and Pharisees, who were of Jerusalem, saying, 2 Why do thy disciples transgress the tradition of the elders? for they wash not their hands when they eat bread. 3 But he answered and said to them, Why do ye also transgress the commandment of God by your tradition? 4 For God commanded, saying, Honor thy father and mother: and, He that curseth father or mother, let him die the death. 5 But ye say, Whoever shall say to his father or his mother, It is a gift, by whatever thou mightest be profited by me; 6 And honor not his father or his mother, he shall be free . Thus have ye made the commandment of God of no effect by your tradition. 7 Ye hypocrites, well did Isaiah prophesy of you, saying, 8 This people draw nigh to me with their mouth, and honor me with their lips; but their heart is far from me. 9 But in vain they do worship me, teaching for doctrines the commandments of men. 10 And he called the multitude, and said to them, Hear, and understand: 11 Not that which goeth into the mouth defileth a man; but that which cometh out of the mouth, this defileth a man. 12 Then came his disciples, and said to him, Knowest thou that the Pharisees were offended after they heard this saying? 13 But he answered and said, Every plant, which my heavenly Father hath not planted, shall be extirpated. 14 Let them alone: they are blind leaders of the blind. And if the blind leadeth the blind, both will fall into the ditch. 15 Then answered Peter and said to him, Declare to us this parable. 16 And Jesus said, Are ye also yet without understanding? 17 Do ye not yet understand, that whatever entereth in at the mouth goeth into the belly, and is cast out into the draught? 18 But those things which proceed out of the mouth come forth from the heart; and they defile the man. 19 For out of the heart proceed evil thoughts, murders, adulteries, fornications, thefts, false witness, blasphemies: 20 These are the things which defile a man: but to eat with unwashen hands defileth not a man. 21 Then Jesus went thence, and departed into the territories of Tyre and Sidon. 22 And behold, a woman of Canaan came out of the same territories, and cried to him, saying, Have mercy on me, O Lord, thou son of David; my daughter is grievously afflicted with a demon. 23 But he answered her not a word. And his disciples came and besought him, saying, Send her away; for she crieth after us. 24 But he answered and said, I am not sent but to the lost sheep of the house of Israel. 25 Then came she and worshiped him, saying, Lord, help me. 26 But he answered and said, It is not meet to take the children's bread, and to cast it to dogs. 27 And she said, Truth, Lord: yet the dogs eat of the crums which fall from their master's table. 28 Then Jesus answered and said to her, O woman, great is thy faith: be it to thee even as thou wilt. And her daughter was healed from that very hour. 29 And Jesus departed from thence, and came nigh to the sea of Galilee; and ascended a mountain, and sat down there. 30 And great multitudes came to him, having with them those that were lame, blind, mute, maimed, and many others, and cast them down at Jesus' feet; and he healed them: 31 So that the multitude wondered, when they saw the mute to speak, the maimed to be whole, the lame to walk, and the blind to see: and they glorified the God of Israel. 32 Then Jesus called his disciples to him , and said, I have compassion on the multitude, because they continue with me now three days, and have nothing to eat: and I will not send them away fasting, lest they faint in the way. 33 And his disciples say to him, Whence should we have so much bread in the wilderness, as to satisfy so great a multitude? 34 And Jesus saith to them, How many loaves have ye? And they said, Seven, and a few little fish. 35 And he commanded the multitude to sit on the ground. 36 And he took the seven loaves and the fish, and gave thanks, and broke them , and gave to his disciples, and the disciples to the multitude. 37 And they all ate and were filled: and they took up of the fragments that were left seven baskets full. 38 And they that had eaten were four thousand men, besides women and children. 39 And he sent away the multitude, and took a boat, and came into the borders of Magdala.

16

1 The Pharisees also and the Sadducees came, and, tempting, desired him that he would show them a sign from heaven. 2 He answered and said to them, When it is evening, ye say, It will be fair weather: for the sky is red. 3 And in the morning, It will be foul weather to-day: for the sky is red and lowering. O ye hypocrites, ye can discern the face of the sky; but can ye not discern the signs of the times? 4 A wicked and adulterous generation seeketh for a sign; and there shall no sign been to it, but the sign of the prophet Jonah. And he left them, and departed. 5 And when his disciples had come to the other side, they had forgotten to take bread. 6 Then Jesus said to them, Take heed and beware of the leaven of the Pharisees and of the Sadducees. 7 And they reasoned among themselves, saying, It is because we have taken no bread. 8 Which when Jesus perceived, he said to them, O ye of little faith, why reason ye among yourselves, because ye have brought no bread? 9 Do ye not yet understand, neither remember the five loaves of the five thousand, and how many baskets ye took up? 10 Neither the seven loaves of the four thousand, and how many baskets ye took up? 11 How is it that ye do not understand that I spoke not to you concerning bread, that ye should beware of the leaven of the Pharisees and of the Sadducees? 12 Then they understood that he did not caution them against the leaven of bread, but against the doctrine of the Pharisees and of the Sadducees. 13 When Jesus came into the borders of Cesarea Phillippi, he asked his disciples, saying, Who do men say that I the Son of man am? 14 And they said, Some say that thou art John the Baptist: some Elijah; and others, Jeremiah, or one of the prophets. 15 He saith to them, But who say ye that I am? 16 And Simon Peter answered and said, Thou art the Christ, the Son of the living God. 17 And Jesus answered and said to him, Blessed art thou, Simon-Barjona: for flesh and blood hath not revealed it to thee, but my Father who is in heaven. 18 And I say also to thee, that thou art Peter, and upon this rock I will build my church: and the gates of hell shall not prevail against it. 19 And I will give to thee the keys of the kingdom of heaven: and whatever thou shalt bind on earth, shall be bound in heaven; and whatever thou shalt loose on earth, shall be loosed in heaven. 20 Then he charged his disciples that they should tell no man that he was Jesus the Christ. 21 From that time forth Jesus began to show to his disciples, that he must go to Jerusalem, and suffer many things from the elders and chief priests, and scribes, and be killed, and be raised again the third day. 22 Then Peter took him, and began to rebuke him, saying, Be it far from thee, Lord: this shall not be to thee. 23 But he turned, and said to Peter, Get thee behind me, Satan; thou art an offense to me: for thou savorest not the things that are of God, but those that are of men. 24 Then said Jesus to his disciples, If any man will come after me, let him deny himself, and take up his cross, and follow me. 25 For whoever will save his life, shall lose it: and whoever will lose his life for my sake, shall find it. 26 For what is a man profited, if he shall gain the whole world, and lose his own soul? or what shall a man give in exchange for his soul? 27 For the Son of man will come in the glory of his Father, with his angels; and then he will reward every man according to his works. 28 Verily I say to you, There are some standing here, who shall not taste death, till they shall see the Son of man coming in his kingdom.

17

1 And after six days, Jesus taketh Peter, James, and John his brother, and bringeth them upon a high mountain apart. 2 And he was transfigured before them: and his face shone as the sun, and his raiment was white as the light. 3 And behold, there appeared to them Moses and Elijah talking with him. 4 Then answered Peter, and said to Jesus, Lord, it is good for us to be here: if thou wilt, let us make here three tabernacles; one for thee, and one for Moses, and one for Elijah. 5 While he was yet speaking, behold, a bright cloud overshadowed them: and behold, a voice out of the cloud, which said, This is my beloved Son, in whom I am well pleased: hear ye him. 6 And when the disciples heard it , they fell on their face, and were in great fear. 7 And Jesus came and touched them, and said, Arise, and be not afraid. 8 And when they had lifted up their eyes, they saw no man, save Jesus only. 9 And as they were descending the mountain, Jesus charged them, saying, Tell the vision to no man, until the Son of man be raised again from the dead. 10 And his disciples asked him, saying, Why then say the scribes, that Elijah must first come? 11 And Jesus answered and said to them, Elijah truly will first come, and restore all things: 12 But I say to you, that Elijah is come already, and they knew him not, but have done to him whatever they pleased: likewise will also the Son of man suffer by them. 13 Then the disciples understood that he spoke to them concerning John the Baptist. 14 And when they had come to the multitude, there came to him a certain man kneeling down to him, and saying, 15 Lord, have mercy on my son; for he is lunatic, and grievously distressed; for often he falleth into the fire, and often into the water. 16 And I brought him to thy disciples, and they could not cure him. 17 Then Jesus answered and said, O faithless and perverse generation, how long shall I be with you? how long shall I suffer you? bring him hither to me. 18 And Jesus rebuked the demon, and he departed out of him: and the child was cured from that very hour. 19 Then came the disciples to Jesus apart, and said, Why could not we cast him out? 20 And Jesus said to them, Because of your unbelief: for verily I say to you, If ye have faith as a grain of mustard-seed, ye shall say to this mountain, Remove hence to yonder place, and it shall remove; and nothing shall be impossible to you. 21 However, this kind goeth not out, but by prayer and fasting. 22 And while they abode in Galilee, Jesus said to them, The Son of man will be betrayed into the hands of men: 23 And they will kill him, and the third day he will be raised again: And they were exceedingly grieved. 24 And when they had come to Capernaum, they that received tribute -money , came to Peter, and said, Doth not your Master pay tribute? 25 He saith, Yes. And when he had come into the house, Jesus anticipated him, saying, What thinkest thou, Simon? from whom do the kings of the earth take custom or tribute? from their own children, or from strangers? 26 Peter saith to him, From strangers. Jesus saith to him, Then are the children free. 27 Notwithstanding, lest we should offend them, go thou to the sea, and cast a hook, and take the fish that first cometh up: and when thou hast opened his mouth, thou shalt find a piece of money: take that, and give to them for me and thee.

18

1 At the same time came the disciples to Jesus, saying, Who is the greatest in the kingdom of heaven? 2 And Jesus called a little child to him, and set him in the midst of them, 3 And said, Verily I say to you, Except ye be converted, and become as little children, ye shall not enter into the kingdom of heaven. 4 Whoever therefore shall humble himself as this little child, the same is greatest in the kingdom of heaven. 5 And whoever shall receive one such little child in my name, receiveth me. 6 But whoever shall cause one of these little ones who believe in me, to sin, it were better for him that a millstone were hanged about his neck, and that he were drowned in the depth of the sea. 7 Woe to the world because of offenses! for it must needs be that offenses come; but woe to that man by whom the offense cometh! 8 Wherefore, if thy hand or thy foot causeth thee to sin, cut them off, and cast them from thee: it is better for thee to enter into life halt or maimed, rather than having two hands or two feet, to be cast into everlasting fire. 9 And if thy eye causeth thee to sin, pluck it out, and cast it from thee: it is better for thee to enter into life with one eye, rather than having two eyes, to be cast into hell-fire. 10 Take heed that ye despise not one of these little ones: for I say to you, that in heaven their angels do always behold the face of my Father who is in heaven. 11 For the Son of man is come to save that which was lost. 12 How think ye? if a man hath a hundred sheep, and one of them is gone astray, doth he not leave the ninety and nine, and go to the mountains, and seek that which is gone astray? 13 And if he findeth it, verily I say to you, he rejoiceth more over that sheep , than over the ninety and nine which went not astray. 14 Even so it is not the will of your Father who is in heaven, that one of these little ones should perish. 15 Moreover, if thy brother shall trespass against thee, go and tell him his fault between thee and him alone: if he shall hear thee, thou hast gained thy brother. 16 But if he will not hear thee , then take with thee one or two more, that in the mouth of two or three witnesses every word may be established. 17 And if he shall neglect to hear them, tell it to the church: but if he shall neglect to hear the church, let him be to thee as a heathen and a publican. 18 Verily I say to you, Whatever ye shall bind on earth, shall be bound in heaven: and whatever ye shall loose on earth, shall be loosed in heaven. 19 Again I say to you, That if two of you shall agree on earth, concerning any thing that they shall ask, it shall be done for them by my Father who is in heaven. 20 For where two or three are assembled in my name, there am I in the midst of them. 21 Then came Peter to him, and said, Lord, how often shall my brother sin against me, and I forgive him? till seven times? 22 Jesus saith to him, I say not to thee, Until seven times: but, Until seventy times seven. 23 Therefore is the kingdom of heaven likened to a certain king who would take account of his servants. 24 And when he had begun to reckon, one was brought to him who owed him ten thousand talents. 25 But as he had not ability to pay, his lord commanded him to be sold, and his wife and children, and all that he had, and payment to be made. 26 The servant therefore fell down, and worshiped him, saying, Lord, have patience with me, and I will pay thee all. 27 Then the lord of that servant was moved with compassion, and loosed him, and forgave him the debt. 28 But the same servant went out, and found one of his fellow-servants, who owed him a hundred pence: and he laid hands on him, and took him by the throat, saying, Pay me what thou owest. 29 And his fellow-servant fell down at his feet, and besought him, saying, Have patience with me, and I will pay thee all. 30 And he would not: but went and cast him into prison, till he should pay the debt. 31 So when his fellow-servants saw what was done, they were very sorry, and came and told to their lord all that was done. 32 Then his lord, having called him, said to him, O thou wicked servant, I forgave thee all that debt, because thou desiredst me: 33 Shouldst thou not also have had compassion on thy fellow-servant, even as I had pity on thee? 34 And his lord was wroth, and delivered him to the tormentors, till he should pay all that was due to him. 35 So likewise shall my heavenly Father do to you, if ye from your hearts forgive not every one his brother their trespasses.

19

1 And it came to pass, that when Jesus had finished these sayings, he departed from Galilee, and came into the borders of Judea, beyond Jordan: 2 And great multitudes followed him, and he healed them there. 3 The Pharisees also came to him, tempting him, and saying to him, Is it lawful for a man to put away his wife for every cause? 4 And he answered and said to them, Have ye not read, that he who made them , at the beginning made them male and female, 5 And said, For this cause shall a man leave father and mother, and shall cleave to his wife: and they two shall be one flesh? 6 Wherefore they are no more two, but one flesh. Therefore what God hath joined together, let not man put asunder. 7 They say to him, Why did Moses then command to give a writing of divorcement, and to put her away? 8 He saith to them, Moses, because of the hardness of your hearts, suffered you to put away your wives: but from the beginning it was not so. 9 And I say to you, Whoever shall put away his wife, except for lewdness, and shall marry another, committeth adultery: and whoever marrieth her who is put away, committeth adultery. 10 His disciples say to him, If the case of the man is so with his wife, it is not good to marry. 11 But he said to them, All men cannot receive this saying, save they to whom it is given. 12 For there are some eunuchs, who were so born from their mothers womb: and there are some eunuchs, who were made eunuchs by men: and there are eunuchs, who have made themselves eunuchs for the kingdom of heaven's sake. He that is able to receive it , let him receive it . 13 Then were brought to him little children, that he should put his hands on them, and pray: and the disciples rebuked them. 14 But Jesus said, Suffer little children, and forbid them not to come to me: for of such is the kingdom of heaven. 15 And he laid his hands on them, and departed thence. 16 And behold, one came and said to him, Good Master, what good thing shall I do that I may have eternal life? 17 And he said to him, Why callest thou me good? there is none good but one, that is , God: but if thou wilt enter into life, keep the commandments. 18 He saith to him, Which? Jesus said, Thou shalt do no murder, Thou shalt not commit adultery, Thou shalt not steal, Thou shalt not bear false witness, 19 Honor thy father and thy mother: and, Thou shalt love thy neighbor as thyself. 20 The young man saith to him, All these things have I kept from my youth: what lack I yet? 21 Jesus said to him, If thou wilt be perfect, go and sell what thou hast, and give to the poor, and thou shalt have treasure in heaven: and come and follow me. 22 But when the young man heard that saying, he went away sorrowful: for he had great possessions. 23 Then said Jesus to his disciples, Verily I say to you, that a rich man shall with difficulty enter into the kingdom of heaven. 24 And again I say to you, It is easier for a camel to go through the eye of a needle, than for a rich man to enter into the kingdom of God. 25 When his disciples heard it , they were exceedingly amazed, saying, Who then can be saved? 26 But Jesus beheld them , and said to them, With men this is impossible, but with God all things are possible. 27 Then answered Peter, and said to him, Behold, we have forsaken all, and followed thee? what shall we have therefore? 28 And Jesus said to them, Verily I say to you, that ye who have followed me in the regeneration, when the Son of man shall sit on the throne of his glory, ye also shall sit upon twelve thrones, judging the twelve tribes of Israel. 29 And every one that hath forsaken houses, or brethren, or sisters, or father, or mother, or wife, or children, or lands for my name's sake, shall receive a hundred-fold, and shall inherit everlasting life. 30 But many that are first shall be last, and the last shall be first.

20

1 For the kingdom of heaven is like to a man that is a householder, who went out early in the morning to hire laborers into his vineyard. 2 And when he had agreed with the laborers for a penny a day, he sent them into his vineyard. 3 And he went out about the third hour, and saw others standing idle in the market-place, 4 And said to them, Go ye also into the vineyard; and whatever is right, I will give you. And they departed. 5 Again he went out about the sixth and ninth hour, and did likewise. 6 And about the eleventh hour he went out, and found others standing idle, and saith to them, Why stand ye here all the day idle? 7 They say to him, Because no man hath hired us. He saith to them, Go ye also into the vineyard; and whatever is right, that shall ye receive. 8 So when evening was come, the lord of the vineyard saith to his steward, Call the laborers, and give them their hire, beginning from the last to the first. 9 And when they came that were hired about the eleventh hour, they received every man a penny. 10 But when the first came, they supposed that they should receive more; and they likewise received every man a penny. 11 And when they had received it , they murmured against the master of the house. 12 Saying, These last have wrought but one hour, and thou hast made them equal to us, who have borne the burden and heat of the day. 13 But he answered one of them, and said, Friend, I do thee no wrong: didst thou not agree with me for a penny? 14 Take that which is thine, and depart: I will give to this last, even as to thee. 15 Is it not lawful for me to do what I will with my own? is thy eye evil because I am good? 16 So the last shall be first, and the first last: for many are called, but few chosen. 17 And Jesus going up to Jerusalem, took the twelve disciples apart in the way, and said to them, 18 Behold, we go up to Jerusalem; and the Son of man will be betrayed to the chief priests, and to the scribes, and they will condemn him to death, 19 And will deliver him to the Gentiles to mock, and to scourge, and to crucify him : and the third day he will rise again. 20 Then came to him the mother of Zebedee's children, with her sons, worshiping him , and desiring a certain thing of him. 21 And he said to her, What wilt thou: She saith to him, Grant that these my two sons may sit, the one on thy right hand, and the other on the left in thy kingdom. 22 But Jesus answered and said, Ye know not what ye ask. Are ye able to drink of the cup that I shall drink of, and to be baptized with the baptism that I am baptized with? They say to him, We are able. 23 And he saith to them, Ye shall drink indeed of my cup, and be baptized with the baptism that I am baptized with: but to sit on my right hand, and on my left, is not mine to give, but it shall be given to them for whom it is prepared by my Father. 24 And when the ten heard it , they were moved with indignation against the two brethren. 25 But Jesus called them to him , and said, Ye know that the princes of the Gentiles exercise dominion over them, and they that are great exercise authority upon them. 26 But it shall not be so among you: but whoever will be great among you, let him be your minister; 27 And whoever will be chief among you, let him be your servant: 28 Even as the Son of man came not to be ministered to, but to minister, and to give his life a ransom for many. 29 And as they departed from Jericho, a great multitude followed him. 30 And behold, two blind men sitting by the way-side, when they heard that Jesus passed by, cried out, saying, Have mercy on us, O Lord, thou son of David. 31 And the multitude rebuked them, that they should hold their peace: but they cried the more, saying, Have mercy on us, O Lord, thou son of David. 32 And Jesus stood still, and called them, and said, What will ye that I shall do to you? 33 They say to him, Lord, that our eyes may be opened. 34 So Jesus had compassion on them , and touched their eyes: and immediately their eyes received sight, and they followed him.

21

1 And when they drew nigh to Jerusalem, and had come to Bethphage, to the mount of Olives, then Jesus sent two disciples, 2 Saying to them, Go into the village over against you, and immediately ye shall find an ass tied, and a colt with her, loose them , and bring them to me. 3 And if any man shall say anything to you, ye shall say, The Lord hath need of them; and immediately he will send them. 4 All this was done, that it might be fulfilled which was spoken by the prophet, saying, 5 Tell ye the daughter of Sion, Behold, thy King cometh to thee, meek, and sitting upon an ass, and a colt the foal of an ass. 6 And the disciples went, and did as Jesus commanded them, 7 And brought the ass and the colt, and put on them their clothes, and they set him thereon. 8 And a very great multitude spread their garments in the way; others cut down branches from the trees, and strewed them in the way. 9 And the multitudes that went before, and that followed, cried, saying, Hosanna to the son of David: blessed is he that cometh in the name of the Lord: Hosanna in the highest. 10 And when he had come into Jerusalem, all the city was moved, saying, Who is this? 11 And the multitude said, This is Jesus the prophet of Nazareth of Galilee. 12 And Jesus went into the temple of God, and cast out all them that sold and bought in the temple, and overthrew the tables of the money-changers, and the seats of them that sold doves. 13 And said to them, It is written, My house shall be called the house of prayer, but ye have made it a den of thieves. 14 And the blind and the lame came to him in the temple; and he healed them. 15 And when the chief priests and scribes saw the wonderful things that he did, and the children crying in the temple, and saying, Hosanna to the son of David; they were greatly displeased, 16 And said to him, Hearest thou what these say? And Jesus saith to them, Yes: have ye never read, Out of the mouth of babes and sucklings thou hast perfected praise? 17 And he left them, and went out of the city into Bethany, and he lodged there. 18 Now in the morning as he was returning into the city, he was hungry. 19 And when he saw a fig-tree in the way, he came to it, and found nothing on it, but leaves only, and said to it, Let no fruit grow on thee henceforth for ever. And immediately the fig-tree withered. 20 And when the disciples saw it , they marveled, saying, How soon is the fig-tree withered! 21 Jesus answered and said to them, Verily I say to you, If ye have faith, and doubt not, ye shall not only do this which is done to the fig-tree, but also, if ye shall say to this mountain, Be thou removed, and be thou cast into the sea; it shall be done. 22 And all things whatever ye shall ask in prayer, believing, ye shall receive. 23 And when he had come into the temple, the chief priests and the elders of the people came to him as he was teaching, and said, By what authority doest thou these things; and who gave thee this authority? 24 And Jesus answered and said to them, I also will ask you one thing, which if ye tell me, I also will tell you by what authority I do these things. 25 The baptism of John, whence was it? from heaven, or from men? And they reasoned with themselves, saying, if we shall say, From heaven; he will say to us, Why then did ye not believe him? 26 But if we shall say, From men; we fear the people: for all hold John as a prophet. 27 And they answered Jesus, and said, We cannot tell. And he said to them, Neither do I tell you by what authority I do these things. 28 But what think ye? A certain man had two sons; and he came to the first, and said, Son, go, work to-day in my vineyard. 29 He answered and said, I will not; but afterward he repented, and went. 30 And he came to the second, and said likewise. And he answered and said, I go , sir: and went not. 31 Which of the two did the will of his father? They say to him, The first. Jesus saith to them, Verily I say to you, that the publicans and the harlots go into the kingdom of God before you. 32 For John came to you in the way of righteousness, and ye believed him not: but the publicans and the harlots believed him: and ye, when ye had seen it , repented not afterward, that ye might believe him. 33 Hear another parable; There was a certain householder, who planted a vineyard, and hedged it around, and dug a wine-press in it, and built a tower, and let it out to husbandmen, and went into a remote country: 34 And when the time of the fruit drew near, he sent his servants to the husbandmen, that they might receive the fruits of it. 35 And the husbandmen took his servants, and beat one, and killed another, and stoned another. 36 Again he sent other servants more than the first: and they did to them in like manner. 37 But last of all he sent to them his son, saying, They will reverence my son. 38 But when the husbandmen saw the son, they said among themselves, This is the heir; come, let us kill him, and let us seize on his inheritance. 39 And they caught him, and cast him out of the vineyard, and slew him . 40 When therefore the Lord of the vineyard cometh, what will he do to those husbandmen? 41 They say to him, He will miserably destroy those wicked men, and will let out his vineyard to other husbandmen, who will render him the fruits in their seasons. 42 Jesus saith to them, Did ye never read in the scriptures, The stone which the builders rejected, the same is become the head of the corner: this is the Lord's doing, and it is marvelous in our eyes? 43 Therefore I say to you, The kingdom of God shall be taken from you, and given to a nation bringing forth the fruits of it. 44 And whoever shall fall on this stone, shall be broken: but on whomsoever it shall fall, it will grind him to powder. 45 And when the chief priests and Pharisees had heard his parables, they perceived that he spoke of them. 46 But when they sought to lay hands on him, they feared the multitude, because they took him for a prophet.

22

1 And Jesus answered, and spoke to them again by parables, and said, 2 The kingdom of heaven is like to a certain king, who made a marriage for his son, 3 And sent his servants to call them that were invited to the wedding: and they would not come. 4 Again, he sent other servants, saying, Tell them who are invited, Behold, I have prepared my dinner: my oxen and my fatlings are killed, and all things are ready: come to the marriage. 5 But they made light of it , and went, one to his farm, another to his merchandise. 6 And the remnant took his servants, and treated them spitefully, and slew them . 7 But when the king heard of it , he was wroth: and he sent his armies, and destroyed those murderers, and burned up their city. 8 Then he saith to his servants, The wedding is ready, but they who were invited were not worthy. 9 Go ye therefore into the highways, and as many as ye shall find, invite to the marriage. 10 So those servants went out into the highways, and collected all as many as they found, both bad and good: and the wedding was furnished with guests. 11 And when the king came in to see the guests, he saw there a man who had not a wedding-garment: 12 And he saith to him, Friend, how camest thou in hither, not having a wedding-garment? And he was speechless. 13 Then said the king to the servants, Bind him hand and foot, and take him away, and cast him into utter darkness: there shall be weeping and gnashing of teeth. 14 For many are called, but few are chosen. 15 Then went the Pharisees, and took counsel how they might entangle him in his talk. 16 And they sent out to him their disciples, with the Herodians, saying, Master, we know that thou art true, and teachest the way of God in truth, neither carest thou for any man : for thou regardest not the person of men. 17 Tell us therefore, What thinkest thou? Is it lawful to give tribute to Cesar, or not? 18 But Jesus perceived their wickedness, and said, Why tempt ye me, ye hypocrites? 19 Show me the tribute-money. And they brought to him a penny. 20 And he saith to them, Whose is this image, and superscription? 21 They say to him, Cesar's. Then saith he to them, Render therefore to Cesar, the things which are Cesar's; and to God, the things that are God's. 22 When they had heard these words , they marveled, and left him, and departed. 23 The same day came to him the Sadducees, who say that there is no resurrection, and asked him, 24 Saying, Master, Moses said, If a man shall die, having no children, his brother shall marry his wife, and raise up seed to his brother. 25 Now there were with us seven brothers: and the first, when he had married a wife, deceased; and having no issue, left his wife to his brother. 26 Likewise the second also, and the third, to the seventh. 27 And last of all the woman died also. 28 Therefore in the resurrection, whose wife shall she be of the seven? for they all had her. 29 Jesus answered and said to them, Ye do err, not knowing the scriptures, nor the power of God. 30 For in the resurrection they neither marry, nor are given in marriage, but are as the angels of God in heaven. 31 But as concerning the resurrection of the dead, have ye not read that which was spoken to you by God, saying, 32 I am the God of Abraham, and the God of Isaac, and the God of Jacob? God is not the God of the dead, but of the living. 33 And when the multitude heard this , they were astonished at his doctrine. 34 But when the Pharisees had heard that he had put the Sadducees to silence, they were assembled about him. 35 Then one of them who was a lawyer, asked him a question , tempting him, and saying, 36 Master, which is the great commandment in the law? 37 Jesus said to him, Thou shalt love the Lord thy God with all thy heart, and with all thy soul, and with all thy mind. 38 This is the first and great commandment. 39 And the second is like it, Thou shalt love thy neighbor as thyself. 40 On these two commandments hang all the law and the prophets. 41 While the Pharisees were assembled, Jesus asked them, 42 Saying, What think ye of Christ? whose son is he? They say to him, The son of David. 43 He saith to them, How then doth David in spirit call him Lord, saying, 44 The LORD said to my Lord, Sit thou on my right hand, till I make thy enemies thy footstool? 45 If David then calleth him Lord, how is he his son? 46 And no man was able to answer him a word, nor from that day on did anyone dare question him anymore.

23

1 Then Jesus spoke to the multitude, and to his disciples, 2 Saying, The scribes and the Pharisees sit in Moses's seat. 3 All therefore, whatever they bid you observe, that observe and do: but do not ye according to their works: for they say, and do not. 4 For they bind heavy burdens, and grievous to be borne, and lay them on men's shoulders; but they themselves will not move them with one of their fingers. 5 But all their works they do to be seen by men: they make broad their phylacteries, and enlarge the borders of their garments, 6 And love the uppermost rooms at feasts, and the chief seats in the synagogues, 7 And greetings in the markets, and to be called by men, Rabbi, Rabbi. 8 But be not ye called Rabbi: for one is your Master, even Christ; and all ye are brethren. 9 And call no man your father upon the earth: for one is your Father who is in heaven. 10 Neither be ye called masters: for one is your master, even Christ. 11 But he that is greatest among you, shall be your servant. 12 And whoever shall exalt himself, shall be abased; and he that shall humble himself, shall be exalted. 13 But woe to you, scribes and Pharisees! hypocrites! for ye shut up the kingdom of heaven against men: for ye neither go in yourselves , neither suffer ye them that are entering, to go in. 14 Woe to you, scribes and Pharisees, hypocrites! for ye devour widows' houses, and for a pretense make long prayer: therefore ye shall receive the greater damnation. 15 Woe to you, scribes and Pharisees, hypocrites! for ye compass sea and land to make one proselyte, and when he is made, ye make him two-fold more the child of hell than yourselves. 16 Woe to you, ye blind guides, who say, Whoever shall swear by the temple, it is nothing; but whoever shall swear by the gold of the temple, he is a debtor. 17 Ye fools, and blind: for which is greater, the gold, or the temple that sanctifieth the gold? 18 And whoever shall swear by the altar, it is nothing; but whoever sweareth by the gift that is upon it, he is guilty. 19 Ye fools, and blind: for which is greater, the gift, or the altar that sanctifieth the gift? 20 Whoever therefore shall swear by the altar, sweareth by it, and by all things upon it. 21 And whoever shall swear by the temple, sweareth by it, and by him that dwelleth in it. 22 And he that shall swear by heaven, sweareth by the throne of God, and by him that sitteth upon it. 23 Woe to you, scribes and Pharisees, hypocrites! for ye pay tithe of mint, and anise, and cummin, and have omitted the weightier matters of the law, judgment, mercy, and faith: these ye ought to have done, and not to leave the others undone. 24 Ye blind guides, who strain out a gnat, and swallow a camel. 25 Woe to you, scribes and Pharisees, hypocrites! for ye make clean the outside of the cup and of the platter, but within they are full of extortion and excess. 26 Thou blind Pharisee, cleanse first that which is within the cup and platter, that the outside of them may be clean also. 27 Woe to you, scribes and Pharisees, hypocrites! for ye are like whitened sepulchers, which indeed appear beautiful outward, but are within full of dead men's bones, and of all uncleanness. 28 Thus ye also outwardly appear righteous to men, but within ye are full of hypocrisy and iniquity. 29 Woe to you, scribes and Pharisees, hypocrites! because ye build the tombs of the prophets, and adorn the sepulchers of the righteous, 30 And say, If we had been in the days of our fathers, we would not have been partakers with them in the blood of the prophets. 31 Wherefore ye are witnesses to yourselves, that ye are the children of them who killed the prophets. 32 Fill ye up then the measure of your fathers. 33 Ye serpents, ye generation of vipers, how can ye escape the damnation of hell? 34 Wherefore behold, I send to you prophets, and wise men, and scribes; and some of them ye will kill and crucify, and some of them ye will scourge in your synagogues, and persecute them from city to city: 35 That upon you may come all the righteous blood shed upon the earth, from the blood of righteous Abel, to the blood of Zacharias son of Barachias, whom ye slew between the temple and the altar. 36 Verily I say to you, all these things shall come upon this generation. 37 O Jerusalem, Jerusalem, thou that killest the prophets, and stonest them who are sent to thee, how often would I have gathered thy children, even as a hen gathereth her chickens under her wings, and ye would not! 38 Behold, your house is left to you desolate. 39 For I say to you, Ye shall not see me henceforth, till ye shall say, Blessed is he that cometh in the name of the Lord.

24

1 And Jesus went out, and departed from the temple: and his disciples came to him to show him the buildings of the temple. 2 And Jesus said to them, See ye not all these things? verily I say to you, There shall not be left here one stone upon another, that shall not be thrown down. 3 And as he sat upon the mount of Olives, the disciples came to him privately, saying, Tell us, when will these things be? and what will be the sign of thy coming, and of the end of the world? 4 And Jesus answered and said to them, Take heed that no man deceive you. 5 For many will come in my name, saying, I am Christ; and will deceive many. 6 And ye will hear of wars, and rumors of wars: see that ye be not troubled: for all these things must come to pass, but the end is not yet. 7 For nation will rise against nation, and kingdom against kingdom: and there will be famines, and pestilences, and earthquakes in divers places. 8 All these are the beginning of sorrows. 9 Then will they deliver you up to be afflicted, and will kill you: and ye will be hated by all nations for my name's sake. 10 And then will many be offended, and will betray one another, and will hate one another. 11 And many false prophets will rise, and will deceive many. 12 And because iniquity will abound, the love of many will become cold. 13 But he that shall endure to the end, the same shall be saved. 14 And this gospel of the kingdom shall be preached in all the world, for a testimony to all nations; and then shall the end come. 15 When therefore ye shall see the abomination of desolation spoken of by Daniel the prophet, stand in the holy place, (whoever readeth, let him understand,) 16 Then let them who are in Judea flee to the mountains: 17 Let him who is on the house-top not come down to take any thing out of his house: 18 Neither let him who is in the field return back to take his clothes. 19 And woe to them that are with child, and to them that nurse infants in those days! 20 But pray ye that your flight may not be in the winter, neither on the sabbath: 21 For then shall be great tribulation, such as hath not been since the beginning of the world to this time, no, nor ever shall be. 22 And except those days should be shortened, there would no flesh be saved: but for the elect's sake those days shall be shortened. 23 Then if any man shall say to you, Lo, here is Christ, or there; believe it not. 24 For false Christs will arise, and false prophets, and will show great signs and wonders; so that, if it were possible, they would deceive the very elect. 25 Behold, I have told you before. 26 Wherefore, if they shall say to you, Behold, he is in the desert; go not forth: behold, he is in the secret chambers; believe it not. 27 For as the lightning cometh out of the east, and shineth even to the west; so shall also the coming of the Son of man be. 28 For wherever the carcass is, there will the eagles be collected. 29 Immediately after the tribulation of those days, shall the sun be darkened, and the moon shall not give her light, and the stars shall fall from heaven, and the powers of the heavens shall be shaken: 30 And then shall appear the sign of the Son of man in heaven: and then shall all the tribes of the earth mourn, and they shall see the Son of man coming in the clouds of heaven with power and great glory. 31 And he will send his angels with a great sound of a trumpet, and they will gather his elect from the four winds, from one end of heaven to the other. 32 Now learn a parable of the fig-tree; When its branch is yet tender and putteth forth leaves, ye know that summer is nigh: 33 So likewise ye, when ye shall see all these things, know that it is near, even at the doors. 34 Verily I say to you, This generation shall not pass, till all these things shall be fulfilled. 35 Heaven and earth shall pass away, but my words shall not pass away. 36 But of that day and hour knoweth no man , no, not the angels of heaven, but my Father only. 37 But as the days of Noah were , so will also the coming of the Son of man be. 38 For as in the days that were before the flood, they were eating and drinking, marrying and giving in marriage, until the day that Noah entered into the ark, 39 And knew not until the flood came, and took them all away: so also will be the coming of the Son of man. 40 Then will two be in the field; the one shall be taken, and the other left. 41 Two women will be grinding at the mill; the one shall be taken, and the other left. 42 Watch therefore; for ye know not what hour your Lord cometh. 43 But know this, that if the master of the house knew in what watch the thief would come, he would watch, and would not suffer his house to be broken up. 44 Therefore be ye also ready: for in such an hour as ye think not, the Son of man cometh. 45 Who then is a faithful and wise servant, whom his Lord hath made ruler over his household, to give them food in due season? 46 Blessed is that servant, whom his lord, when he cometh, shall find so doing. 47 Verily I say to you, that he will make him ruler over all his goods. 48 But if that evil servant shall say in his heart, My Lord delayeth his coming; 49 And shall begin to beat his fellow-servants, and to eat and drink with the drunken; 50 The Lord of that servant will come in a day when he looketh not for him , and in an hour that he is not aware of, 51 And will cut him asunder, and appoint him his portion with the hypocrites: there shall be weeping and gnashing of teeth.

25

1 Then shall the kingdom of heaven be likened to ten virgins, who took their lamps, and went forth to meet the bridegroom. 2 And five of them were wise, and five were foolish. 3 They that were foolish took their lamps, and took no oil with them: 4 But the wise took oil in their vessels with their lamps. 5 While the bridegroom tarried, they all slumbered and slept. 6 And at midnight there was a cry made, Behold, the bridegroom cometh; go ye out to meet him. 7 Then all those virgins arose, and trimmed their lamps. 8 And the foolish said to the wise, Give us of your oil: for our lamps are gone out. 9 But the wise answered, saying, Not so ; lest there be not enough for us and you: but go ye rather to them that sell, and buy for yourselves. 10 And while they were going to buy, the bridegroom came; and they that were ready, went in with him to the marriage, and the door was shut. 11 Afterward came also the other virgins, saying, Lord, Lord, open to us. 12 But he answered and said, Verily I say to you, I know you not. 13 Watch therefore, for ye know neither the day nor the hour in which the Son of man cometh. 14 For the kingdom of heaven is as a man traveling into a far country, who called his own servants, and delivered to them his goods. 15 And to one he gave five talents, to another two, and to another one; to every man according to his several ability; and forthwith took his journey. 16 Then he that had received the five talents, went and traded with the same, and gained other five talents. 17 And likewise he that had received two, he also gained other two. 18 But he that had received one, went and dug in the earth, and hid his lord's money. 19 After a long time the lord of those servants cometh, and reckoneth with them. 20 And he that had received five talents, came and brought other five talents, saying, Lord, thou deliveredst to me five talents: behold, I have gained besides them five talents more. 21 His lord said to him, Well done thou good and faithful servant; thou hast been faithful over a few things, I will make thee ruler over many things: enter thou into the joy of thy lord. 22 He also that had received two talents came, and said, Lord, thou deliveredst to me two talents: behold, I have gained two other talents besides them. 23 His lord said to him, Well done, good and faithful servant; thou hast been faithful over a few things, I will make thee ruler over many things: enter thou into the joy of thy lord. 24 Then he who had received the one talent came, and said, Lord, I knew thee that thou art a hard man, reaping where thou hast not sown, and gathering where thou hast not strewed: 25 And I was afraid, and went and hid thy talent in the earth: lo, there thou hast what is thine. 26 His lord answered and said to him, Thou wicked and slothful servant, thou knewest that I reap where I have not sown, and gather where I have not strewed: 27 Thou oughtest therefore to have put my money to the exchangers, and then at my coming I should have received my own with interest. 28 Take therefore the talent from him, and give it to him who hath ten talents. 29 For to every one that hath shall be given, and he shall have abundance: but from him that hath not shall be taken away even that which he hath. 30 And cast ye the unprofitable servant into utter darkness: there shall be weeping and gnashing of teeth. 31 When the Son of man shall come in his glory, and all the holy angels with him, then will he sit upon the throne of his glory: 32 And before him shall be gathered all nations: and he will separate them one from another, as a shepherd divideth his sheep from the goats: 33 And he will set the sheep on his right hand, but the goats on the left. 34 Then will the King say to them on his right hand, Come, ye blessed of my Father, inherit the kingdom prepared for you from the foundation of the world: 35 For I was hungry, and ye gave me food: I was thirsty, and ye gave me drink: I was a stranger, and ye took me in: 36 Naked, and ye clothed me: I was sick, and ye visited me: I was in prison, and ye came to me. 37 Then will the righteous answer him, saying, Lord, when saw we thee hungry, and fed thee ? or thirsty, and gave thee drink? 38 When saw we thee a stranger, and took thee in? or naked, and clothed thee ? 39 Or when saw we thee sick, or in prison, and came to thee? 40 And the king will answer and say to them, Verily I say to you, Inasmuch as ye have done it to one of the least of these my brethren, ye have done it to me. 41 Then will he say also to them on the left hand, Depart from me, ye cursed, into everlasting fire, prepared for the devil and his angels: 42 For I was hungry, and ye gave me no food: I was thirsty, and ye gave me no drink: 43 I was a stranger, and ye took me not in: naked, and ye clothed me not: sick, and in prison, and ye visited me not. 44 Then will they also answer him, saying, Lord, when saw we thee hungry, or thirsty, or a stranger, or naked, or sick, or in prison, and did not minister to thee? 45 Then will he answer them, saying, Verily I say to you, Inasmuch as ye did it not to one of the least of these, ye did it not to me. 46 And these shall go away into everlasting punishment: but the righteous into life eternal.

26

1 And it came to pass, when Jesus had finished all these sayings, he said to his disciples, 2 Ye know that after two days is the passover, and the Son of man is betrayed to be crucified. 3 Then assembled the chief priests, and the scribes, and the elders of the people, in the palace of the high priest, who was called Caiaphas, 4 And consulted that they might take Jesus by subtilty, and kill him . 5 But they said, Not on the feast -day , lest there be an uproar among the people. 6 Now when Jesus was in Bethany, in the house of Simon the leper, 7 There came to him a woman having an alabaster-box of very precious ointment, and poured it on his head as he sat at table . 8 But when his disciples saw it , they had indignation, saying, To what purpose is this waste? 9 For this ointment might have been sold for much, and given to the poor. 10 When Jesus understood it , he said to them, Why trouble ye the woman? for she hath wrought a good work upon me. 11 For ye have the poor always with you; but me ye have not always. 12 For in that she hath poured this ointment on my body, she did it for my burial. 13 Verily I say to you, Wherever this gospel shall be preached in the whole world, there shall also this, which this woman hath done, be told for a memorial of her. 14 Then one of the twelve, called Judas Iscariot, went to the chief priests, 15 And said, What will ye give me, and I will deliver him to you? And they covenanted with him for thirty pieces of silver. 16 And from that time he sought opportunity to betray him. 17 Now the first day of the feast of unleavened bread, the disciples came to Jesus, saying to him, Where wilt thou that we prepare for thee to eat the passover? 18 And he said, Go into the city to such a man, and say to him, The Master saith, My time is at hand; I will keep the passover at thy house with my disciples. 19 And the disciples did as Jesus had appointed them; and they made ready the passover. 20 Now when the evening was come, he sat down with the twelve. 21 And as they were eating, he said, Verily I say to you, that one of you will betray me. 22 And they were exceeding sorrowful, and began every one of them to say to him, Lord, is it I? 23 And he answered and said, He that dippeth his hand with me in the dish, the same will betray me. 24 The Son of man goeth, as it is written concerning him: but woe to that man by whom the Son of man is betrayed! it had been good for that man, if he had not been born. 25 Then Judas, who betrayed him, answered and said, Master, is it I? He said to him, Thou hast said. 26 And as they were eating, Jesus took bread, and blessed it , and broke it , and gave it to the disciples, and said, Take, eat; this is my body. 27 And he took the cup, and gave thanks, and gave it to them, saying, Drink ye all of it; 28 For this is my blood of the new testament, which is shed for many for the remission of sin. 29 But I say to you, I will not drink henceforth of this fruit of the vine, until that day when I drink it new with you in my Father's kingdom. 30 And when they had sung a hymn, they went out to the mount of Olives. 31 Then saith Jesus to them, All ye shall be offended because of me this night: for it is written, I will smite the shepherd, and the sheep of the flock shall be scattered abroad. 32 But after I am risen again, I will go before you into Galilee. 33 Peter answered and said to him, Though all men shall be offended because of thee, yet will I never be offended. 34 Jesus said to him, Verily I say to thee, that this night, before the cock shall crow, thou wilt deny me thrice. 35 Peter said to him, Though I should die with thee, yet will I not deny thee. Likewise also said all the disciples. 36 Then cometh Jesus with them to a place called Gethsemane, and saith to the disciples, Sit ye here, while I go yonder and pray. 37 And he took with him Peter, and the two sons of Zebedee, and began to be sorrowful and very heavy. 38 Then saith he to them, My soul is exceeding sorrowful, even to death: tarry ye here, and watch with me. 39 And he went a little further, and fell on his face, and prayed, saying, O my Father, if it is possible, let this cup pass from me: nevertheless, not as I will, but as thou wilt . 40 And he cometh to the disciples, and findeth them asleep, and saith to Peter, What, could ye not watch with me one hour? 41 Watch and pray, that ye enter not into temptation: the spirit indeed is willing, but the flesh is weak. 42 He went away again the second time, and prayed, saying, O my Father, if this cup may not pass away from me, except I drink it, thy will be done. 43 And he came and found them asleep again: for their eyes were heavy. 44 And he left them, and went away again, and prayed the third time, saying the same words. 45 Then he cometh to his disciples, and saith to them, Sleep on now, and take your rest: behold, the hour is at hand, and the Son of man is betrayed into the hands of sinners. 46 Rise, let us be going: behold, he is at hand that doth betray me. 47 And while he was yet speaking, lo, Judas, one of the twelve, came, and with him a great multitude with swords and staffs, from the chief priests and elders of the people. 48 Now he that betrayed him, gave them a sign, saying, Whomsoever I shall kiss, that same is he; hold him fast. 49 And forthwith he came to Jesus, and said, Hail Master; and kissed him. 50 And Jesus said to him, Friend, Why art thou come? Then they came, and laid hands on Jesus, and took him. 51 And behold, one of them, who were with Jesus, stretched out his hand, and drew his sword, and struck a servant of the high priest, and smote off his ear. 52 Then said Jesus to him, Put up again thy sword into its place: for all they that take the sword, shall perish by the sword. 53 Thinkest thou that I cannot now pray to my Father, and he will presently give me more than twelve legions of angels? 54 But how then shall the scriptures be fulfilled, that thus it must be? 55 In that same hour said Jesus to the multitudes, Are ye come out as against a thief with swords and staffs to take me? I sat daily with you teaching in the temple, and ye laid no hold on me. 56 But all this was done, that the scriptures of the prophets might be fulfilled. Then all the disciples forsook him, and fled. 57 And they that had laid hold on Jesus, led him away to Caiaphas the high priest, where the scribes and the elders were assembled. 58 But Peter followed him at a distance, to the high priest's palace, and went in, and sat with the servants to see the end. 59 Now the chief priests and elders, and all the council, sought false testimony against Jesus, to put him to death; 60 But found none: and, though many false witnesses came, yet found they none. At the last came two false witnesses, 61 And said, This man said, I am able to destroy the temple of God, and to build it in three days. 62 And the high priest arose, and said to him, Answerest thou nothing, what is it which these testify against thee? 63 But Jesus held his peace. And the high priest answered and said to him, I adjure thee by the living God, that thou tell us whether thou art the Christ the Son of God. 64 Jesus saith to him, Thou hast said: nevertheless I say to you, Hereafter shall ye see the Son of man sitting on the right hand of power, and coming in the clouds of heaven. 65 Then the high priest tore his clothes, saying, He hath spoken blasphemy; what further need have we of witnesses? behold, now ye have heard his blasphemy. 66 What think ye? They answered and said, He is guilty of death. 67 Then they spit in his face, and buffetted him; and others smote him with the palms of their hands, 68 Saying, Prophesy to us, thou Christ, Who is he that smote thee? 69 Now Peter sat without in the palace: and a damsel came to him, saying, Thou also wast with Jesus of Galilee. 70 But he denied before them all, saying, I know not what thou sayest. 71 And when he had gone out into the porch, another maid saw him, and said to them that were there, This man was also with Jesus of Nazareth. 72 And again he denied with an oath, I do not know the man. 73 And after a while came to him they that stood by, and said to Peter, Surely thou also art one of them; for thy speech betrayeth thee. 74 Then began he to curse and to swear, saying , I know not the man. And immediately the cock crowed. 75 And Peter remembered the word of Jesus, who said to him, Before the cock shall crow, thou wilt deny me thrice. And he went out, and wept bitterly.

27

1 When the morning was come, all the chief priests and elders of the people took counsel against Jesus to put him to death. 2 And when they had bound him, they led him away, and delivered him to Pontius Pilate the governor. 3 Then Judas, who had betrayed him, when he saw that he was condemned, repented and brought again the thirty pieces of silver to the chief priests and elders, 4 Saying, I have sinned in that I have betrayed innocent blood. And they said, What is that to us? see thou to that . 5 And he cast down the pieces of silver in the temple, and departed, and went and hanged himself. 6 And the chief priests took the silver pieces, and said, It is not lawful to put them into the treasury, because it is the price of blood. 7 And they took counsel, and bought with them the potter's field, to bury strangers in. 8 Wherefore that field has been called, The field of blood, to this day. 9 Then was fulfilled that which was spoken by Jeremiah the prophet, saying, And they took the thirty pieces of silver, the price of him that was valued, whom they of the children of Israel did value; 10 And gave them for the potter's field, as the Lord appointed me. 11 And Jesus stood before the governor: and the governor asked him, saying, Art thou the King of the Jews? And Jesus said to him, Thou sayest. 12 And when he was accused by the chief priests and elders, he answered nothing. 13 Then saith Pilate to him, Hearest thou not how many things they testify against thee? 14 And he answered him to not a word; so that the governor marveled greatly. 15 Now at that feast, the governor was wont to release to the people a prisoner, whom they would. 16 And they had then a notable prisoner, called Barabbas. 17 Therefore when they were assembled, Pilate said to them, Whom will ye that I release to you? Barabbas, or Jesus, who is called Christ? 18 (For he knew that for envy they had delivered him.) 19 When he was sitting on the judgment-seat, his wife sent to him, saying, Have thou nothing to do with that just man: for I have suffered many things this day in a dream, because of him. 20 But the chief priests and elders persuaded the multitude that they should ask Barabbas, and destroy Jesus. 21 The governor answered and said to them, Which of the two will ye that I release to you? They said, Barabbas. 22 Pilate saith to them, What shall I do then with Jesus, who is called Christ? They all say to him, Let him be crucified. 23 And the governor said, Why, what evil hath he done? But they cried out the more, saying, Let him be crucified. 24 When Pilate saw that he could not prevail at all, but that rather a tumult was made, he took water, and washed his hands before the multitude, saying, I am innocent of the blood of this just person: see ye to it . 25 Then answered all the people, and said, His blood be on us, and on our children. 26 Then he released Barabbas to them: and when he had scourged Jesus, he delivered him to be crucified. 27 Then the soldiers of the governor took Jesus into the common hall, and gathered to him the whole band of soldiers . 28 And they stripped him, and put on him a scarlet robe. 29 And when they had platted a crown of thorns, they put it upon his head, and a reed in his right hand: and they bowed the knee before him, and mocked him, saying, Hail, King of the Jews? 30 And they spit upon him, and took the reed, and struck him on the head. 31 And after that they had mocked him, they took the robe off from him, and put his own raiment on him, and led him away to crucify him . 32 And as they came out, they found a man of Cyrene, Simon by name: him they constrained to bear his cross. 33 And when they had come to a place called Golgotha, that is to say, a place of a skull, 34 They gave him vinegar to drink, mingled with gall: and when he had tasted of it , he would not drink. 35 And they crucified him, and parted his garments, casting lots: that it might be fulfilled which was spoken by the prophet, They parted my garments among them, and upon my vesture they cast lots. 36 And sitting down, they watched him there: 37 And set up over his head his accusation written, THIS IS JESUS THE KING OF THE JEWS. 38 Then were there two thieves crucified with him: one on the right hand, and another on the left. 39 And they that passed by, reviled him, wagging their heads, 40 And saying, Thou that destroyest the temple, and buildest it in three days, save thyself. If thou art the Son of God, come down from the cross. 41 Likewise also the chief priests mocking him , with the scribes and elders, said, 42 He saved others; himself he cannot save. If he is King of Israel, let him now come down from the cross, and we will believe him. 43 He trusted in God; let him deliver him now if he will have him: for he said, I am the Son of God. 44 The thieves also who were crucified with him, cast the same in his teeth. 45 Now from the sixth hour there was darkness over all the land to the ninth hour. 46 And about the ninth hour Jesus cried with a loud voice, saying, Eli, Eli, lama sabachthani? that is to say, My God, my God, why hast thou forsaken me? 47 Some of them that stood there, when they heard that , said, This man calleth for Elijah. 48 And immediately one of them ran, and took a spunge, and filled it with vinegar, and put it on a reed, and gave him to drink. 49 The rest said, Forbear, let us see whether Elijah will come to save him. 50 Jesus, when he had cried again with a loud voice, expired. 51 And behold, the veil of the temple was torn in two, from the top to the bottom: and the earth shook, and the rocks split; 52 And the graves were opened, and many bodies of saints who slept, arose, 53 And came out of the graves after his resurrection, and went into the holy city, and appeared to many. 54 Now when the centurion, and they that were with him, watching Jesus, saw the earthquake, and those things that were done, they feared greatly, saying, Truly this was the Son of God. 55 And many women were there (beholding at a distance) who followed Jesus from Galilee, ministering to him: 56 Among whom was Mary Magdalene, and Mary the mother of James and Joses, and the mother of Zebedee's children. 57 When the evening was come, there came a rich man of Arimathea, named Joseph, who also himself was a disciple of Jesus. 58 He went to Pilate, and begged the body of Jesus. Then Pilate commanded the body to be delivered. 59 And when Joseph had taken the body, he wrapped it in a clean linen cloth, 60 And laid it in his own new tomb, which he had hewn out in the rock; and he rolled a great stone to the door of the sepulcher, and departed. 61 And there was Mary Magdalene, and the other Mary, sitting over against the sepulcher. 62 Now the next day that followed the day of the preparation, the chief priests and Pharisees came together to Pilate, 63 Saying, Sir, we remember that that deceiver said, while he was yet alive, After three days I will rise again. 64 Command therefore that the sepulcher be made secure until the third day, lest his disciples come by night, and steal him away, and say to the people, He is risen from the dead: so the last error will be worse than the first. 65 Pilate said to them, Ye have a watch: go, make it as secure as ye can. 66 So they went, and having sealed the stone, made the sepulcher secure with a watch.

28

1 In the end of the sabbath, as it began to dawn towards the first day of the week, came Mary Magdalene, and the other Mary to see the sepulcher. 2 And behold, there was a great earthquake: for the angel of the Lord descended from heaven, and came and rolled back the stone from the door, and sat upon it. 3 His countenance was like lightning, and his raiment white as snow. 4 And for fear of him the keepers trembled and became as dead men . 5 And the angel answered and said to the women, Fear ye not: for I know that ye seek Jesus, who was crucified. 6 He is not here: for he is risen, as he said. Come, see the place where the Lord lay. 7 And go quickly, and tell his disciples, that he is risen from the dead, and behold, he goeth before you into Galilee; there shall ye see him: lo, I have told you. 8 And they departed quickly from the sepulcher, with fear and great joy; and ran to bring word to his disciples. 9 And as they were going to tell his disciples, behold, Jesus met them, saying, All hail. And they came, and held him by the feet, and worshiped him. 10 Then said Jesus to them, Be not afraid: go tell my brethren, that they go into Galilee, and there shall they see me. 11 Now when they were going, behold, some of the watch came into the city, and showed to the chief priests all the things that had been done. 12 And when they were assembled with the elders, and had taken counsel, they gave a large sum of money to the soldiers, 13 Saying, Say ye, His disciples came by night, and stole him away while we slept. 14 And if this shall come to the governor's ears, we will persuade him, and secure you. 15 So they took the money, and did as they were instructed: and this saying is commonly reported among the Jews until this day. 16 Then the eleven disciples went away into Galilee, to a mountain where Jesus had appointed them. 17 And when they saw him, they worshiped him: but some doubted. 18 And Jesus came, and spoke to them, saying, All power is given to me in heaven and upon earth. 19 Go ye therefore and teach all nations, baptizing them in the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit. 20 Teaching them to observe all things whatever I have commanded you: and lo, I am with you always, even to the end of the world. Amen.

Romans

1
2
3
4
5
6
7
8
9
10

11
12
13
14
15
16

THE EPISTLE OF PAUL THE APOSTLE TO THE ROMANS

1

1 Paul, a servant of Jesus Christ, called to be an apostle, separated to the gospel of God, 2 (Which he had promised before by his prophets in the holy scriptures) 3 Concerning his Son Jesus Christ our Lord, who was born of the seed of David according to the flesh. 4 And declared to be the Son of God, with power, according to the spirit of holiness, by the resurrection from the dead: 5 By whom we have received grace and apostleship for obedience to the faith among all nations for his name: 6 Among whom are ye also the called of Jesus Christ: 7 To all that are in Rome, beloved of God, called to be saints: Grace to you, and peace from God our Father, and the Lord Jesus Christ. 8 First, I thank my God through Jesus Christ for you all, that your faith is spoken of throughout the whole world. 9 For God is my witness, whom I serve with my spirit in the gospel of his Son, that without ceasing I make mention of you always in my prayers, 10 Making request (if by any means now at length I may have a prosperous journey by the will of God) to come to you. 11 For I long to see you, that I may impart to you some spiritual gift, to the end ye may be established; 12 That is, that I may be comforted together with you, by the mutual faith both of you and me. 13 Now I would not have you ignorant, brethren, that I have often purposed to come to you (but have been hitherto hindered) that I might have some fruit among you also, even as among other Gentiles. 14 I am debtor both to the Greeks, and to the barbarians, both to the wise, and to the unwise. 15 So, as much as in me is, I am ready to preach the gospel to you that are at Rome also. 16 For I am not ashamed of the gospel of Christ: for it is the power of God to salvation to every one that believeth; to the Jew first, and also to the Greek. 17 For in this is the righteousness of God revealed from faith to faith: as it is written, The just shall live by faith. 18 For the wrath of God is revealed from heaven against all ungodliness, and unrighteousness of men, who hold the truth in unrighteousness. 19 Because that which may be known of God, is manifest in them; for God hath shown it to them. 20 For the invisible things of him from the creation of the world are clearly seen, being understood by the things that are made, even his eternal power and Godhead; so that they are without excuse: 21 Because that when they knew God, they glorified him not as God, neither were thankful, but became vain in their imaginations, and their foolish heart was darkened. 22 Professing themselves to be wise, they became fools: 23 And changed the glory of the incorruptible God into an image made like to corruptible man, and to birds, and four-footed beasts, and creeping animals. 24 Wherefore God also gave them up to uncleanness, through the lusts of their own hearts, to dishonor their own bodies between themselves: 25 Who changed the truth of God into a lie, and worshiped and served the creature more than the Creator, who is blessed for ever. Amen. 26 For this cause God gave them up to vile affections. For even their women did change the natural use into that which is against nature: 27 And likewise also the men, leaving the natural use of the woman, burned in their lust one towards another; men with men working that which is unseemly, and receiving in themselves that recompense of their error which was meet. 28 And even as they did not like to retain God in their knowledge, God gave them over to a reprobate mind, to do those things which are not convenient; 29 Being filled with all unrighteousness, fornication, wickedness, covetousness, maliciousness; full of envy, murder, debate, deceit, malignity; whisperers, 30 Backbiters, haters of God, despiteful, proud, boasters, inventers of evil things, disobedient to parents, 31 Without understanding, covenant-breakers, without natural affection, implacable, unmerciful: 32 Who, knowing the judgment of God, that they who commit such things are worthy of death; not only do the same, but have pleasure in them that do them.

2

1 Therefore thou art inexcusable, O man, whoever thou art, that judgest: for wherein thou judgest another, thou condemnest thyself; for thou that judgest, doest the same things. 2 But we are sure that the judgment of God is according to truth, against them who commit such things. 3 And thinkest thou this, O man, that judgest them who do such things, and doest the same, that thou shalt escape the judgment of God? 4 Or despisest thou the riches of his goodness, and forbearance, and long-suffering; not knowing that the goodness of God leadeth thee to repentance? 5 But after thy hardness and impenitent heart, treasurest up to thyself wrath against the day of wrath, and revelation of the righteous judgment of God; 6 Who will render to every man according to his deeds: 7 To them who by patient continuance in well-doing, seek for glory, and honor, and immortality; eternal life: 8 But to them that are contentious, and do not obey the truth, but obey unrighteousness; indignation and wrath: 9 Tribulation and anguish upon every soul of man that doeth evil, of the Jew first, and also of the Gentile; 10 But glory, honor, and peace, to every man that worketh good, to the Jew first, and also to the Gentile; 11 For there is no respect of persons with God. 12 For as many as have sinned without law, shall also perish without law: and as many as have sinned in the law, shall be judged by the law, 13 (For not the hearers of the law are just before God, but the doers of the law shall be justified. 14 For when the Gentiles, who have not the law, do by nature the things contained in the law, these having not the law, are a law to themselves. 15 Who show the work of the law written in their hearts, their conscience also bearing testimony, and their thoughts the mean while accusing, or else excusing one another) 16 In the day when God shall judge the secrets of men by Jesus Christ, according to my gospel. 17 Behold, thou art called a Jew, and restest in the law, and makest thy boast of God, 18 And knowest his will, and approvest the things that are more excellent, being instructed out of the law, 19 And art confident that thou thyself art a guide of the blind, a light of them who are in darkness, 20 An instructor of the foolish, a teacher of babes, who hast the form of knowledge, and of the truth in the law: 21 Thou therefore who teachest another, teachest thou not thyself? thou that preachest a man should not steal, dost thou steal? 22 Thou that sayest a man should not commit adultery, dost thou commit adultery? thou that abhorrest idols, dost thou commit sacrilege? 23 Thou that makest thy boast of the law, through breaking the law dishonorest thou God? 24 For the name of God is blasphemed among the Gentiles, through you, as it is written. 25 For circumcision verily profiteth, if thou keepest the law; but if thou art a breaker of the law, thy circumcision is made uncircumcision. 26 Therefore, if the uncircumcision keepeth the righteousness of the law, shall not his uncircumcision be counted for circumcision? 27 And shall not uncircumcision which is by nature, if it fulfilleth the law, judge thee, who by the letter and circumcision dost transgress the law? 28 For he is not a Jew, who is one outwardly; neither is that circumcision, which is outward in the flesh: 29 But he is a Jew who is one inwardly; and circumcision is that of the heart, in the spirit, and not in the letter; whose praise is not from men, but from God.

3

1 What advantage then hath the Jew? or what profit is there of circumcision? 2 Much every way: chiefly, because that to them were committed the oracles of God. 3 For what if some did not believe? will their unbelief make the faith of God without effect? 4 By no means: verily let God be true, but every man a liar; as it is written, That thou mayest be justified in thy sayings, and mayest overcome when thou art judged. 5 But if our unrighteousness commendeth the righteousness of God, what shall we say? Is God unrighteous who taketh vengeance? (I speak as a man.) 6 By no means: for then how shall God judge the world? 7 For if the truth of God hath more abounded through my lie to his glory; why yet am I also judged as a sinner? 8 And not rather (as we are slanderously reported, and as some affirm that we say) Let us do evil, that good may come? whose damnation is just. 9 What then? are we better than they ? No, in no wise: for we have before proved both Jews and Gentiles, that they are all under sin; 10 As it is written, There is none righteous, no, not one: 11 There is none that understandeth, there is none that seeketh God. 12 They are all gone out of the way, they are together become unprofitable: there is none that doeth good, no, not one. 13 Their throat is an open sepulcher; with their tongues they have used deceit; the poison of asps is under their lips: 14 Whose mouth is full of cursing and bitterness. 15 Their feet are swift to shed blood. 16 Destruction and misery are in their ways: 17 And the way of peace have they not known. 18 There is no fear of God before their eyes. 19 Now we know that whatever things the law saith, it saith to them who are under the law: that every mouth may be stopped, and all the world may become guilty before God. 20 Therefore by the deeds of the law, there shall no flesh be justified in his sight: for by the law is the knowledge of sin. 21 But now the righteousness of God without the law is manifested, being testified by the law and the prophets; 22 Even the righteousness of God, which is by faith of Jesus Christ to all, and upon all them that believe; for there is no difference: 23 For all have sinned, and come short of the glory of God; 24 Being justified freely by his grace, through the redemption that is in Jesus Christ: 25 Whom God hath set forth to be a propitiation, through faith in his blood, to declare his righteousness for the remission of sins that are past, through the forbearance of God; 26 To declare, I say , at this time his righteousness: that he may be just, and the justifier of him who believeth in Jesus. 27 Where is boasting then? It is excluded. By what law? of works? No; but by the law of faith. 28 Therefore we conclude, that a man is justified by faith without the deeds of the law. 29 Is he the God of the Jews only? is he not also of the Gentiles? Yes, of the Gentiles also: 30 Seeing it is one God who will justify the circumcision by faith, and uncircumcision through faith. 31 Do we then make void the law through faith? By no means: but we establish the law.

4

1 What shall we then say that Abraham our father, as pertaining to the flesh, hath found? 2 For if Abraham were justified by works, he hath whereof to glory, but not before God. 3 For what saith the scripture? Abraham believed God, and it was counted to him for righteousness. 4 Now to him that worketh, is the reward not reckoned of grace, but of debt. 5 But to him that worketh not, but believeth on him that justifieth the ungodly, his faith is counted for righteousness. 6 Even as David also describeth the blessedness of the man to whom God imputeth righteousness without works, 7 Saying , Blessed are they whose iniquities are forgiven, and whose sins are covered. 8 Blessed is the man to whom the Lord will not impute sin. 9 Cometh this blessedness then upon the circumcision only , or upon the uncircumcision also? For we say that faith was reckoned to Abraham for righteousness. 10 How then was it reckoned? when he was in circumcision, or in uncircumcision? Not in circumcision, but in uncircumcision. 11 And he received the sign of circumcision, a seal of the righteousness of the faith, which he had yet being uncircumcised: that he might be the father of all them that believe, though they are not circumcised, that righteousness might be imputed to them also; 12 And the father of circumcision to them who are not of the circumcision only, but who also walk in the steps of that faith of our father Abraham which he had being yet uncircumcised. 13 For the promise that he should be the heir of the world was not to Abraham, or to his seed, through the law, but through the righteousness of faith. 14 For if they who are of the law are heirs, faith is made void, and the promise made of no effect. 15 Because the law worketh wrath: for where no law is, there is no transgression. 16 Therefore it is of faith, that it might be by grace; to the end the promise might be sure to all the seed, not to that only which is of the law, but to that also which is of the faith of Abraham, who is the father of us all; 17 (As it is written, I have made thee a father of many nations) before him whom he believed, even God, who reviveth the dead, and calleth those things which are not, as though they were. 18 Who against hope believed with hope, that he should become the father of many nations; according to that which was spoken, So shall thy seed be. 19 And being not weak in faith, he considered not his own body now dead, when he was about a hundred years old, neither yet the deadness of Sarah's womb. 20 He staggered not at the promise of God through unbelief; but was strong in faith, giving glory to God; 21 And being fully persuaded, that what he had promised, he was able also to perform. 22 And therefore it was imputed to him for righteousness. 23 Now it was not written for his sake alone, that it was imputed to him; 24 But for us also, to whom it will be imputed, if we believe on him that raised Jesus our Lord from the dead, 25 Who was delivered for our offenses, and raised again for our justification.

5

1 Therefore being justified by faith, we have peace with God, through our Lord Jesus Christ: 2 By whom also we have access by faith into this grace in which we stand, and rejoice in hope of the glory of God. 3 And not only so , but we glory in tribulations also; knowing that tribulation worketh patience; 4 And patience, experience; and experience, hope: 5 And hope maketh not ashamed, because the love of God is shed abroad in our hearts, by the Holy Spirit which is given to us. 6 For when we were yet without strength, in due time Christ died for the ungodly. 7 For scarcely for a righteous man will one die: yet perhaps for a good man some would even dare to die. 8 But God commendeth his love towards us, in that while we were yet sinners, Christ died for us. 9 Much more then, being now justified by his blood, we shall be saved from wrath through him. 10 For if when we were enemies, we were reconciled to God by the death of his Son; much more, being reconciled, we shall be saved by his life. 11 And not only so , but we also joy in God, through our Lord Jesus Christ, by whom we have now received the atonement. 12 Wherefore as by one man sin entered into the world, and death by sin; and so death passed upon all men, for that all have sinned. 13 For until the law, sin was in the world: but sin is not imputed when there is no law. 14 Nevertheless, death reigned from Adam to Moses, even over them that had not sinned after the similitude of Adam's transgression, who is the figure of him that was to come. 15 But not as the offense, so also is the free gift. For if through the offense of one many are dead, much more the grace of God, and the gift by grace, which is by one man, Jesus Christ, hath abounded to many. 16 And not as it was by one that sinned, so is the gift. For the judgment was by one to condemnation, but the free gift is of many offenses to justification. 17 For if by one man's offense death reigned by one; much more they who receive abundance of grace, and of the gift of righteousness, shall reign in life by one, Jesus Christ. 18 Therefore, as by the offense of one, judgment came upon all men to condemnation, even so by the righteousness of one the free gift came upon all men to justification of life. 19 For as by one man's disobedience many were made sinners, so by the obedience of one shall many be made righteous. 20 Moreover the law entered, that the offense might abound. But where sin abounded, grace did much more abound: 21 That as sin hath reigned to death, even so might grace reign through righteousness to eternal life, by Jesus Christ our Lord.

6

1 What shall we say then? Shall we continue in sin, that grace may abound? 2 By no means: how shall we, that are dead to sin, live any longer therein? 3 Know ye not, that so many of us as were baptized into Jesus Christ, were baptized into his death? 4 Therefore we are buried with him by baptism into death: that as Christ was raised from the dead by the glory of the Father, even so we also should walk in newness of life. 5 For if we have been planted together in the likeness of his death, we shall be also in the likeness of his resurrection: 6 Knowing this, that our old man is crucified with him , that the body of sin may be destroyed, that henceforth we should not serve sin. 7 For he that is dead is freed from sin. 8 Now if we are dead with Christ, we believe that we shall also live with him: 9 Knowing that Christ, being raised from the dead, dieth no more; death hath no more dominion over him. 10 For in that he died, he died to sin once: but in that he liveth, he liveth to God. 11 Likewise reckon ye also yourselves to be dead indeed to sin, but alive to God through Jesus Christ our Lord. 12 Let not sin therefore reign in your mortal body, that ye should obey it in the lusts of it. 13 Neither yield ye your members as instruments of unrighteousness to sin: but yield yourselves to God, as those that are alive from the dead, and your members as instruments of righteousness to God: 14 For sin shall not have dominion over you: for ye are not under the law, but under grace. 15 What then? shall we sin, because we are not under the law, but under grace? By no means. 16 Know ye not, that to whom ye yield yourselves servants in obedience, his servants ye are whom ye obey; whether of sin to death, or of obedience to righteousness? 17 But God be thanked, that ye were the servants of sin; but ye have obeyed from the heart that form of doctrine which was delivered you. 18 Being then made free from sin, ye became the servants of righteousness. 19 I speak after the manner of men, because of the infirmity of your flesh: for as ye have yielded your members servants to uncleanness and to iniquity, to (work ) iniquity; even so now yield your members servants to righteousness, to (work ) holiness. 20 For when ye were the servants of sin, ye were free from righteousness. 21 What fruit had ye then in those things of which ye are now ashamed? for the end of those things is death. 22 But now being made free from sin, and having become servants to God, ye have your fruit to holiness, and the end everlasting life. 23 For the wages of sin is death: but the gift of God is eternal life, through Jesus Christ our Lord.

7

1 Know ye not, brethren, (for I speak to them that know the law) that the law hath dominion over a man as long as he liveth? 2 For the woman who hath a husband, is bound by the law to her husband so long as he liveth; but if the husband is dead, she is loosed from the law of her husband. 3 So then, if while her husband liveth, she is married to another man, she shall be called an adulteress: but if her husband is dead, she is free from that law; so that she is no adulteress, though she be married to another man. 4 Wherefore, my brethren, ye also are become dead to the law by the body of Christ; that ye should be married to another, even to him who is raised from the dead, that we should bring forth fruit to God. 5 For when we were in the flesh, the motions of sins, which were by the law, did work in our members to bring forth fruit to death: 6 But now we are delivered from the law, that being dead by which we were held; that we should serve in newness of spirit, and not in the oldness of the letter. 7 What shall we say then? Is the law sin? By no means. No, I had not known sin, but by the law: for I had not known lust, except the law had said, Thou shalt not covet. 8 But sin, taking occasion by the commandment, wrought in me all manner of concupiscence. For without the law sin was dead. 9 For I was alive without the law once: but when the commandment came, sin revived, and I died. 10 And the commandment which was ordained to life, I found to be to death. 11 For sin, taking occasion by the commandment, deceived me, and by it slew me . 12 Wherefore the law is holy, and the commandment holy, and just, and good. 13 Was then that which is good made death to me? By no means. But sin, that it might appear sin, working death in me by that which is good; that sin by the commandment might become exceeding sinful. 14 For we know that the law is spiritual: but I am carnal, sold under sin. 15 For that which I do, I allow not: for what I would, that I do not; but what I hate, that I do. 16 If then I do that which I would not, I consent to the law that it is good. 17 Now then it is no more I that do it, but sin that dwelleth in me. 18 For I know that in me (that is, in my flesh,) dwelleth no good thing: for to will is present with me; but how to perform that which is good, I find not. 19 For the good that I would, I do not; but the evil which I would not, that I do. 20 Now if I do that which I would not, it is no more I that do it, but sin that dwelleth in me. 21 I find then a law, that when I would do good, evil is present with me. 22 For I delight in the law of God, after the inward man: 23 But I see another law in my members warring against the law of my mind, and bringing me into captivity to the law of sin which is in my members. 24 O wretched man that I am! who shall deliver me from the body of this death? 25 I thank God, through Jesus Christ our Lord. So then, with the mind I myself serve the law of God; but with the flesh the law of sin.

8

1 There is therefore now no condemnation to them who are in Christ Jesus, who walk not according to the flesh, but according to the Spirit. 2 For the law of the Spirit of life, in Christ Jesus, hath made me free from the law of sin and death. 3 For what the law could not do, in that it was weak through the flesh, God, sending his own Son in the likeness of sinful flesh, and for sin, condemned sin in the flesh: 4 That the righteousness of the law may be fulfilled in us, who walk not according to the flesh, but according to the Spirit. 5 For they that are according to the flesh, do mind the things of the flesh: but they that are according to the Spirit, the things of the Spirit. 6 For to be carnally minded is death; but to be spiritually minded is life and peace: 7 Because the carnal mind is enmity against God: for it is not subject to the law of God, neither indeed can be. 8 So then they that are in the flesh cannot please God. 9 But ye are not in the flesh, but in the Spirit, if the Spirit of God dwelleth in you. Now if any man hath not the Spirit of Christ, he is not his. 10 And if Christ is in you, the body is dead because of sin; but the Spirit is life because of righteousness. 11 But if the Spirit of him that raised Jesus from the dead dwelleth in you, he that raised Christ from the dead will also revive your mortal bodies by his Spirit that dwelleth in you. 12 Therefore, brethren, we are debtors, not to the flesh, to live according to the flesh. 13 For if ye live according to the flesh, ye shall die: but if ye through the Spirit mortify the deeds of the body, ye shall live. 14 For as many as are led by the Spirit of God, they are the sons of God. 15 For ye have not received the spirit of bondage again to fear; but ye have received the Spirit of adoption, by which we cry, Abba, Father. 16 The Spirit itself testifieth with our spirit, that we are the children of God: 17 And if children, then heirs; heirs of God, and joint-heirs with Christ; if we suffer with him , that we may be glorified together. 18 For I reckon, that the sufferings of this present time are not worthy to be compared with the glory which shall be revealed in us. 19 For the earnest expectation of the creature waiteth for the manifestation of the sons of God. 20 For the creature was made subject to vanity, not willingly, but by reason of him who hath subjected the same in hope: 21 Because the creature itself also shall be delivered from the bondage of corruption, into the glorious liberty of the children of God. 22 For we know that the whole creation groaneth, and travaileth in pain together until now: 23 And not only they , but ourselves also, who have the first-fruits of the Spirit, even we ourselves groan within ourselves, waiting for the adoption, to wit , the redemption of our body. 24 For we are saved by hope: But hope that is seen, is not hope: for what a man seeth, why doth he yet hope for? 25 But if we hope for what we see not, then with patience we wait for it . 26 Likewise the Spirit also helpeth our infirmities: for we know not what we should pray for as we ought: but the Spirit itself maketh intercession for us with groanings which cannot be uttered. 27 And he that searcheth the hearts knoweth what is the mind of the Spirit, because he maketh intercession for the saints, according to the will of God. 28 And we know that all things work together for good, to them that love God, to them who are the called according to his purpose. 29 For whom he did foreknow, he also did predestinate to be conformed to the image of his Son, that he might be the first-born among many brethren. 30 Moreover, whom he did predestinate, them he also called: and whom he called, them he also justified: and whom he justified, them he also glorified. 31 What shall we then say to these things? If God is for us, who can be against us? 32 He that spared not his own Son, but delivered him up for us all, how shall he not with him also freely give us all things? 33 Who will lay any thing to the charge of God's elect? It is God that justifieth: 34 Who is he that condemneth? It is Christ that died, or rather that is risen again, who is even at the right hand of God, who also maketh intercession for us. 35 Who shall separate us from the love of Christ? shall tribulation, or distress, or persecution, or famine, or nakedness, or peril, or sword? 36 As it is written, For thy sake we are killed all the day long; we are accounted as sheep for the slaughter. 37 But in all these things we are more than conquerors, through him that loved us. 38 For I am persuaded, that neither death, nor life, nor angels, nor principalities, nor powers, nor things present, nor things to come, 39 Nor hight, nor depth, nor any other creature, will be able to separate us from the love of God which is in Christ Jesus our Lord.

9

1 I say the truth in Christ, I lie not, my conscience also bearing me testimony in the Holy Spirit, 2 That I have great heaviness and continual sorrow in my heart. 3 For I could wish that myself were accursed from Christ, for my brethren, my kinsmen according to the flesh: 4 Who are Israelites; to whom pertain the adoption, and the glory, and the covenants, and the giving of the law, and the service of God , and the promises; 5 Whose are the fathers, and from whom according to the flesh, Christ came , who is over all, God blessed for ever. Amen. 6 Not as though the word of God hath taken no effect. For they are not all Israel, who are descendants from Israel? 7 Neither because they are the seed of Abraham, are they all children: but, In Isaac shall thy seed be called. 8 That is, They who are the children of the flesh, these are not the children of God; but the children of the promise are counted for the seed. 9 For this is the word of promise, At this time will I come, and Sarah shall have a son. 10 And not only this ; but when Rebecca also had conceived by one, even by our father Isaac, 11 (For the children being not yet born, neither having done any good or evil, that the purpose of God, according to election might stand, not of works, but of him that calleth) 12 It was said to her, The elder shall serve the younger. 13 As it is written, Jacob have I loved, but Esau have I hated. 14 What shall we say then? Is there unrighteousness with God? By no means. 15 For he saith to Moses, I will have mercy on whom I will have mercy, and I will have compassion on whom I will have compassion. 16 So then, it is not of him that willeth, nor of him that runneth, but of God that showeth mercy. 17 For the scripture saith to Pharaoh, Even for this same purpose have I raised thee up, that I might show my power in thee, and that my name might be declared throughout all the earth. 18 Therefore he hath mercy on whom he will have mercy , and whom he will he hardeneth. 19 Thou wilt say then to me, Why doth he yet find fault? for who hath resisted his will? 20 No, but, O man, who art thou that repliest against God? shall the thing formed say to him that formed it , Why hast thou made me thus? 21 Hath not the potter power over the clay of the same lump to make one vessel to honor, and another to dishonor? 22 What if God, willing to show his wrath, and to make his power known, endured with much long-suffering the vessels of wrath fitted to destruction: 23 And that he might make known the riches of his glory on the vessels of mercy, which he had before prepared for glory, 24 Even us whom he hath called, not of the Jews only, but also of the Gentiles. 25 As he saith also in Hosea, I will call them My people, who were not my people; and her Beloved, who was not beloved. 26 And it shall come to pass, that in the place where it was said to them, Ye are not my people; there shall they be called, The children of the living God. 27 Isaiah also crieth concerning Israel, Though the number of the children of Israel be as the sand of the sea, a remnant shall be saved: 28 For he will finish the work, and cut it short in righteousness: because a short work will the Lord make upon the earth. 29 And as Isaiah said before, Except the Lord of Sabaoth had left us a seed, we had been as Sodom, and been made like Gomorrah. 30 What shall we say then? That the Gentiles who followed not after righteousness, have attained to righteousness, even the righteousness which is by faith: 31 But Israel, who followed after the law of righteousness, hath not attained to the law of righteousness. 32 Why? Because they sought it not by faith, but as it were by the works of the law. For they stumbled at that stumbling-stone; 33 As it is written, Behold, I lay in Sion a stumbling-stone, and rock of offense: and whoever believeth on him shall not be ashamed.

10

1 Brethren, my heart's desire and prayer to God for Israel is, that they may be saved. 2 For I bear them testimony that they have a zeal of God, but not according to knowledge. 3 For they, being ignorant of God's righteousness, and seeking to establish their own righteousness, have not submitted themselves to the righteousness of God. 4 For Christ is the end of the law for righteousness to every one that believeth. 5 For Moses describeth the righteousness which is by the law, That the man who doeth these things shall live by them. 6 But the righteousness which is by faith speaketh on this wise, Say not in thy heart, Who shall ascend into heaven? (that is, to bring Christ down.) 7 Or, Who shall descend into the deep? (that is, to bring Christ again from the dead.) 8 But what saith it? The word is nigh thee, even in thy mouth, and in thy heart: that is, the word of faith, which we preach: 9 That if thou shalt confess with thy mouth the Lord Jesus, and shalt believe in thy heart that God hath raised him from the dead, thou shalt be saved. 10 For with the heart man believeth to righteousness; and with the mouth confession is made to salvation. 11 For the scripture saith, whoever believeth on him shall not be ashamed. 12 For there is no difference between the Jew and the Greek: for the same Lord over all, is rich to all that call upon him, 13 For whoever shall call upon the name of the Lord shall be saved. 14 How then shall they call on him in whom they have not believed? and how shall they believe in him of whom they have not heard? and how shall they hear without a preacher? 15 And how shall they preach, except they be sent? as it is written, How beautiful are the feet of them that preach the gospel of peace, and bring glad tidings of good things? 16 But they have not all obeyed the gospel. For Isaiah saith, Lord, who hath believed our report? 17 So then, faith cometh by hearing, and hearing by the word of God. 18 But I say, Have they not heard? Yes verily, their sound went into all the earth, and their words to the ends of the world. 19 But I say, Did not Israel know? First, Moses saith, I will provoke you to jealousy by them that are no people, and by a foolish nation I will anger you. 20 But Isaiah is very bold, and saith, I was found by them that sought me not; I was made manifest to them that asked not for me. 21 But to Israel he saith, All day long I have stretched forth my hands to a disobedient and gainsaying people.

11

1 I say then, Hath God cast away his people? By no means. For I also am an Israelite, of the seed of Abraham, of the tribe of Benjamin. 2 God hath not cast away his people which he foreknew. Know ye not what the scripture saith of Elijah? how he maketh intercession to God against Israel, saying, 3 Lord, they have killed thy prophets, and dug down thy altars; and I am left alone, and they seek my life. 4 But what saith the answer of God to him? I have reserved to myself seven thousand men, who have not bowed the knee to Baal. 5 Even so then at this present time also there is a remnant according to the election of grace. 6 And if by grace, then is it no more of works: otherwise grace is no more grace. But if of works, then is it no more grace: otherwise work is no more work. 7 What then? Israel hath not obtained that which he seeketh for; but the election hath obtained it, and the rest were blinded. 8 (According as it is written, God hath given them the spirit of slumber, eyes that they should not see, and ears that they should not hear;) to this day. 9 And David saith, Let their table be made a snare, and a trap, and a stumbling-block, and a recompense to them: 10 Let their eyes be darkened, that they may not see, and bow down their back always. 11 I say then, Have they stumbled that they should fall? By no means: but rather through their fall salvation is come to the Gentiles, to provoke them to jealousy. 12 Now if the fall of them be the riches of the world, and the diminishing of them the riches of the Gentiles; how much more their fullness? 13 For I speak to you Gentiles, inasmuch as I am the apostle of the Gentiles, I magnify my office: 14 If by any means I may incite to jealousy them who are my flesh, and may save some of them. 15 For if the rejection of them be the reconciling of the world, what shall the receiving of them be , but life from the dead? 16 For if the first fruit is holy, the lump is also holy : and if the root is holy, so are the branches. 17 And if some of the branches be broken off, and thou, being a wild olive-tree, art ingrafted among them, and with them partakest of the root and fatness of the olive-tree; 18 Boast not against the branches. But if thou boastest, thou bearest not the root, but the root thee. 19 Thou wilt say then, The branches were broken off, that I might be ingrafted. 20 Well; because of unbelief they were broken off, and thou standest by faith. Be not high-minded, but fear: 21 For if God spared not the natural branches, take heed lest he also spare not thee. 22 Behold therefore the goodness and severity of God: on them who fell, severity; but towards thee, goodness, if thou shalt continue in his goodness: otherwise thou also shalt be cut off. 23 And they also, if they abide not still in unbelief, shall be ingrafted: for God is able to ingraft them again. 24 For if thou wast cut out of the olive-tree which is wild by nature, and wast ingrafted contrary to nature into a good olive-tree; how much more shall these, which are the natural branches , be grafted into their own olive-tree? 25 For I would not, brethren, that ye should be ignorant of this mystery, (lest ye should be wise in your own conceits) that blindness in part hath happened to Israel, until the fullness of the Gentiles shall be come in. 26 And so all Israel shall be saved: as it is written, There shall come out of Sion the Deliverer, and shall turn away ungodliness from Jacob: 27 For this is my covenant to them, when I shall take away their sins. 28 As concerning the gospel, they are enemies for your sakes: but as concerning the election, they are beloved for the father's sakes. 29 For the gifts and calling of God are without repentance. 30 For as ye in times past have not believed God, yet have now obtained mercy through their unbelief; 31 Even so have these also now not believed, that through your mercy they also may obtain mercy. 32 For God hath concluded them all in unbelief, that he might have mercy upon all. 33 O the depth of the riches both of the wisdom and knowledge of God! how unsearchable are his judgments, and his ways past finding out! 34 For who hath known the mind of the Lord? or who hath been his counselor? 35 Or who hath first given to him, and it shall be recompensed to him again? 36 For from him, and by him, and to him are all things: to whom be glory for ever. Amen.

12

1 I beseech you therefore, brethren, by the mercies of God, that ye present your bodies a living sacrifice, holy, acceptable to God, which is your reasonable service. 2 And be not conformed to this world: but be ye transformed by the renewing of your mind, that ye may prove what is that good and acceptable, and perfect will of God. 3 For through the grace given to me, I say, to every man that is among you, not to think of himself more highly than he ought to think; but to think soberly, according as God hath dealt to every man the measure of faith. 4 For as we have many members in one body, and all members have not the same office: 5 So we, being many, are one body in Christ, and every one members one of another. 6 Having then gifts differing according to the grace that is given to us, whether prophecy, let us prophesy according to the proportion of faith; 7 Or ministry, let us wait on our ministering: or he that teacheth, on teaching: 8 Or he that exhorteth, on exhortation: he that giveth, let him do it with simplicity; he that ruleth, with diligence; he that showeth mercy, with cheerfulness. 9 Let love be without hypocrisy. Abhor that which is evil; cleave to that which is good. 10 Be kindly affectioned one to another with brotherly love; in honor preferring one another; 11 Not slothful in business; fervent in spirit; serving the Lord; 12 Rejoicing in hope; patient in tribulation; continuing earnest in prayer; 13 Distributing to the necessity of saints; given to hospitality. 14 Bless them who persecute you; bless, and curse not. 15 Rejoice with them that rejoice, and weep with them that weep. 16 Be of the same mind one towards another. Mind not high things, but condescend to men of low estate. Be not wise in your own conceits. 17 Recompense to no man evil for evil. Provide things honest in the sight of all men. 18 If it is possible, as much as lieth in you, live peaceably with all men. 19 Dearly beloved, avenge not yourselves, but rather give place to wrath: for it is written, Vengeance is mine; I will repay, saith the Lord. 20 Therefore if thy enemy hungereth, feed him; if he thirsteth, give him drink: for in so doing thou shalt heap coals of fire on his head. 21 Be not overcome by evil, but overcome evil with good.

13

1 Let every soul be subject to the higher powers. For there is no power but from God: the powers that are, are ordained by God. 2 Whoever therefore resisteth the power, resisteth the ordinance of God: and they that resist shall receive to themselves damnation. 3 For rulers are not a terror to good works, but to the evil. Wilt thou then not be afraid of the power; do that which is good, and thou shalt have praise from the same: 4 For he is the minister of God to thee for good. But if thou doest that which is evil, be afraid; for he beareth not the sword in vain: for he is the minister of God, an avenger to execute wrath upon him that doeth evil. 5 Wherefore ye must needs be subject, not only for wrath, but also for conscience sake. 6 For, for this cause ye pay tribute also: for they are God's ministers, attending continually upon this very thing. 7 Render therefore to all their dues: tribute to whom tribute is due ; custom to whom custom; fear to whom fear; honor to whom honor. 8 Owe no man any thing, but to love one another: for he that loveth another hath fulfilled the law. 9 For this, Thou shalt not commit adultery, Thou shalt not kill, Thou shalt not steal, Thou shalt not bear false witness, Thou shalt not covet; and if there is any other commandment, it is briefly comprehended in this saying, namely, Thou shalt love thy neighbor as thyself. 10 Love worketh no ill to one's neighbor: therefore love is the fulfilling of the law. 11 And this, knowing the time, that now it is high time to awake out of sleep: for now is our salvation nearer than when we believed. 12 The night is far spent, the day is at hand: let us therefore cast off the works of darkness, and let us put on the armor of light. 13 Let us walk honestly, as in the day; not in rioting and drunkenness, not in chambering and wantonness, not in strife and envying. 14 But put ye on the Lord Jesus Christ, and make not provision for the lusts of flesh.

14

1 Him that is weak in the faith receive ye, but not to doubtful disputations. 2 For one believeth that he may eat all things: another, who is weak, eateth herbs. 3 Let not him that eateth, despise him that eateth not; and let not him who eateth not, judge him that eateth: for God hath received him. 4 Who art thou that judgest another man's servant? to his own master he standeth or falleth: and he shall be held up: for God is able to make him stand. 5 One man esteemeth one day above another: another esteemeth every day alike . Let every man be fully persuaded in his own mind. 6 He that regardeth the day, regardeth it to the Lord: and he that regardeth not the day, to the Lord he doth not regard it . He that eateth, eateth to the Lord, for he giveth God thanks; and he that eateth not, to the Lord he eateth not, and giveth God thanks. 7 For none of us liveth to himself, and no man dieth to himself. 8 For whether we live, we live to the Lord; and whether we die, we die to the Lord: whether we live therefore, or die, we are the Lord's. 9 For to this end Christ both died, and rose, and revived, that he might be Lord both of the dead and the living. 10 But why dost thou judge thy brother? or why dost thou set at naught thy brother? for we shall all stand before the judgment-seat of Christ. 11 For it is written, As I live, saith the Lord, every knee shall bow to me, and every tongue shall confess to God. 12 So then every one of us shall give account of himself to God. 13 Let us not therefore judge one another any more: but judge this rather, that no man put a stumbling-block, or an occasion to fall in his brother's way. 14 I know, and am persuaded by the Lord Jesus, that there is nothing unclean by itself: but to him that esteemeth any thing to be unclean, to him it is unclean. 15 But if thy brother is grieved with thy food, now walkest thou not charitably. Destroy not him with thy food, for whom Christ died. 16 Let not then your good be evil spoken of: 17 For the kingdom of God is not food and drink, but righteousness, and peace, and joy in the Holy Spirit. 18 For he that in these things serveth Christ, is acceptable to God, and approved by men. 19 Let us therefore follow after the things which make for peace, and things with which one may edify another. 20 For the sake of food, destroy not the work of God. All things indeed are pure; but it is evil for that man who eateth with offense. 21 It is good neither to eat flesh, nor to drink wine, nor any thing by which thy brother stumbleth, or is offended, or is made weak. 22 Hast thou faith? have it to thyself before God. Happy is he that condemneth not himself in that thing which he alloweth. 23 And he that doubteth is damned if he eateth, because he eateth not from faith: for whatever is not from faith is sin.

15

1 We then that are strong ought to bear the infirmities of the weak, and not to please ourselves. 2 Let every one of us please his neighbor for his good to edification. 3 For even Christ pleased not himself; but, as it is written, The reproaches of them that reproached thee fell on me. 4 For whatever things were written formerly, were written for our learning, that we through patience and comfort of the scriptures might have hope. 5 Now the God of patience and consolation grant you to be like-minded one towards another according to Christ Jesus: 6 That ye may with one mind and one mouth glorify God, even the Father of our Lord Jesus Christ. 7 Wherefore receive ye one another, as Christ also received us to the glory of God. 8 Now I say that Jesus Christ was a minister of the circumcision for the truth of God, to confirm the promises made to the fathers: 9 And that the Gentiles might glorify God for his mercy; as it is written, For this cause I will confess to thee among the Gentiles, and sing to thy name. 10 And again he saith, Rejoice, ye Gentiles, with his people. 11 And again, Praise the Lord, all ye Gentiles; and laud him, all ye people. 12 And again Isaiah saith, There shall be a root of Jesse, and he that shall rise to reign over the Gentiles; in him shall the Gentiles trust. 13 Now the God of hope fill you with all joy and peace in believing, that ye may abound in hope, through the power of the Holy Spirit. 14 And I myself also am persuaded concerning you, my brethren, that ye also are full of goodness, filled with all knowledge, able also to admonish one another. 15 Nevertheless, brethren, I have written the more boldly to you in some sort, as putting you in mind, because of the grace that is given to me from God. 16 That I should be the minister of Jesus Christ to the Gentiles, ministering the gospel of God, that the offering up of the Gentiles might be acceptable, being sanctified by the Holy Spirit. 17 I have therefore cause for glorying through Jesus Christ, in those things which pertain to God. 18 For I will not dare to speak of any of those things which Christ hath not wrought by me, to make the Gentiles obedient, by word and deed, 19 Through mighty signs and wonders, by the power of the Spirit of God; so that from Jerusalem, and around to Illyricum, I have fully preached the gospel of Christ. 20 And so have I strived to preach the gospel, not where Christ was named, lest I should build upon another man's foundation: 21 But as it is written, They shall see to whom he was not spoken of: and they that have not heard shall understand. 22 For which cause also I have been much hindered from coming to you. 23 But now having no more place in these parts, and having a great desire these many years to come to you; 24 Whenever I take my journey into Spain, I will come to you: for I trust to see you in my journey, and to be brought on my way thitherward by you, if first I shall be somewhat filled with your company . 25 But now I go to Jerusalem to minister to the saints. 26 For it hath pleased them of Macedonia and Achaia to make a certain contribution for the poor of the saints who are at Jerusalem. 27 It hath pleased them verily; and their debtors they are. For if the Gentiles have been made partakers of their spiritual things, their duty is also to minister to them in carnal things. 28 When therefore I have performed this, and have sealed to them this fruit, I will go by you into Spain. 29 And I am sure that when I come to you, I shall come in the fullness of the blessing of the gospel of Christ. 30 Now I beseech you, brethren, for the Lord Jesus Christ's sake, and for the love of the Spirit, that ye strive together with me in your prayers to God for me; 31 That I may be delivered from them in Judea who do not believe; and that my service which I have for Jerusalem, may be acceptable to the saints; 32 That I may come to you with joy by the will of God, and may with you be refreshed. 33 Now the God of peace be with you all. Amen.

16

1 I commend to you Phebe our sister, who is a servant of the church which is at Cenchrea: 2 That ye receive her in the Lord, as it becometh saints, and that ye assist her in whatever business she hath need of you: for she hath been a succorer of many, and of myself also. 3 Greet Priscilla and Aquila my helpers in Christ Jesus: 4 Who have for my life laid down their own necks: to whom not only I give thanks, but also all the churches of the Gentiles. 5 Likewise greet the church that is in their house. Salute my well-beloved Epenetus, who is the first-fruits of Achaia to Christ. 6 Greet Mary, who bestowed much labor on us. 7 Salute Andronicus and Junia my kinsmen, and my fellow-prisoners, who are of note among the apostles, who also were in Christ before me. 8 Greet Amplias my beloved in the Lord. 9 Salute Urbane, our helper in Christ, and Stachys my beloved. 10 Salute Apelles approved in Christ. Salute them who are of Aristobulus' household . 11 Salute Herodion my kinsman. Greet them that are of the household of Narcissus, who are in the Lord. 12 Salute Tryphena and Tryphosa, who labor in the Lord. Salute the beloved Persis, who labored much in the Lord. 13 Salute Rufus chosen in the Lord, and his mother and mine. 14 Salute Asyncritus, Phlegon, Hermas, Patrobas, Hermes, and the brethren who are with them. 15 Salute Philologus, and Julia, Nereus, and his sister, and Olympas, and all the saints who are with them. 16 Salute one another with a holy kiss. The churches of Christ salute you. 17 Now I beseech you, brethren, mark them who cause divisions and offenses, contrary to the doctrine which ye have learned; and avoid them. 18 For they that are such serve not our Lord Jesus Christ, but their own belly; and by good words and fair speeches deceive the hearts of the simple. 19 For your obedience is come abroad to all men . I am glad therefore on your behalf: but yet I would have you wise to that which is good, and simple concerning evil. 20 And the God of peace will soon bruise Satan under your feet. The grace of our Lord Jesus Christ be with you. Amen. 21 Timothy my work-fellow, and Lucius, and Jason, and Sosipater my kinsmen, salute you. 22 I Tertius, who wrote this epistle, salute you in the Lord. 23 Gaius my host, and of the whole church, saluteth you. Erastus the chamberlain of the city saluteth you, and Quartus a brother. 24 The grace of our Lord Jesus Christ be with you all. Amen. 25 Now to him that is able to establish you according to my gospel, and the preaching of Jesus Christ, according to the revelation of the mystery, which hath been kept secret since the world began, 26 But now is made manifest, and by the scriptures of the prophets, according to the commandment of the everlasting God, made known to all nations for the obedience of faith: 27 To God the only wise, be glory through Jesus Christ for ever. Amen.